<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A general discourse of simony by Ja. Metford.</title>
            <author>Metford, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1780</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12774168</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12774168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50760)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 699:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A general discourse of simony by Ja. Metford.</title>
                  <author>Metford, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 167, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Lawson ..., and sold by R. Chiswell ..., and T. Sawbridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Simony.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93734:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93734:1"/>
            <p>A General DISCOURSE OF SIMONY.</p>
            <p>BY JA. METFORD, Rector of <hi>Baſſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in
<hi>Lincolnſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi aurum placet, ibi &amp; vitium.</p>
               <bibl>Greg. l. <hi>9.</hi> ep. <hi>40.</hi> Iſicio Epd. Hieros.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for JOSEPH LAWSON, in the <hi>Baile</hi> of <hi>Lincoln, Bookſeller;</hi> and ſold by R. CHISWEL, at the
<hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s-<hi>Church-Yard,</hi> and T. SAWBRIDGE at the three <hi>Flower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de-luces</hi> in
<hi>Little-Brittain.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93734:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93734:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God THOMAS Lord Biſhop of
<hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur inceſſant pains, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere endeavours both by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Elaborate Tractates, do ſufficiently diſcover you a true Engliſh Prelate, and able Patron of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cauſe. And your great vigilance and integrity in your high and holy Calling, hath given you a juſt eſteem in the hearts of good men; and wrought a belief in your Dioceſs, that things are well done if they gain your approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which forces me to give you the trouble of hearing, that about a month before the death of the Learned and truly Reverend Dr. <hi>Michael
<pb facs="tcp:93734:3"/>Honywood</hi> late Dean, and now the juſt grief of the Church of <hi>Lincoln;</hi> he was pleaſed to inform me with ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment of the too great Progreſs of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in this Nation; bewailing the fatal Conſequences of it to the Church, and commanding me to ſay ſomething (if poſſible) to ſtop its growth. To which I anſwer'd, but with two ſad aſſurance of truth, that I had travail'd leſs in the ſearch of that Subject than in moſt others that a Divine is obliged to know. And beſides was ſo valetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, that in few days time I uſed to hear ſome ſoft Footſteps of approaching Mortality: which (though he knew to be true) yet his warm heart would not retreat, but permitted me only to be a little ſhorter. Two days after, I was adviſed to travail about ſixty miles, to a Spaw for health; which I did: and at my return, was ſaluted with the moſt unwelcome News of the Deans death: ſo that I was forced to
<pb facs="tcp:93734:3"/>ſhare in the common ſorrow. Though (not to diſſemble) 'twas ſome eaſe to me, that I was delivered from my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to him. But about five weeks ſince, a common Friend, conſcious to my Obligation, demanded an account of Simony; as promiſed to the Decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: I anſwer'd, that death had cut the Band of that Promiſe: He replied, that the Deans life or death was no condition of it; and the reaſon of performing, was the ſame now as before. I ſubmitted; and do now humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent theſe weak Lines to your Lordſhips view; deſiring (if they are thought of any uſe) they may paſs your Dioceſs under your Protection. I know the deſign is uſeful, though the ill handling may offend. If your Lordſhip think them uſeleſs, be pleaſed to receive them to that ſure Sanctuary of Secreſy and Silence; which will be moſt ſafe for</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Baſs.
<date>Dec. 2d. <hi>1681.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt dutiful Petitioner and Servant,</hi> Ja. Metford.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:93734:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93734:4"/>
            <head>A General DISCOURSE OF SIMONY.</head>
            <p>COnſidering the ſmart Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, lately made by a very worthy Gentleman on a Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice but too common in this degenerate age, of giving Bonds to Patrons for the Reſignation of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice at their pleaſure: and noting ſome Commotion in his mind, I aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf, ſo ſtrong and ſound a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, could not be rapt away by his well-commanded paſſions; but upon the ſharpeſt Spur of Provocation: and therefore ſuſpected ſome ſecret venom, in that which ſeemed to once thinking men, a harmleſs pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. The deeper I did dig into it, the ſtronger and ranker the ſtench ſum'd up; which at length convinc'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93734:5"/>me, that no leſs than a bottomleſs Pit of Miſchief lay under it; which I hope to diſcover, by ſhewing both the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Simony in general, and what ſhare theſe Bonds for Reſignation bear, in that weighty guilt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simony</hi> is ſo called from <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> that famous <hi>Samaritan</hi> born at <hi>Gitton,</hi> mentioned in <hi>Acts</hi>
8, who came to <hi>Rome</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> ſays
<hi>Euſebius</hi>) where he was worſhipped in an Image (ſays <hi>Juſt. Martyr</hi>) between the two Bridges of <hi>Tyber,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> apology. <hi>1.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. L. <hi>1.</hi> adv. har. <hi>10.</hi> Ephiph. adv. haer. to. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> haer. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; Aug. ad Quod. haer.
<hi>1.</hi>
               </note> with this Inſcription, <hi>Simoni Sancto Deo;</hi> yea the
<hi>Samaritans</hi> and many others alſo, adored him ſaith
<hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus.</hi> The occaſion of his giving the name to <hi>Simony,</hi> is ſet down <hi>Act.</hi> 8.20. <hi>A Petro Spiritus Sancti gratiam mereari volebat, unde vitio nomen dedit,</hi> (ſays <hi>Aquinas</hi>) and many others. Not but that the crime had got footing in the World long before, and was known to the <hi>Jews</hi> by the name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and by the
<hi>Arabians</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Talm,</hi> ſays
<hi>Schindler;</hi> and both from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fraudavit expilavit.</hi> The <hi>Greeks</hi> knew it by the Name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And the <hi>Latines</hi> by the word <hi>Ambitus.</hi> Which I note, to ſhew
'tis a moral
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93734:5"/>evil, and was troubleſome to all Nations and Religions. But this bold Chapmans offer, purchaſed not the grace of God, but diſgrace of turning his name into ſin, by which he will be juſtly infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous to the laſt gaſp of time.</p>
            <p>The nature of this ſin is well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, by them that call it <hi>Studio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam voluntatem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Panorm. &amp; nemo extra Aquinas Sa. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nundinandi aliquid ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituale, aut ſpirituali annexum;</hi> for 'tis a deſire, and endeavour to make Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of things ſacred. Some add <hi>inſecuto opere,</hi> but the purpoſe of the heart is <hi>Simony,</hi> though we can't ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh it, as
<hi>Simon</hi> could not. And 'tis the heart <hi>Peter</hi> blames. <hi>Thy heart is not right in the ſight of God.</hi> Acts 8.21. And again,
<hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>if perhaps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee.</hi> 'Tis true, <hi>in foro ſoli,</hi> ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Act muſt appear; but <hi>in foro poli,</hi> the deſign though fruſtrate, is the crime.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 3.2.</note> 'Tis a crime that <hi>Stella</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for the teeming womb of infinite Evils, that follow; contrived by
<hi>Herod,</hi> to render the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, making the Prieſthood annual; as <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.49. ſhews, <hi>that</hi> Caiaphas <hi>was High-Prieſt for that year only: and</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as <hi>ſoon after,</hi> as
<hi>Acts</hi> 4.6. evidently
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93734:6"/>diſcovers. <hi>Which,</hi> ſays he,
<hi>forc't the High Prieſt to oppreſs the People, for the raiſing ſuch Simoniacal Sums.</hi> And unworthy men, thereby get into the greateſt truſts in the Church; which made the times, <hi>Calamitoſa &amp; Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa,</hi> as alſo it doth ours.</p>
            <p>But for the better diſplaying this growing ſin, we ſhall conſider 1. Its ſpecies, buying and ſelling things ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred. 2. The things bought and ſold. 3. The means by which 'tis done.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Species, buying and ſelling, which being Relative Acts, will in their own nature, be alike lawful or unlawful: though accidental circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, may make them more evil to one than another. Like
<hi>Judas</hi> ſelling, and the <hi>Jews purchaſing</hi> the Son of God. The <hi>Scotch</hi> ſelling, and the Rumpers buying <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt. Or <hi>Didius Julianus</hi> buying and the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torian Cohorts</hi> ſelling, the ſacred Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire. Or <hi>Herod</hi>'s ſelling and
<hi>Caiaphas</hi> buying the holy Order of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> High-prieſt.
'Tis hard to ſay which is moſt tainted with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Avarice, ſince both their breaths ſmell ſo exceeding earthy. 'Tis but
<hi>Cretenſis cum Aegineta,</hi> two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93734:6"/>Knaves well met: poyſoning each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the Toad doth the Spider. They both labour under the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe of greedy deſire; having Souls black as Hell by thoſe deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Like
<hi>Attabus</hi> and <hi>Numeneus,</hi> that puzl'd <hi>Apollo</hi> himſelf to determine which was worſt: being both Loaves of the ſame ſowre Batch: Viols in uniſon, wound up by the dexterity of the Devil. He that thinks himſelf beſt, is but the greater Deceiver, and the weaker head. They broke both the ſame laws of God and Man, from the ſame principles of ſordid cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs; to the ſame end to enrich themſelves on the Spoils of Religion. Averring both the ſame damnable poſitions,<note place="margin">Quaſi nulium ſit peccatum majus quam nummis carere. Eſpenc. in Tit. c. <hi>1.</hi> Credidit ingens pauperiem viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Hor. ſerm.
<hi>2.</hi> ſat <hi>3.</hi> nunc ſit barbaries gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis habere nihil. Latro eſt qui au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ex religione ſectatur. Hieron.</note> * that Money is the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary qualification for the Miniſtry. And that Poverty is the beſt evidence of a ſcandalous and inſufficient Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. They may differ in their Coat, but wear both the ſame Cloak of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſy to cover their Knavery.</p>
            <p>Can a greedy Patron (ſhall I call him, or <hi>Latron</hi>) excuſe himſelf from Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, whilſt he fills his bottomleſs Bag out of the Church Revenue? Can he fancy himſelf not perfidious, that being
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93734:7"/>but a<note n="*" place="margin">Depoſita pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, ſays Crig. 2r. <hi>31</hi> in Math. Tert apolog. c.
<hi>39.</hi>
               </note> Truſtee for the Churches Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, treacherouſly converts it to its own uſe. What did <hi>Ananias</hi> do more, than retain part of what was devoted to Gods ſervice? O the divine charms of Money, that can ſo far blind men, as not to diſcover ſins of the greateſt ſize! Can they hope to avoid the ſhame and puniſhment of thie very, that ſo audaciouſly rob God? <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8. Or can their witty guilt find out any fair gloſs to elude the teeth of the Text from biting them. Muſt God be ſorc't to pay tribute to their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Deities? Will men take Heaven to ſatisfie their unſatiable appetites? 'Tis ſtrangely ſawcy to lick their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in God's Broath. <hi>Major Nummi quam Numinis ardor.</hi> They ſhew more devotion to the Golden Calf, than the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> It ſeems they are of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi>'s mind, that Gold ſmells well, though pickt out of Gods pocket. Can Cuſtom preſcribe againſt honeſty? Can wrong by<note n="*" place="margin">Quicquid multis peccatur multum eſt. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> multitudes of ſinners be bound to right? Is Robbery the more lawful, becauſe committed on the Church?<note n="*" place="margin">Nihil ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuationem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licti numerus impudens valere conſuevit. Cyp l.
<hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>26.</hi> ſed pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor &amp; modeſtia
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Or the leſs criminal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many practiſe it? Can they gueſs themſelves good men that won't
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93734:7"/>do their duty without Bribery? If it be not the Churches Right, why do they give them any? If it be, why do they detain any? He that invades ſome part of the Church Revenues, would all, but for ſhame of the World; having as true a right to all, as to any part of it. What defence will it be at the laſt day, to ſay we are Gentlemen, and have robb'd none but God; and defrauded none but the Church; nor been diſhoneſt to any but the Miniſtry? God will reward them, for giving his Prophets a Cup of cold Water: bur ſo will he too, for cheating them of half their maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And certainly, <hi>Cicero</hi> is right, that thoſe men are the greateſt plagues of the Common-wealth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. de off.</hi> 1.1.</note> that doing evil, <hi>Id agunt, ut boni viri eſſe vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur.</hi> They expect to be eſteemed honeſt in the fowleſt Acts.</p>
            <p>Now for the Buyer; we have the leſs to ſay againſt him, becauſe his Act is partly involuntary: yet there could be no Sellers, were there no Buyers, for both are neceſſary to make up a Market. At beſt, he doth evil, that good may come of it; and ſticks not at bribery, to make way for a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93734:8"/>
               <hi>quocunque modo rem.</hi> He plucks the Devils Office out of his hand, and turns Tempter of his Patron; and prefers the call of Gold, before the call of God. He declares himſelf without merits, ſeeing his money is to anſwer all things, and ſeems bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purchaſer than Preacher. If (with <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) he hath not a golden Mouth, he hath a golden Hand. If he can't enter as <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> yet can like
<hi>Simon Magus,</hi> with Letters Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial in Golden Characters: and then ſays one, He is in the Church, <hi>permiſſione non voluntate Dei;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stell. In Luc. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, but againſt the will of God. And by this he diſcovers his aim, to be more at the benefice, than office of a Divine; which may be had in a more populous, and leſs profitable place, at a much lower Rate. <hi>Non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit Dominus, ſed ipſi ſe conſtituerunt,</hi> ſays he. 'Tis not the Saints Bell of divine Invitation, rings them in, as Bees are courted to their Hives; but 'tis the tinkling of their Silver: which ſhews they go in their own errand, not Gods. And how can men chooſe but ſuſpect them, for bad Servants; that are forc'd to hire their Services.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93734:8"/>Nay they are rather Slaves than Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in the houſe of God; that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and continue ſhackled in Manacles and Chains of Bonds, Contracts, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, Limitations, and a thouſand other Inventions of darkneſs. Theſe Links of Iron gall them at every nod of the Patrons diſpleaſure; which they allways fear, more than the ſaddeſt preſages of a guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>That the Purchaſer may know his condition,<note place="margin">Cornelius vim paſſus eſt ut E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopatum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actus exciperet. Cyp. to. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. <hi>52.</hi> St. Aug. wept when elected to the Biſhoprick of Hippo. Poſſidon. in vita Auguſt. Greg. Thauma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgus fled into the Wilderneſs to avoid a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick. v. Nyſſen in vita Ireg.</note> let him read his Indictment before the great and dreadful Aſſizes come: that he may the better fit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for his Anſwer. He ſtands in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted for filthy Avarice, the ground of his ſacrilegious purchaſe. For de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate audaciouſneſs, in thinking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf worthy the weightieſt truſt in the Church. While St. <hi>Hierom</hi> calls it,
<hi>Onus Angelicis humeris formidandum. Jonah</hi> in a great fright fled from it. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.6. Cryed out, <hi>ah Lord I am a, Child, I cannot ſpeak.</hi> And many of the primitive Fathers, had almoſt the skin of their Modeſty pluckt over their ears, before they could be induced to come near the holy Veſtments. Nor are his Treaſons leſs, conſpiring with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93734:9"/>his Patron, againſt the liberty of God's Church, and pawning his Living on it, to preach what hereſy his Patron ſhall require. He commits Burglary on the Church of God, breaking open her door with a Golden Cramp; and forces the holy Spouſe of Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her will; and values the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable grace of God at the rate of worldly pelf. Good God! what Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant is his heart made of? how ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate is his conſcience, that groans not under theſe heavy weights of ſin? Venturing boldly on that villany, that all good mens hearts, in former ages, trembled at. I muſt leave him to prepare his anſwer at that great Tribunal; or elſe for ſlighting this timely notice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us conſider the things bought and ſold; which to ſhew them to be Simony, muſt be the gifts of the holy Ghoſt; both ordinary, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, real or ſo accepted. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is ſacriledge to take away from the Church, is Simony to buy or ſell in the Church. But we may reduce them (though ſcarcely numerable) to the enſuing heads. 1. Buying and Selling, the inſtituted means, by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93734:9"/>which the holy Spirit is attained; as Prayers, whoſe Evangelical worth cannot be valued, and if purchaſed are worth nothing. 'Tis the worſt kind of Uſury to take ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> for our Prayers, or elſe not to let them out; I confeſs I know no Church that hires out Prayers, or Maſſes at 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> a piece, but the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which excells in this kind of Alchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, turning all Materials into Gold. In our Church 'tis decreed by <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in a Provincial Synod, holden about the year 1250, That no Maſſes be ſold, nor any thing given or taken, for
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia</hi> or <hi>Tricennalia Miſſarum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. vetu sl. tit. <hi>2.</hi> cap. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea venal.</note> as <hi>Lind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> ſhews us: which were Maſſes for a year, or 30 Maſſes, if the word be rightly written, and not <hi>triennalia</hi> as ſome ſuſpect; which would be Maſſes for three years. So too, for Sacraments largely or ſtrictly taken: ſince they were the Golden Veſſels; in which grace was conveyed; the Church ever held them invaluable: knowing that it would have beggered all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of Heaven fully to compenſate for any one of them. Hence
<hi>Stephen Langton,</hi> in the firſt Council of <hi>Oxford,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93734:10"/>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1222 decreed,<note place="margin">Provin. ib. cap. firmiter Inhibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be required for Baptiſm, <hi>Chriſme, vel aliquod Eccleſiaſticum Sacramentum.</hi> And ſo is the Legantine Conſtitution of <hi>Otho, A. D.</hi> 1236. <hi>tit.</hi> 4. <hi>cap. auditu horribili,</hi> &amp;c. concerning Confeſſion or Penance, as they call it, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain confirmed, by <hi>Othobon</hi> another Legate, <hi>A. D.</hi> 1268, with ſtricter In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions; as appears <hi>tit.</hi> 2. <hi>cap. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam caeca poteſt as</hi> &amp;c, where he ſpeaks not of Confeſſion, and
<hi>Chriſme</hi> only, but adds, <hi>Et qui alia quaelibet Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, interventu Pecuniae conferunt, ſitales invenerint (ſc. Archidiaconi) eos tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Simoniacos puniant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To Buy or Sell the Offices of the Church, inſtituted by the holy Ghoſt, which (tis very probable) was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of <hi>Simon Magus:</hi> to have been an Apoſtle, or at leaſt a Biſhop in the Church. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Apoſtles, or Apoſtolical men only, was the power of miracles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on others: and therefore it muſt be their authority that he would pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe: and 'tis the authority denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates the perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He deſires to do it by laying on of hands, which was an act of Office
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93734:10"/>power, in Ordination, Confirmation, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It ſeems by St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s anſwer, he ſo underſtood him: for he ſays, <hi>Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this matter,</hi> or in this word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.21. As if he had told him, Thou haſt no ſhare in the Apoſtleſhip, nor Call to be in the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: or to publiſh this word of God, which is confirmed with theſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The powring out theſe gifts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men, was but an extraordinary Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to the Miniſtry. Which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, 1. In that it was not given to all that were baptized; for then <hi>Simon</hi> had ſhared without Money. 2. Nor can men give any Reaſon, for theſe gifts of tongue, unleſs they were to be uſed in the Miniſtry. Since the faith might be confirmed, as well to their own minds, internally by the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the holy Ghoſt. 3. Nor were theſe gifts given to any Woman that we read of, and therefore were not neceſſary to confirmation of the faith, nor ſanctification in the faith internally: for that they needed as well as men; but that Sex was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93734:11"/>the Miniſtry. Nor do we want concurrent judgments in this point, both ancient and modern; but that is beſide my deſign to proſecute. Only I obſerve <hi>Cornel. a Lapide</hi> ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular, as to affirm, that he deſired the Biſhoprick of
<hi>Samaria:</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Lap. in loc. l. <hi>4.</hi> de notis eccl. c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is very certain, he offered Money for the Epiſcopal authority. <hi>Conſtat</hi> Simon
<hi>Epiſcopalem authoritatem ambiviſſe, &amp; durâ pecuniâ emere volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the buying or ſelling any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, inſtituted by the holy Ghoſt, in the Church, was adjudged Symony, appears by <hi>Stratford,</hi> who decrees <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1342 (as <hi>Sharrock</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms out of a Mss. in <hi>Bodley</hi>'s Library) <hi>nec decet epiſcopum manus impoſitionem vendere: nec miniſtrum, calamum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nundare:</hi> And accordingly 'tis deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the Council, that from thence-forward, the whole charges of every diſtinct Ordination, and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Orders</hi> ſealed in
<hi>England,</hi> ſhould coſt the Ordained but 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> and all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, for ſetling the Clerk in his benefice, but 12
<hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> vid. Lindwood, l.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 22. <hi>de cenſibus. Cap. Saeva &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerabilis,</hi> &amp;c. And if the Candidate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93734:11"/>for Orders, proved Simoniacal, <hi>ad quoſcunque Ordines ne praeſumat accedere,</hi> ſays <hi>Walter Reynold</hi> Arch. <hi>Cant.</hi> in the ſecond Council at <hi>Oxford, A. D.</hi> 1322. And if he could get into Orders un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcover'd, yet is he declared by <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> Arch. <hi>Cant.</hi> Irregular; and he compares him with Homicides, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries; and forbid to diſpenſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Myſteries till he have made full ſatisfaction to the Church.<note place="margin">Prov. Vet. l. <hi>1.</hi> tit. <hi>4.</hi> de Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandis.</note> Thus too, it was managed under Pope <hi>Greg.</hi> M. in the reign of
<hi>Mauritius,</hi> who follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſacred Rules of his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, decreed, <hi>nihil unquam de ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus accipiendum:</hi> no nor for the Pall, nor any Papers: and gives this reaſon for it,<note place="margin">Greg in Synodo Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Quia non decet aut Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopos ſuam manum, aut Miniſtros, vel Notarios, ſuam vocem vel calamum ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi> And indeed it looks a little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth, that a man ſhould purchaſe leave to ſerve God; and hire the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of being Chriſt's Meſſenger. And that the Ordainer ſhould ſell the Spirit, as <hi>Judas</hi> did the Son; and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained like curſed <hi>Jews,</hi> ſhould be the Buyers. <hi>Midas</hi> Fable is but too ſinfully verified in ſuch men, ſince their Touch turns all to Gold. Doubtleſs they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93734:12"/>would not give the droppings of their Noſe, whoſe very breath coſt men ſo dear. But we may well deſiſt, this Crime being more rare, than Wolves in <hi>England,</hi> ſince the Reformation: and ſeems to be a native plant of <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> flouriſhing no where ſo well, as where the Pope hath ſet his foot. Of which the ſelect Cardinals make a moſt ſad Complaint to <hi>Paul</hi> 3
<abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they diſcovered <hi>in Eligentibus cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatem, in Electis inſulſitatem, in utris<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Simoniacam perverſitatem.</hi> The ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny at <hi>Rome</hi> who is fit for Orders, is made in the Pocket, not in the Pate: nor do they examine his Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but his Compenſation: 'tis no matter if he be no able Scholar, ſo he be an able man. Nay a Child will ſerve the turn, for the beſt Biſhoprick in <hi>France,</hi> if he ſend a golden Orator to procure it. The Pope once told his Cardinals upon preferring a mean man: if the King of
<hi>England</hi> had deſired his Horſe to be made a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, he would not have refuſed him; for the King had commended him, not in a long Teſtimonial, but in a round Summ, which with them is the Total of all perfection.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93734:12"/>
            <p>The <hi>Centum Gravamina,</hi> complains, <hi>indoctis, agaſonibus, ſtabulariis, dantur beneficia.</hi> Hoſtlers and Grooms were well enough letered, if well enough lined. <hi>Picus</hi> Count
<hi>Mirandula</hi> tells Pope <hi>Leo</hi> 10th to his face and his Council in
<hi>Lateran,</hi> That they gave Church Livings, <hi>lenonibus, &amp; Catami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> to Pimps and Panders, <hi>Ganymedes,</hi> and what not for Money? Yea, the very Apoſtolical Legates (as they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natically Cant) in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> confeſs men were ordained in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, that had nothing Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical but their Copes and Caſſocks. What
<hi>Nauclerus</hi> confeſſes of <hi>Boniface</hi> 9th time, <hi>Curiam Romanam labe Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacâ infamem eſſe;</hi> was true long before,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.</note> and it may ſerve for their Character ever ſince. Let the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Clergy rejoyce that they live out of the reach of theſe <hi>Tarpeian</hi> Harpies: which made our Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors purſes tremble at every ſcreich of the impure Bird.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And to buy and ſell the Manſions of the holy Ghoſt. Here the Paſtors and Teachers, are ſet over the Church by the holy Ghoſt; the Church is the Temple of Chriſt, and the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93734:13"/>ſpiritual. Now in buying and ſelling theſe, Gods people are bought and ſold like Slaves, in this profane Market. The Souls of Men, once va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued ſo high, as to be the purchaſe of our Saviours precious bloud, are now ſold for a ſacrilegious Bribe. O unheard of impudence! That makes thoſe invaluable Jewels, the matter of vain Mens traffick.<note place="margin">Epiph.</note> This was ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the ancient of piety, that they judg'd the very opinion of its lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a haereſy:<note place="margin">Aug. ad quod vult d. de haer. in principio. Greg. l. <hi>3.</hi> ep. <hi>13.</hi> &amp; paſſim.</note> and ſo doth
<hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, St. <hi>Auguſtine, Greg. Mag.</hi> and ſo <hi>de Langius,</hi> and <hi>Schaffnaburgenſis,</hi> in their Chronicles all along. Yea ſo hateful hath it been to the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Community, that an Oath hath been adminiſtred againſt it for many ages. And for <hi>England</hi> in particular, 'tis decreed in <hi>Conc. primo Oxon.</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſaid Archbiſhop, <hi>Stephen Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> That all Biſhops ſhould impoſe an Oath on any ſuſpected perſon: that <hi>nec promiſerit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2</hi> tit. <hi>6.</hi> de jureju.</note> 
                  <hi>nec dederit aliquod praeſentanti; nec aliquam propter hoc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ierit pactionem.</hi> I confeſs this Oath is very large, but it ſhews the piety of thoſe times, would not endure any kind of bargain about theſe things.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93734:13"/>And ſo watchful was this Council o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Biſhops, that they decreed in Collation of a Praebend, <hi>Commendum</hi> or the like, the Biſhop ſhould receive nothing for Inſtitution or Miſſion; no nor <hi>vel chartâ ſuper hoc faciendâ.</hi> Nor might he ſuffer his Officials or Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, to extort any thing: becauſe (ſays the gloſs) 'twas adjudged Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony ſo to do.<note place="margin">V. l.
<hi>3.</hi> tit. <hi>6.</hi> cap. Quia juxta.</note> St. <hi>Edmund</hi> goes far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his Council, and degrees; <hi>nulli liceat Eccleſiam nomine dotalitatis ad aliquem transferre, vel pro praeſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione alicujus perſonae, Pecuniam, vel ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod aliud emolumentum, pacto interve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niente recipere,</hi> &amp;c. In <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus, Let it be lawful for none to transfer a Church to any man, in the name of a Dowry (which is commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Smock Simony</hi>) or to receive any Money for the preſentation of any perſon; or to bargain for any other profit. Which if any ſhall do, and be convict in Law, or ſhall confeſs it; we decree him as well by royal as our own authority, to be deprived of the Patronage of that Church for ever. This Canon being the chiefeſt againſt Simoniacal Patrons, is by
<hi>Sharrock</hi>'s Edition of the Provincial
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93734:14"/>reckon'd to St. <hi>Edmund;</hi> but that is a miſtake, for 'tis plac'd upon <hi>Richard Wetherſhead,</hi> in the old Books, who was St. <hi>Edmund</hi>'s Predeceſſor: and ſo 'tis in the Syllabus of this election; and ſo 'tis reckon'd by other good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: and accordingly it bears date, <hi>A. D.</hi> 1229, which was two years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Edmund</hi> came to the ſee of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi> And for the royal authority mentioned in it, I conceive it depends upon a former Canon, made under <hi>Richard</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in the reign of
<hi>Henry</hi> the 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>d,</hi>
                  </abbr> in his Synod held at <hi>London, A. D.</hi> 1175. Which decreed, that every Patron ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king reward for any preſentation, ſhould loſe his Patronage for ever. As <hi>Hoved.</hi> notes, <hi>in Vita Hen.</hi> 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>d,</hi>
                  </abbr> at which decree,
<hi>Henry</hi> the 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>d</hi>
                  </abbr> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Firſt were preſent, and conſented. But becauſe both theſe, transferred and forfeited a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral right, which the Law (it ſeems would not allow a Canon to do) they both prov'd ineffectual. 'Tis pretty to obſerve, what pains the Gloſſator on this Canon takes, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain <hi>Perpetuum,</hi> to be during the life of that Patron: being loath ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93734:14"/>breaches of truſt, ſhould be too ſeverely puniſhed: when 'tis plain, that the King and Church, did by that means declare the truſt forfeited for ever; by the abuſe of it. But the Canon being rejected, the Lords portion is become his Daughters; the Patrons children are enabled to live by Sacriledge; and yet himſelf declared unfit to bear any Truſt in the Church affairs. And the very Clouds labour with the weight of Curſes that hang over his head. <hi>Curſed be the Deceiver</hi> ſaith
<hi>Malachi</hi> 1.14; and he is no ſmall one, that deceives God, in what is intruſted to him: and <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Ye are curſed with a Curſe, for ye have rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me. Remigius Altiſſiodor</hi> renders <hi>Anathema</hi> by <hi>alienatio,</hi> and ſays,<note place="margin">Com. in Zack <hi>14.</hi> Bibl. pa tom. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 'tis <hi>in rebut, quas homines vota facientes, templo affigebant, &amp; a ſe alienas facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant,</hi> and in truth, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is put by good Authors, for <hi>donarium Deo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratum,</hi> any thing devoted to God, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for
<hi>Exitio deſttinatus,</hi> one devoted to perdition, and both from
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſet apart; as believing the curſe of God and Man is intail'd on him that takes to himſelf, what is devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God. So that our Patrons <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrick</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93734:15"/>is ſpoken from Mount <hi>Ebat;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.12.</note> and by theſe acts, as <hi>Jacob</hi> told his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he rather brings a curſe then a bleſſing on his Family. And this was <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s ſenſe of <hi>Anathema</hi> too;<note place="margin">V. quaeſt. <hi>121.</hi>
                  </note> yea their own fathers, in their dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, did themſelves load them, that abridge or pervert their free Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, with moſt<note n="*" place="margin">Darius curſe. Ezra. <hi>6.1.</hi> The common form is venien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus contra haec &amp; deſtruentibus ed, occurrat deos in gladio iro &amp; furoris &amp; viadictae &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictionis aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naev. Apoſtolatus Benedict. in Aug. Append. ſido f. <hi>60.</hi>
                  </note> direful Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations: and why may they not fear the effects? as <hi>Hiel</hi> the Bethelite</hi> many years after did feel the curſe that <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> many ages before, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 6.26, had laid upon him that ſhould rebuild <hi>Jericho:</hi> for <hi>Hiel</hi> to pleaſe prophane <hi>Ahab,</hi> and to ſhew how gallantly he could delude thoſe ancient curſes, built on; though he had loſt his Firſt-born Son
<hi>Abiram,</hi> till all his Children pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, one after the other. So that the Gates (which were the laſt thing done), were erected in the death of his youngeſt Son <hi>Segub.</hi> Thus was the City built, but no Heir left to inherit it. 1 <hi>King,</hi> 16.34. Yea the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, have by joynt Votes and Statutes, commanded the Biſhops of each Dioceſs,<note place="margin">Stat. <hi>25.</hi> Edw. <hi>1.</hi> Anno Chriſti. <hi>1297.</hi>
               </note> twice every year, ſolemnly to excommunicate all Perſons whatſoever, that ſhall violate
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93734:15"/>the great Charter, in any clauſe of it. The firſt of which confirms the Rights and Freedoms of the Church, which theſe men ſo boldly violate.</p>
            <p>Nor hath the dire effect been leſs viſible in this Kingdom, than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Look what curſes overthrew <hi>Necuchadnezzar;</hi> the ſame or like, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated our <hi>William</hi> the Conquerer and
<hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth:<note place="margin">De non temer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eccleſ. in pref. p.
<hi>24.</hi>
               </note> and that (as <hi>Spelman</hi> obſerves out of ſeveral Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors) at the ſame period: all their Names and Bloud being rooted out of the earth, in the ſixty eighth year af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their violations.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, he married Wives enough and on purpoſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the defect of iſſue; and enervate the foreboadings of his Adverſaries. And left children enough to have poſſeſſed the Royal Throne to many Generation; had he not left a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious Phthiſis amongſt them, which the piety of his Children could not attone.</p>
            <p>And for the Conqueror, 'tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by all ſorts of Hiſtorians, how eagarly vengeance purſued him; after he had turn'd thirty ſix Pariſh Churches in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> with all their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93734:16"/>Revenues, to his own uſe, for a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. He did it in the Eighteenth year of his Reign, and <hi>Anno</hi> 19, his Son
<hi>Richard</hi> was there goared by a Stag,<note place="margin">Speed, fol.
<hi>429.</hi>
               </note> ſays <hi>Speed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. Cambd. Brit. p. <hi>259.</hi>
               </note> But Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> ſays, by a peſtilent Air breaking out of the Earth. The next year, his Horſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with the flames of the City of <hi>Maunts,</hi> (which he burnt with the Church of St.
<hi>Maries</hi> and two An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorites) yarkt ſo unexpectedly,<note place="margin">Math. Par. fol. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> as to break his Riders Belly, of which he died. His Grandchild <hi>Henry,</hi> Son of <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of
<hi>Normandy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Speed ib.</note> hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this Forreſt, is ſtruck through the Jaws with a Bough of a Tree, and ſo ends his days.<note place="margin">Math. Paris. f. <hi>71.</hi>
               </note> His other Brother <hi>William,</hi> made Earl of <hi>Flanders,</hi> was ſlain by his Uncle <hi>Henry</hi> the 1ſt. <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors eldeſt Son, had his eyes put out,<note place="margin">Ib. f.
<hi>73.</hi>
               </note> by his younger Brother <hi>Henry</hi> the 1ſt, and is ſtarved to death after twenty ſix years impriſonment, by his Brothers Order in <hi>Caerdiff</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Wales.</hi> His Son <hi>William Rufus,</hi> was ſlain by a ſlant rebound of an Arrow ſhot at a Dear by Sir <hi>Walter Tyrrel,</hi> in the ſaid Forreſt, <hi>Anno Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> 13, whilſt himſelf gave the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93734:16"/>command, <hi>Trahe Diabole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. Par. f. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> Shoot you Devil. <hi>Henry</hi> the 1ſt, was the Conqueror's fourth Son,<note place="margin">Ib. Fol.
<hi>69.</hi> Speed. <hi>459.</hi>
               </note> and ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Rufus</hi> in the Throne; whoſe two Sons <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Richard,</hi> and his Daughter <hi>Mary,</hi> were all drowned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a calm day, nigh the
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Shoar. And the King himſelf dies of a ſurfeit of Lampreys. Here is bloud touching bloud, vengeance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vengeance. And ſo concludes this ſacrilegious Conquerors Race: his name being quite put out.</p>
            <p>But Judgment is often ſwifter than ſixty eight years,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</note> for <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> died preſently. And <hi>William Marſhal</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> that rob'd the Biſhop of <hi>Furnes,</hi> of two Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors belonging to his Biſhoprick in <hi>Ireland:</hi> was aſſured by the Biſhop, that in the next generation, his name ſhould be extinct: and the King was told by him, that he ſhould live to ſee it. Yet 'twas unlikely enough,<note place="margin">Math. Paris. f. <hi>687.</hi>
               </note> for he had five Sons, lively and valiant men; but alas, all died Earls of <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke</hi> ſucceſſively, within twenty five years, and his name and family utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blotted out of the World.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93734:17"/>
            <p>Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi> ſeemed the Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his Prince and Countrey for many years: but he ventures on ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, <hi>Anno Hen.</hi> 8.17, and is in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire,<note place="margin">Goodwin. fol.
<hi>104.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Anno Reg.</hi> 21, and deſpoiled of all, even to the want of Bread. And the next year he is forced to take a Purge ſay ſome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mart.</hi> 304.</note> Poyſon ſay others, to get rid of his hated life. Nor did any one of his five Friends, miſs of divine Vengeance, that he imployed in his Sacrilege, as is manifeſted by
<hi>Goodwin</hi> at large.<note place="margin">Goodw. f. <hi>67.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>There is a Family in the County of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> of a Noble Stock, to whom For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had never been unkind, till they dispeopled the Pariſh where they were ſeated by Incloſure; and impounded the Pariſh Church within their own yard, and took all the profits to their own uſe. Since which, a brisk and ſmart Providence hath ſo cloſely purſued them, that five Lords ſucceſſively Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors, and about nine or ten Heirs Male, have periſhed in the ſpace of twenty years. A meer ſtranger to their bloud is now in poſſeſſion of the ſcantling left; and there remains but one feeble Female to ſupport it.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93734:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Staniſlaus Socolovius</hi> takes the <hi>Turks</hi> ſuccesful inrodes into <hi>Hungary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orat. Staniſ. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colov. Gul. Tyrius de bello ſacro. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> to be a judgment on that Nation, for ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Churches Revenues. And <hi>William</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Tyre,</hi> imputes the diſmal blow given to the Knights Templars, to the heavy diſpleaſure of God upon them, for detaining the Lands and Tythes given to the Church, to their own uſe.</p>
            <p>Inſtances in this kind are almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite; and humane experience is nigh cloyed with evidences of the ſmart Reflections providence hath made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sacrilege. Whoever deſires to be further ſatisfied in this matter, may be ſufficiently furniſhed in <hi>Bredenba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> and ſeveral other Authors,<note place="margin">Bredenb. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crileg. vind. &amp; paene.</note> that handle it at large. And therefore with great reaſon, did that noble Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Monk</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, that in all his ample Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, he had not one foot of Church Lands.</p>
            <p>Nor is it from our purpoſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, how exuberantly the bleſſings of Heaven have diſtilled on their heads, that have been careful to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, rather than detract from the Lords Portion. God bleſſed the houſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93734:18"/>of <hi>Obed-Edom,</hi> for protecting the Ark, but ſmote all the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned it, whereſoever it came: ſo that <hi>Aſhdod, Gath</hi> and <hi>Ekron</hi> cryed out,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>Let it go again to its own place, that it ſlay us not, and our People: for there was a deadly deſtruction through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the City; the hand of God was very heavy there.</hi> Who was greater than <hi>Moſes,</hi> that made Collections for the ſervice of God? Or who was more ſucceſsful than <hi>David</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced at the free oblations of the People? Inſtead of detracting, he made large proviſion for the worſhip of God;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.3, 4, 5, 9.</note> offering vaſt treaſures; <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> 3000 <hi>talents of the Gold of</hi> Ophir, <hi>and</hi> 7000 <hi>talents of refined Silver, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Veſſels of Gold and precious Stones.</hi> And this courſe too, ſteer'd that mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſicent Prince <hi>Solomon</hi> the Wiſe. What vaſt Treaſures did <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, (a Prince unparalell'd for Wiſdom, Piety, and Puiſſance) powre out upon the Church, to the provoking the envious Devil to cry out in his hollow ſhreiks in the air, <hi>Hodie vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num infuſum eſt in Eccleſiam.</hi> Thus <hi>Charles</hi> the Great made it his chief ſtudy to increaſe the maintainance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93734:18"/>of Religion: and God bleſſed them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. While a ſacrilegious <hi>Henry</hi> the, 8th, is ever in ſtraights.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hieron. de Cevallos</hi> ſays, If the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Territories be ſurveighed, it will appear, the Eccleſiaſticks have full as much as the Seculars: which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned <hi>Boterus</hi> to ſay; That for the Reverence and Wealth this Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon the Church,<note place="margin">Relat. Vnivers, l. <hi>1</hi> p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> God gave them
<hi>Potozzi, Megalupae</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Indian</hi> Mines.</p>
            <p>And indeed we have the beſt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the World affords to expect ſuch ſucceſs; for God himſelf paſſes his word for it.
<hi>Malach.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10.</note> 3.10. <hi>Bring you all the Tythes into the Store-houſe, that there may be meat in mine houſe, and prove me now herewith, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, if I will not open you the Windows of Heaven, and pour you out a bleſſing, that there ſhall not be room e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to receive it,</hi> and ver. 11. <hi>I will rebuke the Devourer for your ſakes, and he ſhall not deſtroy the fruits of your ground, neither ſhall your Vine caſt her Fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Aug.</hi> affirms,<note place="margin">Aug. ſerm.
<hi>210,</hi> de temp.</note> 
               <hi>Decimae ex debilo requiruntur;</hi> and brings in God, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging the whole proſits, as Lord of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93734:19"/>the world; then dividing it thus,
<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerva Tibi Nonas, da Mihi Decimam</hi> &amp;c. Keep your Nine parts to your ſelves, give me the Tenth: If you will not give me the Tenth, I will take away your Nine:<note place="margin">Walafrid. Sra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo dereb. eccl. c.
<hi>27.29.</hi>
               </note> if you give it, I will mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply your Nine. So that men may aſſure themſelves to thrive well if they tyth well. And that 'tis the beſt ſecurity to our own eſtate, to be juſt to God. He that cannot truſt God on his Word and Promiſe, whom can he truſt? Nor can he be other than an Infidel, that promiſes himſelf Proſperity, whilſt he ſtrives to ſtarve Religion.</p>
            <p>'Tis very probable, that the glory and honour which the Kings of the Earth were to bring to the Chriſtian Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24, were Riches and Reverence. And ſo 'tis ſaid of whole Nations to <hi>Rev.</hi>
21.26. <hi>And they ſhall bring the glory and honour of the Nations into it.</hi> And in truth want without a power of miracles, will expoſe the Church to contempt: for it will depreſs mens ſpirits, and and cool their zeal. If the Preacher live at the Patron or Pariſhioners Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, he muſt be civil to their crimes.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93734:19"/>A Church muſt be ſo refulgent as to awe huffing Atheiſts, in Scarlet or Buff, from affronting it. <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, reverences <hi>Jaddus</hi> the High Prieſt of
<hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> but not without his <hi>Pontificalia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 9.15.</note> 
               <hi>The Poor mans Wiſdom will be deſpiſed.</hi> A dull and blockiſh Irreverence will aſſault a poor Divine from a ſtupid Plough-boy. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Farmer will loath heavenly Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na out of a Beggers hands. Majeſty it ſelf without its Crown and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, its Pomp and State, would ſoon be ſlighted, Nor doth any thing hold off the trembling multitude from tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling on the Judge, more than his Trumpet, Robes and Grandeur. So that to impair the Churches Revenue is to attempt its ruine, and muſt needs draw the heavy vengeance of its Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der after it: Whilſt to increaſe it, is to act for and with God; and ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures the bleſſing to us and our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, in a word, all things eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially belonging to the Miniſterial calling, admit of Simony: whether Antecedent as Election, when ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are bought and ſold; Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in contracting for the Church:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93734:20"/>Ordination, agreeing its price with the Biſhop or his Officers, Inſtitution, or Induction. 2. Or Concomitant, as making Merchandiſe of the Word and Sacraments. 3. Or conſequent, as taking Bribes, to conceal preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble crimes. Or binding men in Church cenſures, not to reform ill manners, but to be paid for looſing them. Or to pay
<hi>Archidiaconal procurations,</hi> that they may not perſonally viſit their Churches, which is declared by <hi>Otho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> the Legates conſtitution, <hi>ſapere Simoniacam pravitatem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. tit. <hi>19.</hi> c. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us omni.</note> Nor is any Church far from intentional Symony, That makes Canons, not to direct their peoples practiſe, but to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſed with for their Money. They are well called <hi>Retia,</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> being more profitable than St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Nets: and deſerve execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Beſome of Deſtruction, rather than to be executed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The means by which Simony is effected, and they are either generally, by Bargaining, or particularly by the things Bargained for.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Generally by Bargaining, which in this caſe is utterly unlawful, becauſe the ſubject matter is ſo. It is no more
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93734:20"/>lawful to treat of it, than of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Rates of Rebellion, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Whoredom, and ſuch like. In which to endeavour to perſwade, is to woe a mans conſent to evil; and to get him to promiſe, what is a ſin to perform, and conſequently 'tis to oblige him to ſin. Whereas that work, becomes none better than the Devil: ſince 'tis but to undertake the office of a Tempter. I the more wonder any tongue can be ſo baſe, as to accept the employ. Men muſt firſt reckon him a mercenary wretch, whom they ſend in this Errand. The Caſuiſts reckon them amongſt the <hi>Contract us il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciti;</hi> and the Canons condemn the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining.
<hi>Ames defines</hi> Simonie;<note place="margin">de Conſ. <hi>15.</hi> c.
<hi>42.</hi> f. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que modo commutare, rem ſacram vel ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualem, pro temporali.</hi> He matters not what is exchanged, ſo it be a bartering of a temporal for a ſpiritual, and gives a double reaſon for it; becauſe ſacred things are prophaned and polluted, and handled as worldly things: when they are brought into bargaining, and valued by worldly things. 2. Becauſe 'tis unjuſt to ſell, what ought freely to be given. And in truth, the very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates (as means) do partake of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93734:21"/>nature of, and are deſecrated by the end.</p>
            <p>But let us hear them treat. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons Agent is fain to Lapwing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, while he negotiates; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding an old Horſe to ſale: or tacking a crakt <hi>Abigail,</hi> at the tail
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Preſentation. Or in honeſt words deſiring him to be obliged to be coſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in part of his Glebes or Tythes ſaying, the Patron deſires a peaceable Man, that ſhould not be ſevere with himſelf or Tenents, and to that end demands a Bond, for Reſignation at pleaſure, or when his Son or Friend comes to be ſit. This halter's Horſes conſciences, without bogling. He can't ſay, the Patron hath a living to ſell: the word Sell would affront con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and proclaims an open lie: for the Patron preſents a Miniſter, not a Proctor, to the Church; not Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage Barn; to the cure of Souls not of Tythes: and accordingly the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop inſtitutes. The Parſonage is but a conſequent, provided by charitable Laws, to ſupport him in his Office; and was never in the Patron. For as the Digeſts affirm, in their barbarous; ſtyle;<note place="margin">v. l <hi>1.</hi> tit. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93734:21"/>Sacred things are of Divine Right, and are holden of no Lord. The truth of which, in our Law, will be conſidered hereafter. The Patron preſents to the Church real, rather than Metonymical; that is, to the Chriſtians living in ſuch a Pariſh, to whom the Archdeacon, by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops mandate, opens a Temple for publick worſhip.</p>
            <p>Can the Agent ſay, the party treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed deſerves not the whole profits? this were to affront him: and to ſhame his Matter that made ſo ill a choice. Doth he ſay, the Patron deſerves a gratuity? but then it muſt be free, and may be done after, without bargain. Yet the very attempt to bargain, ſhews the Patron unworthy; by ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to betray his truſt, and to daub himſelf with the defilement of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Sacrilege; and to introduce a Prieſt by Perjury.</p>
            <p>But what can the poor Prieſt reply to abate theſe high demands? Is two hundred pound too much, to purchaſe the Office of Chriſt's Ambaſſador? that were to vilifie his Maſter and Calling. Are not the ſouls of the people worth half the money? What need is there
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93734:22"/>then of any Paſtor. Is it a mean Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to be Prieſt of the moſt high God? and a Saviour of himſelf, and them that hear him? what then is great? O unfortunate Market! where neither Buyer nor Seller can ſpeak ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, the Miniſter will tranſact this part by a friend; true but this is to defile two conſcience inſtead of one. 2. The Clerick is the more guilty, for doing by another, what his own conſcience is aſhamed of. 3. And the guilt no leſs, for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus cujuſque eſt quiſque;</hi> he knows well enough, <hi>Qui facit per alium facit per ſe. David</hi> was not excus'd for <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi>'s Murder, though ſlain by the Children of <hi>Ammon.</hi> Nor <hi>Ahab</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Naboths</hi> Murder, though he lent not: ſtone. Nor St. <hi>Paul</hi> of devout <hi>Stephen</hi> Martyrdom, though he lifted not ſinger againſt him. Nay if done with out the Incumbents privily, he is; a Simoniſt in Law; as will appear a non. And an after diſcovery obliges him to grief: as not called of Chriſt, who calls none by ſin. As a Thief that came over the Wall; as one that hath long lived upon the wages of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93734:22"/>And is bound to Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as
<hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, was to ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if the marriage were inceſtuous, though not diſcovered till twenty years after. 'Tis no good Title to a ſtolen Horſe that the Thief gave it to him, though ignorant of the Thie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. Accordingly, the Novel Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions outed him.<note place="margin">Phot. Nom. Tit. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi> Schol.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And the Tranſactor (whom the imperial Law, as well as the Canon calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. <hi>3</hi> Baſil. tit. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> &amp; Phot. Nom. tit. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> Schol.</note> and the <hi>Latines</hi> call <hi>Interventorem, Proxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam, &amp;c.</hi> is within the reach of juſtice too, and puniſhed in double the ſum contracted for:
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and if he were a Clerick, it was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation, but to midwife this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure birth into the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Particularly, the things Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted for. Which are as various, as the ſubtil Serpents windings; to elude the Laws, and couzen the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men: which never appear long in any one ſhape. So that the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are fain to ſay, Simony is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted not only by giving Money,
<hi>ſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93734:23"/>verſatur in iis omnibus, quae vel pecuniae aut pretio poſſunt aeſtimari,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains all valuable Conditions in order to a promotion, to any ſpritual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment.<note place="margin">Calv. Inſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> ſ. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> diſtinguiſhes them as many others before and ſince have done, into
<hi>munus a manu, munus a linguâ,</hi> and <hi>munus ab obſequio;</hi> which different ages have differently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That a <hi>Manu,</hi> intimates money or moneys worth: whether Goods Cattle, Bonds, Covenants, Leaſes, or glebes or tythes at half rates, or to debar tythes, in ſome particular grounds; or to perfect injurious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, ripening them into Cuſtoms but who can reckon all the ſtrange turnings of this crooked Serpent? It would affright an innocent conſcience but to peep into theſe dark Cavern of iniquity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That a <hi>Linguâ,</hi> is commonly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to lie in flatteries: but may extend to giving verbal Promiſes, to offer intimations of willingneſs, to renounce the Churches known rights or to acknowledge feigned Debts, to be due to the Patron, before ſuch Negotiation. Or to give leave to ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:93734:23"/>the Timber of the Glebes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but who can account, for the ſacrilegious prodigality of the tongue?</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>ab obſequio,</hi> when a man ſhall wait on the Patron <hi>gratis,</hi> or ſubmit to pay ſome of his debts: or become his Steward, or Bailiff for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or to entertain himſelf or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, as oft as they come thither: or to be Domeſtic Chaplain: or to teach his children <hi>gratis.</hi> Which is to pervert Gods Miniſter, from the Altar, to attend the Patrons drugery. And to build up his own houſe with Gods Revenues.</p>
            <p>Having conſidered the means, let us now view, 1. the greatneſs of this ſin in general. 2. The ſad conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that attend it. 3. The ſeverity of the Laws made againſt it. 4. That of Bond Simony in particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may conſider the greatneſs of this ſin; 1. In its original cauſe, which is Avarice. 'Tis the viperous Spawn of that root of all evil: and therefore is not only equal to, but identical with Idolatry.
<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5. Since the Selling of God in his gifts for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; declares we value money above all. The Phariſees thought Gold
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93734:24"/>greater than the Altar: but the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſt (worſe than the vileſt Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee) thinks it greater than the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and its owner too. Covetous <hi>Midas</hi> turned his food; but this the bread of life into Gold. The Golden Number with them, is much before the Dominical Letter. Both Buyer and Seller concluding, that Money is a valuable conſideration, for all things concerning Religion. They would be thought fine Gentlemen, whom God brands with this mark of filthy lucre. What will they anſwer, when at the Judgment ſeat, God ſhall deride them, in the ſcornful words of the Prophet; <hi>a goodly price that I was prized at of them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.13.</note> It ſeems then,
<hi>Judas</hi> is not the only men that ſells, nor the <hi>Jews</hi> the only men that buy their God. And the great <hi>Iharaſius</hi> ſaith,
<hi>Tolerabilior eſt Macedonii haereſis;</hi> that made the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit a Slave to God; than the Simoniſt that makes him the Merchandize of men:<note place="margin">Dec. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> cos qui, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> for when we ſell him as our beaſt, or our Slaves, we declare him our Slave; and that we have dominion over him. No doubt, theſe earthly ſouls, count gain the greateſt Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: and with King <hi>John,</hi> would ſell
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93734:24"/>their faith, as well as Churches, upon good Conſideration. Thus have we reſtored, the Buyers and Sellers into the Temple, whom Chriſt whipt out. <hi>Per nummularios</hi> (ſaith St.
<hi>Hierom</hi>) are meant, <hi>beneficii eccleſiaſtici venditores,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 21.12. <hi>Joh.</hi>
2.16.</note> 
               <hi>qui domum Dei faciunt ſpeluncam latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> And
<hi>Greg. Mag.</hi> explains,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 7. <hi>ep.</hi>
110.</note> 
               <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbas vendere, eſt de Spiritu Sancto, quem ſibi Deus per impoſitionem manuum hominibus tribuit, commodum temporale percipere.</hi> Upon this account, the Church hath been oft branded, for preferring
<hi>Lucratinas artes loco Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae,</hi> as <hi>Alliaco</hi> notes.<note place="margin">In. ep. lib. de e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendat. eccles.</note> And the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> ſadly complain, that their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Churches, <hi>ob pecuniam, infimis homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus conferri;</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. <hi>100.</hi> Grav. Germ.</note> were confer'd on the dregs of men, for their Muck. And the flattering Canoniſts, to eaſe the Popes and Cardinals Conſciences, in ſelling of benefices,<note place="margin">V. extra. de of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicii Judicis Deleg. ex parte N. ingloſ.</note> cunningly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, between <hi>Simoniaca jure divino, and jure poſitivo;</hi> making the buying and ſelling Sacraments (a thing ſeldom done, and of little profit) to be Simony by divine Law: and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling benefices (the greateſt, as well as wickedeſt trade driven in the Church) to be Simony; only by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93734:25"/>Law: <hi>quo laxiores in peccando reddant conſcientias,</hi> ſays one. And another of their own; <hi>In aureo ſpeculo,</hi> crys out, O <hi>Peter, Peter,</hi> what Troups of Souls hath this ſuperſtitious and damned Diſtinction ſent, and yet doth ſend headlong to hell. It is the occaſion (ſays he) and opens the way to their everlaſting damnation. Let greedy Patrons (if they can) ſhew any one title of divine Right, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Law, that favours ſo vile Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. Or elſe let their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces acknowledge, with the fathers: <hi>Avaritiam Simoniae Matrem,</hi> that it hath no other Womb but that of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice. And then let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that old Verſe,
<q>Si vites mortem vites ſaligia mortis.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From the villany it diſcovers; that we have a very ſlight eſteem of God and Religion. What could diſcover the profaneneſs of <hi>Eſau</hi>'s mind,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.33.34.</note> more than to ſell his Fathers Bleſſing and Birthright which carried the Prieſthood with it. The Scripture ſaith, when he had ſold it, <hi>Thus Eſau deſpiſed his Birthright.</hi> And thus was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93734:25"/>
               <hi>Jeroboam</hi> convicted of a falſe heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, in that he conſecrated, whoſoever would purchaſe it, to be a Prieſt to the Lord;<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.33.</note> even of the loweſt of the people. What is this, but ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Religion to ſale? And what can more evidence, a carnal and worldly mind? ſuch a one is eaſed of all farther trouble of examining his heart, and may take St.
<hi>Peter</hi>'s word for it (as a caſe already judged) that he is in the gall of bitterneſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.23.</note> and bond of iniquity. Doth not he deal barbarouſly with God, that will not let him have a Prieſt to ſerve at his Altar; but at ſo dear a rate? Had theſe Patrons liv'd in the time of Chriſt, would they not have attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to force a Fine from him for his high Prieſts Office? Is not this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God a Merchant, and retailing his Bleſſings for Money? Had not <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hazi</hi> a ſordid opinion of God's gift to <hi>Naaman,</hi> that would value it at the rate of a Talent of Silver?<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.20.</note> How ſtrangely would it look in Chriſt, had he turned Stones into Bread, and then ſet up a Bakers ſhop, and ſold Loaves for pence? Or to have turn'd Water into Wine, and then have retail'd it
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93734:26"/>by Quarts, for Money? Or to cure the Sick, Blind or Lame, and then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for his Fee? Or to catch Fiſh by miracle, and then furniſh the Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles for Money? By ſo doing, he had ſhewed, 'twas Earth not Heaven; 'twas Gold not God that he valued. <hi>Hoc enim eſt ſub pretio redigere gratiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. ſiquis epiſc. d. queſt.</note> 
               <hi>quae vendi non poteſt.</hi> Says the Canon, to ſet a rate upon grace that cannot be ſold.<note place="margin">Apol. c.
<hi>39.</hi>
               </note> For as <hi>Tert.</hi> well notes, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que enim pretio ulla res Dei conſtat,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of God is ſaleable. So that, if the people ſinfully pinch on the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſide, the Patrons do more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely pinch on Gods ſide; yea they ſell their own Reputation for honeſty, and allow as many as know the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, the liberty to eſteem them ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious Atheiſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From the inexcuſableneſs of the Crime; it being much more honeſt to die for want, than live by robbery and ſacrilege.<note place="margin">F. de offic. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. L. Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> colum. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> See what pains the fawning Canoniſts are at, to excuſe the Pope, in this wicked practiſe. <hi>Baldus</hi> holds, he can't be a Simoniack, though he take Money for Benefices; and ſo ſays
<hi>Bartol.</hi> and <hi>Theodoric</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſchiſm between
<hi>Urban</hi> and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 32.</note>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:93734:26"/>
               <hi>Clement,</hi> gives the reaſon. <hi>Quia Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia excuſatur per authoritatem ejus;</hi> that is, he is ſupreme, and none can judge him for it: but ſure every Patron, ſwells not to this Papal heighth. The <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Angelica</hi> ſaith, that Simony is <hi>de jure poſitivo,</hi> and the Pope can't be bound by his own conſtitutions;<note place="margin">De offic. judicie deleg. ex parte N.</note> but ſure the Laws againſt Simony are not the conſtitutions of private Patrons.
<hi>Felinus</hi> excuſes him out of charity; becauſe of the Popes great profit. <hi>Nam ceſſante tali redditu qui maximus eſt, ſedes apoſtolica contemneretur.</hi> As if 'twere lawful to live by unlawful means; and cauſe enough to juſtify thievery that we are poor: and that actions were then juſtifiable when profitable, and the greateſt Offenders were the leaſt Criminals. 'Tis ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bold, to rob God to uphold our pomp and train. But the Arch-dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con of <hi>Florence,</hi> argues much better, <hi>Papa eſt Dominus rerum temporalium,</hi> by his Charter <hi>Tibi dabo claves;</hi> and therefore may do what he will with his own. But will our Patrons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any ſuch Dominion; could all the wits of <hi>Rome</hi> have found any better excuſes; the Pope had not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93734:27"/>wanted them: yet after all this adoe, ſeveral of them ſtand infamed for this odious crime. <hi>Langius</hi> charges
<hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> the 9th with horrid Simonies:<note place="margin">Chr. ad an.
<hi>2404.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Plutina</hi> many more: <hi>Calvin</hi> cannot excuſe one in a hundred: and <hi>Marla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi> condemns them all: <hi>vix in toto Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patu reperiatur ſacerdos, qui non palam ſit ſimoniacus:</hi> and ſo ſays their own <hi>gloſſe Roma eſt caput avaritiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Act. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ideo omnia ibi venduntur.</hi> And
'twas grown into a Proverb;<note place="margin">De modo celeb. Conc. Tr.
<hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Omnia Romae vaenalia.</hi> Yea, ſo common ſaith
<hi>Durand,</hi> as if it were indeed no ſin. Inſomuch that every School boy can tell us.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vendit <hi>Alexander</hi> cruces, altaria, Chriſtum.</l>
               <l>Vendere jure poteſt, emerat illi pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But why do we travel beyond ſea, to find what too frequently occurs at home? Many ſeeming Proteſtants, having made this piece of Popery their own; and reduc'd it into daily practiſe: yet have leſs to ſay for it than thoſe abroad. Our Laws ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Patron a Defender; 'tis ſtrange they ſhould find him a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauder.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93734:27"/>I wiſh they find not the Old ſaying true,
<hi>Proditores ſunt ſui Perditores,</hi> for commonly ſuch Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors end in tortures if not of body yet of mind: the Worm of ſacrilege gnawing on their Liver.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From the abhorrency good men in all ages have had of it. Dr.<hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor thinks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duct. Dub. l. <hi>2.</hi> c.
<hi>3.</hi> r. <hi>3.</hi> n. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> there needed no law againſt Simony; for all men had light enough to deteſt it without a Law; and holds it ſufficiently condemn'd by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; though not the ſame crime with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> becauſe 'tis like it. But if it be true, that <hi>Magus</hi> attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to purchaſe a part in the Apoſtles Miniſtry, as we have prov'd before; and St. <hi>Peters</hi> anſwer imports, I ſee not how the learned Doctor will clear it, from being the ſame crime; and ſo juſtly wears his name and reproach. The Canon calls it <hi>Crimen Capitale:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qui ſtudet. <hi>1.</hi> q.
<hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and the chapter <hi>Sicut</hi> 6. affirms, <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum atrocius peccatum,</hi> no viler ſin can be committed. That zealous man
<hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidor Peluſiota,</hi> writing to <hi>Leontius,</hi> calls the Simoniſts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1.
<hi>op.</hi> 315.</note> as the true murderers of Chriſt: and indeed they break open the door upon him, with their Golden Wedges, and force
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93734:28"/>him to accept their ſervice and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently raviſh his Spouſe the Church: Or at leaſt force her to marry them or none; depoſing their Saviour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the golden calf, and ſelling him to any <hi>Caiaphas</hi> for Money. How brisk and keen the Fathers are upon this crime;<note place="margin">In Matth. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> may be ſeen in
<hi>Hierom,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 37th Sermon to the Brethren in the deſart, in <hi>Iſidore Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſiota</hi> and
<hi>Greg.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 5. <hi>ep.</hi> 276.</note> the Great, every where, but eſpecially in his 4th Book and 50 Ep. to
<hi>Virgil</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Arles:</hi> So is <hi>Tharaſius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> in his Synodical Epiſtle to Pope
<hi>Adrian:</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius</hi> zeal may be ſeen in his Decretal Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Dec. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. quos conſtite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> where he determines, <hi>dantem pariter accipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temque damnatio Simonis, quam ſacra lectio teſtatur, involvit.</hi> Neither giver nor taker can be ſaved; but are both involved in the ſame condemnation with <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> And
<hi>Echbert</hi> ſays, they that ſtrive to enter by Money, <hi>a deo maledicuntur:</hi> and if they prevail, 'tis <hi>donum iraſcentis Dei:</hi> they have it not by the grace, but indignation of God; <hi>ut tanto damnabiliores fiant,</hi> that they may be more the children of Hell than ever. And when the Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacks
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93734:28"/>anſwer, that they neither buy nor ſell ſpiritual, but temporal things, as Tythes, Glebes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he replies, <hi>Nam quiſquis horum alterum vendit</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Eikbert advi. Catharos ſerm. <hi>10.</hi> in Bibl. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum.</note> He that ſells one thing, without which the other can't be had, ſells both, and he that buys, buys both: as he that ſells a Mill, ſells alſo the water with it; though it be a daily renewing bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God. And thus he affirms, Pope <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> determined the matter. In a word, to make it the more odious, they appropriated a certain word to it, call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> filthy lucre.<note place="margin">conc. chal. can. <hi>2.</hi> tit. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> And the fathers in
<hi>Conc. Chalc.</hi> pronounces an anathema on ſuch as are guilty: which ſo affrighted that great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <hi>Photius</hi>'s Conſcience, that in his <hi>Scholia</hi> on the <hi>Nomocanons,</hi> he falls to his Prayers ſaying, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: adding if God ſhould be pleaſed to mark their tranſgreſſions, who may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide it? yea ſo bitter was the whole body of Chriſtians againſt it, that whereas the Canons had diſabled ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ranks of men from witneſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Clergy; as <hi>Jews.</hi> Hereticks,<note place="margin">L. ſi quenq. <hi>31.</hi> d. ult.</note> Infamous, Stage Players <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet here as in treaſon, all mankind were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93734:29"/>accuſers. Hear <hi>Ivo Carnot. Praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea ſecundum conſuetudinem</hi> &amp;c. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more according to the cuſtom of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church,<note place="margin">Ep. <hi>27.</hi> ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donem.</note> they act otherwiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Simoniacks and the hereſy of the <hi>Neophites,</hi> than againſt other crimes for whereas in other accuſations, the honeſty of the Accuſers, and Witneſſes is conſidered; to convict theſe even infamous perſons are admitted: and 'tis probable the reaſon was, that none but infamous perſons would be privy to ſuch infamous actions.</p>
            <p>Having viewed the greatneſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the crime, let us conſider,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Its miſerable attendencies. 1. In unhappy events.
<hi>Baronius</hi> tells us our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Deſideratus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Annal. ad an.
<hi>1047.</hi>
               </note> that Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the 9th having ſuſpended a Biſhop of <hi>France</hi> from his Office, a Presbyter with a good ſum to the Chancellor, procured his Abſolution: which <hi>Leo</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſaid to the Presbyter, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Money periſh with thee;</hi> at which he fell out of his wits; and could never do buſineſs more. So <hi>Malmsbury</hi> and <hi>Math. Weſtm.</hi> tell us, that <hi>Hen. 2d.</hi> Emperor, was three days fearfully haunted by the Devil, for being guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this ſcandalous ſin: and
<hi>Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:93734:29"/>Damiani</hi> tells us of a Prieſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi>
15. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> that could never ſay the Doxology after his Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: but ſeemed choakt at thoſe words: <hi>and to the holy Ghoſt. Gehazi</hi>'s leproſy is not unknown to any that have read the Scripture, for taking money for the gift of healing. <hi>Jaſon</hi> a bold Simoniſt, purchaſed the Prieſthood of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> at the price of
360 talents, and a Penſion of 80 talents:<note place="margin">2
<hi>Maccab.</hi> 4, 8.</note> but <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelaus</hi> outbid him by 300 talents: and got the high Prieſts office from him: but both came to fearful ends; for
<hi>Jaſon</hi> was accuſed before <hi>Aretas</hi> King of <hi>Arabia:</hi> fled from place to place,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Maccab.</hi> 5.8.</note> purſued of all men, hated as a forſaker of the Law, and had in abomination by his Country, having none to mourn for him, nor any ſolemn Funerals nor Grave with his Fathers. And <hi>Mene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> was judged a wicked Wretch, the cauſe of all miſchief, and was put to death by <hi>Antiochus</hi> at
<hi>Baraea</hi> pounded, up with Aſhes in a Tower rather than a Mortar of fifty Cubits high, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo much as burial: and that juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (ſaith the Author) becauſe he had committed many ſins about the Altar,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 13.5.8.</note> whoſe fire and aſhes were holy: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he received his death in aſhes. If
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93734:30"/>a man eſcape publick vengeance, yet ſo many Curſes cannot but lie fretting and burning him at heart; ſo as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of his ſacrilegious pleaſures. As to the Seller his horrid end is ſcarcely unknown to any man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Buyer and Seller both come to a very bad Market for both loſe.<note place="margin">Eman. Saaphor in v. Simonia.</note> The Buyer gets nothing is plain by that known Maxime of the Caſuiſts, <hi>Collatio beneficii Simoniaca nulla eſt;</hi> and by the Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> the 5th, he is <hi>inhabilis ad alia,</hi> uncapable of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Benefice, and that we ſhall ſhew is true hereafter by the Canon Law. <hi>Navar</hi> confeſſes him uncapable in Law,<note place="margin">V. Conſi. <hi>34.</hi> de ſem.</note> but might be capable in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and who doubts that upon true repentance, not otherwiſe; but even that would not make him capable in Law any more: ſo that he is a meer Intruder and plain Uſurper both of his Office and Benefice.<note place="margin">Ib. v. Th. Aq. l. c. art. <hi>6.</hi> ad
<hi>3.</hi> c. de Sim.</note> And accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly <hi>qui Simoniaci, beneficium accepit, in foro conſcientiae tenetur beneficium re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquere.</hi> He is bound in conſcience to leave what is Symoniacally gotten. The reaſon is, the Law forbids any thing to paſs by ſuch an Act. And ſo is the Novel too, as cited by <hi>Joh. Antioch,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:93734:30"/>Nomoc. tit.</hi> 11. out of 6 <hi>Nov. c.</hi>
1. <hi>v.</hi> 9. And ſuch was the Apoſtolical Canon, and that <hi>Cohal Con. c.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Let him that is advanced by Merchandizing in holy things gain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by it; but be a ſtranger to that oure or dignity he hath got by Money. So that the Simoniſt is no Paſtor, hath no title, nor did he ever enter <hi>de jure</hi> but <hi>de facto</hi> only. The Patron alſo hath loſt his preſentation for ever by Canon: <hi>pro hac vice,</hi> by the Statute; beſides the penalty ſuperadded.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Both are excommunicated, ſo it be real and not mental Simony; to wit,<note place="margin">Navar. l.c. num. <hi>111.</hi>
               </note> that
'tis not a meer Intention to give but a real performance or obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that neither party are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of it: for the rule is, <hi>Simoniacus realis eſt ipſo jure excommunicatus.</hi> And the Extravagant affirms the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Procurers and Agents,<note place="margin">C. l. cap <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> as well as principal. And indeed as <hi>Hinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marus Rhemenſis</hi> cites the Apoſtles Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, <hi>ei qui pecuniâ dignitatis eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticae compotes facti fuerint deponuntur &amp; conſortio fidelium pelluntur.</hi> They that get eccleſiaſtical preferment by Money, let them be depoſed, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93734:31"/>the Communion of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. The words are in <hi>Alexius Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinus</hi> his Synopſis added at the end,<note place="margin">Can. ap. <hi>25</hi> aliis <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Simonis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi inſtar in perpetuum excommunicetur.</hi> A Sentence now ſlighted, but once, yea many ages together, the moſt tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menduous puniſhment on this ſide Hell; and the greateſt that Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in this world againſt impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinners. It being <hi>futuri judicii prejudicium</hi> as a Father calls it: and a ſerious and grave judgment of the wiſeſt and moſt conſcientious men and beſt Laws; that the Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate is (without repentance) in a ſtate of damnation: which a truly tender conſcience would tremble to hear; but Fools make a mock of ſin, and of all ſpiritual judgments that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it. They fear hanging not damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. A good man would dread being bound in theſe eccleſiaſtical chains: or to hear his damnation proclaimed at the mouth of theſe venerable Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons; whoſe reverend gray Hairs have been conſecrated by the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all the Chriſtian world to them.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93734:31"/>
            <p n="4">4. Reſtitution is on both ſides to be made <hi>Facinus quos inquinat aequat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lucan. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> One receives the unrighteous Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, the other the wages of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: both live on what is none of their own.<note place="margin">Cyp. ep.
<hi>68.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Et dum junguntur in culpâ fic nec in paenâ ſeparantur:</hi> they are united in ſinning, and can't be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in ſuffering. For as <hi>Gunther</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>conſenſu culpae meruit conſortia paenae;</hi> agreement in ſin, calls for agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in puniſhment; accordingly the <hi>proemium</hi> on one ſide, and the profits on the other are to be delivered to ſome charitable uſe as Goods unjuſtly got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.<note place="margin">L. <hi>2.</hi> col. <hi>15.</hi> Cov. l. c. n.
<hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jure divino Simoniaca pecunia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituenda eſt;</hi> ſay <hi>Soto</hi> and <hi>Covarrun,</hi> and many others. This Law of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, is no invention of School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Canoniſts, nor one of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh traditions or unwritten verities; but came from the holy Ghoſt by the Pen of <hi>Moſes. Lev.</hi> 6.4. <hi>He ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore what he took violently away;</hi> which will refer to Patrons that force Money out of their Preſentees, <hi>Or the thing he hath deceitfully gotten.</hi> That relates to both Patron and Preſentee, both having agreed to deceive the Law, the Church and Religion too. But
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93734:32"/>many chooſe to go to Hell with a full purſe, rather than to Heaven with a clear conſcience. Hence 'tis ſo few vomit the ſurfeits of their Sacrilege; yet 'twas well practiſed by a true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert in the Goſpel; <hi>If I have taken any thing from any man I reſtore him four-fold.</hi> But more of this anon.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The people in Communion are many wayes injured by it. For
1. The Patron chooſes not the beſt man for their uſe; but the richeſt for his own. If he can but purchaſe, 'tis no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whether he can perform his duty or not. If his pockets be but full, 'tis no matter how empty his Scull: for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron is to edify his own purſe, not his peoples ſouls; and therefore like <hi>Judas</hi> will ſell though to accurſed
<hi>Caiaphas.</hi> Hence the Princes complain they were diſpoſed to ſuch,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent. grav.</note> 
               <hi>Qui ad mulos magis quàm ad homines paſcendos &amp; regendos eſſent idonei;</hi> as were fitter to fodder beaſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. delect.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> than feed men. The Cardinals call them <hi>homines imperitiſſimos, viliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimos malis moribus praeditos:</hi> Indiſcreet baſe, and evil men were brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Church preferment. They were (as the Emperor
<hi>Frederick</hi> calls them) <hi>Non tam praedicatores quam praedatores,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93734:32"/>non orbis Reparatores,</hi> ſays he to Pope
<hi>Adrian, quam auri Corraſores.</hi> And here by <hi>William</hi> of
<hi>Wickams</hi> leave, 'tis Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney not Manners makes the man; but it marrs both Religion and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hoſpitality and charity to the Poor muſt needs be abated: For 'tis morally impoſſible the wide drains of Simony ſhould leave the Purſe as full as it would be otherwiſe. Nor can a Living maintain both Parſon and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, as well as it would maintain the Parſon only. The fuller the Patrons purſe, the emptier the poors belly: and the more he gets the leſs the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners can expect. So that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons gripe, pinches not only the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but the Pariſhioners and Poor at once.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It makes the Incumbent the more exacting: <hi>Petrus Fullo</hi> purchaſed the Chair at <hi>Antioch</hi> by bribing
<hi>Apollina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>'s faction; and then uſed it ſo ill, that
<hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cyrus</hi> depoſed him, and <hi>Zeno</hi> baniſhed him, ſays the Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Book, <hi>Anno</hi> 482. The Palls of
<hi>Mentz Coloigne</hi> and <hi>Saltzburg</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from 10000 Ducats, to
24000 a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, make the people grone, who
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93734:33"/>are always fleac'd to pay it. <hi>James</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> dying ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was preferred, was not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at his death, but that his poor Subjects ſhould ſo ſoon again be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd to pay a grievous exaction for the Pall. Which
<hi>Maximilian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror calls <hi>palliatum Simoni-amactoak,</hi> for Simony in his Letters to <hi>Adrian</hi> the 6th. Theſe payments like Exciſe impoſed on Ale by <hi>Frederick</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chro. ad an. <hi>1486.</hi>
               </note> made the Sellers <hi>menſuram mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuere non abſque grandi ſcandalo &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure Communitatis,</hi> ſays <hi>Langius.</hi> And ſo will theſe payments give men oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to abate their care of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſafety, and to be very ſtrict for their dues. Coming to it as to a Farm rather than a Church. And as our Statute 21.
<hi>Car.</hi> 2, impoſing 9 <hi>
                  <abbr>d.</abbr> per</hi> Barrel on Ale, indemnified the Sellers as to rate or price. So muſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron be quiet and permit his fluxt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentee to reimburſe himſelf though by very oppreſſive means.<note place="margin">Plut. in polit. preceptis.</note>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſays, you may not enter ſome Temples till you have laid down your Gold; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'twas counted a heinous crime to bring it in: but many in <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:93734:33"/>can't come into the Temples with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it: though perſons cry,
<q>In Sancto quid facit aurum?</q>
            </p>
            <p>What Concord between Chriſt and <hi>Mercurius,</hi> the Temple and the Market? yet theſe two things that agree no more, ſays Dr.
<hi>Taylor,</hi> than Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation and a Cart-rope, met in
<hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> and are no Strangers in <hi>England</hi> but to the publick calamity. For the Patrons great purge makes the Prieſt bite ſharp to ſupply his empty Bowels.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And the Preſentee is made by it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of his Office; for how ſhould the people believe a perjur'd man? <hi>Qui culpas debet emendare committit,</hi> ſays <hi>Gregory.</hi> He that ſhould correct, commits the faults.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ep.</hi>
113.</note> How can he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn indirect ways in others, that practiſes them himſelf? Can he preſs ſelf denial, that hath ventur'd his conſcience and credit both for ſelf In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt? Can the Patron reverence him at the Altar, whom he knows for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn at the Conſiſtory. And how can the people honour him as a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, whom they know to be a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? What guide will he prove, that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93734:34"/>miſſed his way at the very entrance? How can he joyn in Communion with them, whilſt his conſcience is not cleanſed by Repentance? And what Repentance can there be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Renunciation and Reſtitution: but of this more hereafter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His peace and ſafety depends on the ſilence of the Patron, Procurer and Agents: which makes him a Slave to wicked and covetous men; ſo that he dare not rebuke with any authority: greater ſervitude his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies can't wiſh him. They can blow him away with the breath of their mouth, he ſtands ſo tickle. If they confeſs and amend, he is ruined. 'Tis a kind of treaſon againſt God, of which he muſt fear the diſcovery: nor can he ſleep more ſoundly than the Thief; that fears ſome of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complices may betray him. The neck of his Incumbency is in their Halter: and they may ſniffle him when they pleaſe. <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Nicomedia</hi> that famous <hi>Arian,</hi> hired a Quean to ſware that holy <hi>Euſtathius</hi> got the child in her arms: and ſo got him ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. But after being ſick, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed what ſumm the
<hi>Arians</hi> gave her
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93734:34"/>to ſwear againſt her: and ſaid, 'twas one
<hi>Euſtathius Aerarius</hi> got the child; which turned to the ruine of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers.<note place="margin">In Chriſto Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell. tom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>v. lib. Synodalem.</hi> He is no ſafer than the unchaſte wife, that dares not deny her paramour any thing, for fear he tell: and looks pale (like
<hi>Faux</hi> and his Conſpirators) leſt the truth ſhould come to light. O unhappy Preacher! that fears light more than darkneſs.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly their Incumbent is all good mens ſcorn if known;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.16.</note> our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour never ſhewed a brisker zeal, than againſt the Bank and Marketting in the Temple.<note place="margin">1 <hi>King</hi> 5.27.</note> How ſharply doth <hi>Eliſha</hi> proceed againſt his Servant <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hazi,</hi> for this crime; clapping the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe of <hi>Naaman</hi> incurably upon him and his ſeed for ever.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.7, 8.</note> The Angel with a drawn ſword reſolves <hi>Balaam</hi>'s ruine, for going to ſell his bleſſing. St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſhews the occaſion of his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. <hi>that he loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs:</hi> and ſo we may take that place, <hi>Jude</hi> 11. that the <hi>Gnoſtick</hi> Teachers ran after <hi>Balaam</hi>'s error to ſell their propheſy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings for reward: by this <hi>Balaam</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the wrath of God againſt him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi>
22.22.</note> After this crime, old <hi>Iſaac</hi> would not bleſs
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93734:35"/>his Son <hi>Eſan,</hi> though he ſought it with tears. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17. That ſubtil Magician <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> knowing how hateful this ſin was to all good men, blackned <hi>Henry</hi> the
4th. Emperor with it; in hope to draw all mens affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from him.<note place="margin">Plat. in vit. Greg. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Though 'tis moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that Prince depoſed <hi>Hereman</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Babenburgh;</hi> for entring Simoniacally. And he ſat in the Church of <hi>Babenberg,</hi> to preſent to the rich Abbey of <hi>Fulda,</hi> and had great offers for it: but he was aſhamed of them; and called out an humble <hi>Monk</hi> of <hi>Helvord,</hi> named <hi>Reucelinus,</hi> whom he preferred to that dignity. So a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in a great ſtrife of bribes for the <hi>Loriſſan</hi> Abbey;<note place="margin">V. Lamb. Schaſſmaburg. Chron.</note> he rejected all, and preſented one that never thought of it: and commended <hi>Severus</hi>'s way of rejecting Obtruders, and accepting the moſt modeſt as moſt fitting. But above all inſtances, ſee St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s zeal againſt <hi>Magus, Pereat tecum Pecunia tua.</hi> When he would have purchaſed the Biſhoprick of <hi>Samaria,</hi> or an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip (as hath been formerly ſhewed) and as <hi>Urban</hi> 2d. ſeems to believe, in his Decretal Epiſtle to
<hi>Lucius</hi> Provoſt of St. <hi>Juventius, Anno</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:93734:35"/>1099; where he argues that to buy Church livings was Simony: becauſe <hi>Magus</hi> did not deſire the holy Ghoſt of whom he was unworthy, but the power to give it to others, as the Apoſtles did: upon which in juſt indignation, the Apoſtle ſtooke him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 237.</note> 
               <hi>voce tonitrus</hi> ſays St.
<hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> with that thundring ſentence: knowing 'twas the profit of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing thoſe gifts he looked after. For he conſidered how cheerfully fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would depoſite great ſumms to procure the gifts of Tongues to their children, without the harſh and tedious Padagogy of School-maſters. And how ready rich men would be, to purchaſe wiſdom and gifts of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, and to underſtand all myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: if they could be had in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that they were the <hi>res Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticae,</hi> the profits of Religion he aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at; and therefore that is the firſt notion of Simony. And againſt it that great Apoſtle is ſo hot. What favour the Fathers had for it, hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in part, and may be eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectur'd by the ſharp Canons made againſt it. We will conclude this part with the zeal of that mirror of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:93734:36"/>and all goodneſs. Dr. <hi>Michael Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nywood</hi> late Dean of <hi>Lincoln:</hi> who was wont to proteſt, he would no more converſe with a Simoniacal Clergy man, of what rank ſo ever, than with a Felon burnt in the hand, or branded on the Forehead.</p>
            <p>Yet as hateful as this crime hath been to all good Chriſtians; former ages have not been ſo happy, as to be free from this accurſed practice: no not the hither ſide of the Primitive times. For <hi>Peter</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> and immediate Succeſſor to the great
<hi>Athanaſius,</hi> ſadly complains of <hi>Lucian</hi> the <hi>Arian,</hi> his Simoniacal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading of that See. That he did it not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Theodorit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c.
<hi>20.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Theodorit</hi> reports it: and 'tis not to be wondred at, if a uſurping Biſhop, and monſtruous He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, enter by Goldſmiths Row, into that famous City of <hi>Alexandria. Iſidore Peluſiota</hi> gives <hi>Cyril</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch an account, of
<hi>Martinianus</hi> a Presbyters robbing the Church of
<hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſidor. Peluſ ep. ad Cyril.</note> for money to buy Votes at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> for his Election: upon which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:93734:36"/>the holy Patriarch threatens him with Excommunication, unleſs he forbear. It ſeems, 'twas too commonly practiſed at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in thoſe early days: for
<hi>Evagrius</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Evagr. l. <hi>2.</hi> c.
<hi>2</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Chryſaphius</hi> a Commander of
<hi>Theodoſius</hi> Guards, demanded of <hi>Flavian</hi> Patriarch of
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ſatisfaction for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to that See. But to ſhame him for ſo baſe a demand: <hi>Flavian</hi> ſent him the Communion Plate of the Church. To revenge which indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<hi>Chryſaphius</hi> and <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther procured him to be kickt or trode to death, in the <hi>Eutychian</hi> Council.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> was alſo promoted by the ſame Simoniſt <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphius:</hi> yet was not fully convicted, ſo as to be excommunicated for it till after his death; the ſubtile Merchants having cloaked the Simony,<note place="margin">Evagr. l. <hi>2.</hi> c.
<hi>4.</hi>
               </note> under the dreſs of ſome civil power, that he had purchaſed: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: yet <hi>Euſebiüs</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilaeum,</hi> ſo far detected him, in the great Council of
<hi>Chalcedon,</hi> that the ſecond Canon was voted (upon that occaſion) againſt Simony.</p>
            <p>We read alſo of an accuſation, brought before St.
<hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> by ſix
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:93734:37"/>
               <hi>Aſian</hi> Biſhops, againſt
<hi>Antoninus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan</hi> of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> as, for other things, ſo particularly, for taking Money for Ordination.<note place="margin">Palladius in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Chryſoſt.</note> It ſeems it was ſo common to buy it, that the Ordained pleaded a cuſtom ſo to do, and if that they ſin'd it was ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> degraded them: and
<hi>Antonine</hi> being dead, he enabled them to recover on his Heirs, their Money got from them by fraud and Simony. Pope <hi>Simplicius</hi> tells us, of his depoſing <hi>Gaudentius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Simplic. epiſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and all ordained by him; being convicted of Simony. And to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> decrees, that the Electors who ſign the Inſtrument of choice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Novel</hi> 123.</note> ſhould take an Oath, that they named them not for Money, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or any other thing but the real worth of the Elect. The methods alſo of Elections, were often alter'd to prevent this inſinuating wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Sometimes the Clergy and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple choſe three,<note place="margin">Novel ib. Anno <hi>541.</hi>
               </note> and the Metropolitan and Biſhops of that Province pickt out one. Sometimes again the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan and Biſhops propounded three;<note place="margin">Conc. Arelat.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Can.
<hi>54.</hi>
               </note> and the Clergy and People choſe out one: as was decreed in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:93734:37"/>the Council of <hi>Aries. Zeno</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror ſhut up the great Church doors of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> left a fair Paper on the Altar, gave the Key to an Eunuch, ordered faſting,<note place="margin">Niceph. l. <hi>16.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> and Prayers forty days; that God would order them a Biſhop. <hi>Flavit as</hi> borrow'd Money of the Bankers, bribed the Eunuch, his name is inſcribed, and accepted as a Patriarch divinely called: but the Bankers tell where the Money was borrowed, and he rejected.</p>
            <p>Thus every age hath applied ſome remedy, to this growing diſeaſe, which is not yet extirpated. <hi>Greg. Mag.</hi> held a Council at
<hi>Rome</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate it: where it appeared, that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was taken in the name of Fees to Clerks and Notaries.<note place="margin">Greg. Decr. in Conc. Rom. can.</note> Therefore they decree that thenceforth no Fee ſhould be given for Clerks labour, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, Paper, Wax, Pall, or any other thing whatſoever. Yet they left it to the Parties diſcretion, to give ſome ſmall gratuity, at pleaſure.</p>
            <p>It would tire a well breathed Reader to repeat all that
<hi>Charles</hi> the Great's Capitulars, and later Councils have determined in this matter. I ſhall only obſerve, that hitherto, this crime
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:93734:38"/>hath been too hard for humane, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:
<hi>Averruncet Deus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We are now to conſider, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of the Laws made againſt it: which we will conſider 1. as Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, 2. Civil, 3. Statute, and 4. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law: we ſhall begin with the Canon Law.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Canon Law, <hi>Greg. Magn.</hi> obſerves to
<hi>Theodorick</hi> and <hi>Theobert</hi> Kings of <hi>France;</hi> that Simony was of the Devils plantation: <hi>Et in ipſo ortu ſuo, zelo apoſtolicae ultionis percuſsa, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata eſt:<note place="margin">Greg. l. <hi>7.</hi> ep.
<hi>114.</hi>
                  </note> that it was blaſted by St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Thunder in its firſt budding. And from thence the Church held Simony to be a haerely: now we may reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly gueſs, they intended not the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to be ſo; but the opinion of its lawfulneſs, againſt the Apoſtles and all ſucceeding Councils judgment. The Apoſtles Canon declares (as in
<hi>Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Antiochenus</hi> collection;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi>
29.</note> 
                  <hi>tit.</hi> 11.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. If any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Presbyter or Deacon hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his dignity by Money, let him be depoſed, and him that ordained him: and let him be altogether cut off from the Church; or Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as the <hi>Latine</hi> verſion hath it;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:93734:38"/>
                  <hi>Alexius Ariſtinus</hi> in his Synopſis places it <hi>Can.</hi> 25. and it differs a little in words rather than in ſenſe. The next is the ſecond Canon of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon;</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. If any Biſhop ſhall cauſe Ordination for Money, and bring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaleable grace to ſale, and ordain a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Presbyter or Deacon,<note place="margin">Codex Can. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis hath <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Biſhop and Presbyter.</note> or any one that is numbred in the Clergy for Money; or ſhall advance any Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, Advocate or Manſionary for Money: or any at all of the Canons for his own filthy lucre. He that is convicted to have attempted it; let his own degree be indangered. And he that is Ordained, let him be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profited by his Ordination or promotion got by Merchandizing: but let him be without his dignity or cure which he gets by Money.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And if any ſhall appear an Agent in this baſe and unlawful gain; if he be a Clerk, let him fall from his own degree: but if a Laick or Monk, let him be <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi> There are ſeveral other Canons to this purpoſe made by later Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils; as <hi>Can.</hi> 22, and 23.
<hi>Conc.</hi> 6th, and <hi>Can.</hi> 4, 5, 19. of the 2d <hi>Nicene</hi> Council;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> and many others reckon'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:93734:39"/>up by <hi>Photius</hi> in his
<hi>Nomocanon:</hi> and Antiochenus,</hi> not needful here to recite. But by theſe 'tis manifeſt what care the Church of God ever took to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs this growing miſchief.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We now come to the Civil Law. The holy Emperors found that the Croſier was inſufficient to beat it down, unleſs their Sword were joyned with it: and therefore <hi>Novel. Conſt.</hi> 130. <hi>cap.</hi>
19. Decrees,<note place="margin">Vide Joh. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch. Nomocan. tit. <hi>11.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. V. Juſt. Nov. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>123.</hi> &amp;
<hi>56.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; both giver and taker and deprived of the Prieſthood. And <hi>Novel</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 9. ſays, the Receiver ſhall reſtore the Money, as well as be outed; and he that gives, ſhall loſe any former preferment he had. And there is an Oath required of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in order to a detection of the crime. And again.
<hi>L. l.</hi> 1. <hi>tit.</hi> 3. <hi>Conſt.</hi> 30, 31; 'tis decreed that none ſhall give ought, but the Clergy of the great Church of
<hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and they that give, are bounded to a ſingle Diary of one year only.<note place="margin">V. Phot. Nomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. tit. <hi>1.</hi> c.
<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> ex l. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Baſil. tit. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And 'tis farther provided, that
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all gifts or promiſes ſhall be confiſcate to the Church for which they were given. But concerning
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:93734:39"/>this laſt, the Canoniſts and Caſuiſts are much divided. For ſome think if the Receiver repent before ſentence juridical; 'tis to be reſtored to the party from whom he had it. If after, ſome think it belongs to the Church, others to the Poor; but moſt think
'tis forfeited to the Pope. <hi>Vide Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var. Convar. Soto</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in Sa</hi>'s <hi>Aphoriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</hi> But this Conſtitution, was left out of the
<hi>Baſilicks,</hi> and therefore is deemed void: but then <hi>Juſtin. Novel.</hi> 123. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. is much the ſame, and is in 3. <hi>lib. Baſil. tit.</hi> 1.<hi>c.</hi> 9. only there 'tis alike dangerous to give Money to any other Perſon.<note place="margin">V. Phot. Nomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. tit.
<hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> Sch.</note> And further adds, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſo that the Agent or Contriver if a Lay-man, was to pay double the ſumm received to the Church, or next Succeſſor ſay ſome. See alſo the Collection of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamon, ex lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cod. tit.</hi> 3.
<hi>num.</hi> 30. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. Where 'tis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that to give or receive Money to be ordained or choſen a Biſhop, ſhall be depoſition, and he ſhall be branded with perpetual Infamy. So ſcandalous was this crime in the eyes of all Chriſtian Princes.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:93734:40"/>
            <p n="3">3. Nor doth this practice meet with better uſage in this Nation, where the Law is as fierce againſt it, as the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is for it. The Statute hath drawn its ſword againſt it, and forfeits the benefice ſo bought and ſold, to the King: againſt both Patron and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent. As appears at large: 31. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 6. Where 'tis provided,
<q rend="margQuotes">If any Perſon or Perſons, bodies politick or corporate, ſhall or do, for any Sum of Money, reward, gift, profit or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit whatſoever, directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, preſent or collate, any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to any Benefice with cure of Souls, dignity, Prebend, or living Eccleſiaſtical: or give or beſtow the ſame for or in reſpect of any ſuch corrupt cauſe or conſideration; that then every ſuch Preſentation to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly void: and every Inſtitution, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Induction, to be of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in Law. And that it ſhall and may be lawful, for the Queen, her Heirs and Succeſſors, to preſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow every ſuch Benefice for one turn only. But this is not all; for 'tis farther provided, that every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſhall give or take any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney —or give or take any bond or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:93734:40"/>—ſhall forfeit (for their corrupt dealing) the double value of one years profit, of every ſuch benefice, to the Queen and Informer. And the Perſon ſo corruptly taking, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting any ſuch benefice; ſhall thenceforth be adjudged a diſabled perſon in Law, to have or enjoy the ſame benefice.</q> The like forfeiture is made, if any perſon give or take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing above the uſual Fees for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, Inſtallation or Induction. So likewiſe if any corruptly reſign or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change any Benefice for any Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſumm of Money or benefit what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. The giver and taker both ſhall loſe the double value of the ſum ſo taken, to the Queen and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former.
<q rend="margQuotes">And 'tis provided, this Statute ſhall not extend to reſtrain, or abate any Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures or penalties againſt this crime: but the ſame ſhall remain in force, and may be put in due execution.</q> So that the Statute is but accumulative not derogative to the ſpiritual power. The three Eſtates of the Kingdom joyning all their force with the King and Church to pull down this ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant Oppreſſion.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:93734:41"/>
            <p>There is a farther Clauſe; that the giver and taker of Money for Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Licenſe to preach or ſerve a Cure, above the uſual Fees, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, the Give 10 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> and the Receiver 40
<abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a piece for ſo doing; and the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be uncapable of any Living for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years after ſuch corrupt purchaſe. Thus it is in the book of Statutes: why the Abridger ſhould make the penalty 10
<abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a piece; or Sir <hi>Simon Degge</hi> ſhould willingly ſay, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver was puniſhed in forty Shillings, is hard to gueſs. He bid his Parſon note, that the Statute is more ſevere upon the Clergy man then the Officer:<note place="margin">Degg. p. <hi>1.</hi> cap.
<hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> for the Officer only forfeits forty Shillings, but the Clergy forfeits ten Pounds; which is irreconcilable with the Statute.</p>
            <p>Having ſhewed the ſubſtance of the Statute, we may view the practiſe as the Lawyers have reported it. They ſay <hi>Trin. Jac.</hi> 8. all the Juſtices agreed, That a Preſentation is void, if for Money, though the Preſentee know nothing of it: and the King may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. If ſo then, the Preſentee is a Simoniſt in Law not in conſcience. And here
<hi>Sa</hi>'s Caution is neceſſary, that the Preſentation fail not;<note place="margin">Cok. <hi>12.</hi> Rep. f. <hi>74.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si quis
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:93734:41"/>tuo nomine ut beneficium perderes pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam dedit pro eo.</hi> For the Report (as <hi>Coke</hi> ſets it down) relating not to them that give to prevent, but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you the Living. Others ſhew that Simony may be committed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Patron nor Incumbent being Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to it: for the forfeiture is made by the Simony, whoever be the Agents in it: as if the Preſentees friend bribe a Courtier, and he prevail with his Prince for the preferment. They that deſire to know more in this point, may conſult
<hi>Crokes</hi> 1ſt. part <hi>fol.</hi> 331, <hi>Bawdcrokes</hi> Caſe.
<hi>Cokes Inſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 153, being an Expoſition of this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute. <hi>Noyes Rep. f.</hi> 22. in <hi>Paſcals</hi> caſe, which (beſides many other Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations) are enough to evidence,<note place="margin">Habrep. f. <hi>165.</hi>
               </note> that our Government is clear in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Nor Church nor State favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this unhappy practice: yet we may ſay of the vice as the Hiſtorian doth of the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> they were always baniſhed from <hi>Rome</hi> yet always there.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there is a doubt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, what contracts are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and what not, we will endeavour to give ſome ſatisfaction. 1. By ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what caſes are juſtifiable. 2. What are not.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:93734:42"/>
            <p n="1">1. In what caſes it may be lawful to uſe Money or Moneys worth: and ſure 'tis lawful to give money to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe our peace, when we meet with litigious men, that pretend a title to our Living but have none. But then the Preſentee muſt have <hi>jus certum &amp; indubitatum</hi> in his own judgment; and he muſt give (not to make a title) but in <hi>vexationis injuſtae redemptionem.</hi> This point doth <hi>Ameſius</hi> determine:<note place="margin">L. <hi>5.</hi> de conſc. c. <hi>42.</hi> n.
<hi>18.</hi>
               </note> Peace we may buy though not bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, as well our daily bread. But here let us remember the Caſuiſts Caution, <hi>In iſtis cavendus eſt dolus, &amp; ſpecies ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li fugienda.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eman. Sa A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor. in v. Sim. n. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> And ſo do <hi>Sa</hi>'s Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors rules determine, in caſe any <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>què impediat electionem vel poſſeſſionem,</hi> unjuſtly hinder his Election or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis alſo lawful for the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent to take, and people to give what is judged convenient, for the time he ſpends, and labour he is at, in mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring to the Congregation: for that is acknowledging his imployment, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than rewarding the deſert, which is ſpiritual and invaluable: rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiting labour, than paying for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Sacraments. And if Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:93734:42"/>be to ride far, to adminiſter either Sacrament, it would be no Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to reward the journey: our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour having aſſured us the Labourer is worthy of his Hire. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle affirms, they that ſerve at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar may live by it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And all Chriſtians poor and rich, are commanded,
<hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. If they are taught in the word, to communicate to him that teacheth in all his Goods. Labour in ſtudy and teaching is no ſupernatural thing: nor neceſſarily of a ſpiritual nature, and therefore may be purchaſed. Hence too, a Chaplain may take pay for his ſervice, becauſe his time and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance are valuable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To purchaſe an Advowſon in Fee ſimple is lawful, when the Church is full: Provided you deſign not to preſent your ſelf,<note place="margin">Hob. <hi>165.</hi> Says' Caſe.</note> nor purchaſe it to preſent any other Party by name. Not for your ſelf, for that is plain mental and Intentional Simony; and differs nothing from actual Simony; but in meer circumſtances, about the manner of preſenting, and in reſpect of time ſooner or later.<note place="margin">Mores Rep.
<hi>877.</hi>
               </note> Nor for any Party named or preſent, for if he be named in the Grant; 'twas adjudged
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:93734:43"/>legal Simony in <hi>Puliſton</hi> and
<hi>Winſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combs</hi> Caſe 14. <hi>Jac.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. Freeman, and Engliſh caſe. Mich. <hi>3.</hi> Jac.</note> So 'twas in <hi>Smiths</hi> and <hi>Shelborn</hi>'s caſe, and many others cited by Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> in his <hi>Parſons Law, c.</hi> 18. If an Advowſon be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed <hi>pro hac vice,</hi> and the Party be meerly preſent when 'tis done, though not named, His Preſentation is Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacal at Law: as the Learned and Pious Sir
<hi>Simon Degge</hi> affirms in that honeſt and uſeful treatiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>The Parſons Counceller.</hi> And it ſeems by <hi>Hutton</hi> 'twas judg'd Simony in Law to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the next Advowſon,<note place="margin">lb.</note> the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent being ſick as <hi>Degge</hi> informs us from <hi>Sheldon</hi> and
<hi>Bretts</hi> Caſe. We may doubt 'tis <hi>malum in ſe</hi> to purchaſe an Advowſon, for one turn, under what circumſtances ſoever; and the Law was ſo as we ſhall ſhew hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; though practiſe makes it at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſeem otherwiſe. For what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there to a conſcientious man, between buying an Advowſon that one may be preſented, or a Preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that end. This is but a Grammar Periphraſis, to expreſs the ſame thing, and uſed to avoid the Law, rather than to avoid the ſin.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:93734:43"/>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis Lawful to reſign a Living <hi>in favorem alterius,</hi> for the kindneſs we have to any worthy unpreferred Prieſt. Provided we believe upon beſt conſideration, that he is more likely to profit the People than our ſelves; and that we make no corrupt bargain, nor reſerve no penſion; for that would make the Reſignation unlawful both in Law and Conſcience; as the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts generally conclude. And ſo do our Lawyers and the Statute too.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Nor could firſt fruits and Tenths be excuſed from Simony; both in Prince and Prieſt: but as they are reckon'd a legal Contribution, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Civil Government: which the Church is to contribute to, as well as the State: ſeeing they equally ſhare with others in common peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. For otherwiſe, what right could any man pretend, to what is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to God and his Church. How came the Soveraign to have more Right to it than the Subject? If Tythes be reſerved by the Divine Law to ſpiritual uſes; how came Princes or Parliaments to annul it? Can time, Cuſtom or Uſurpation, preſcribe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God? Kings might reſerve
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:93734:44"/>Rents or Service, out of Mannors of their own Donation; becauſe they may give as much or as little as they pleaſe of their own: but with what conſcience can they demand the firſt Fruits and Tenths, of what is given by a Decree of Heaven? Or by the Teſtament of other men? Is it meet for them to deſtroy Property? then Government is uſeleſs: for its chief, if not its only end, is to preſerve it.</p>
            <p>This device was hatch'd in the Conclave of <hi>Rome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lang. In Chro. Citizenſi ad an. <hi>1404.</hi> Platin. in vit. Bonif. <hi>9.</hi> Theod. a Niem. ſchiſc. mate. <hi>12.</hi> c.
<hi>7.</hi>
               </note> mutter'd by <hi>John</hi> 22d, but brought forth by
<hi>Boniface</hi> the 9th, ſaith <hi>Langius</hi> and <hi>Platina;</hi> about the tenth year of his Popedome. ſays <hi>Theod.</hi> a <hi>Niem.</hi> And that ſo rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly proſecuted, that he made them pay a years profit, whether they could get the Church or not, before they went to it. And often wiſhed they might never get it.</p>
            <p>But yet this charged only Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drals, Abbies,<note place="margin">Tract. de penſion q. <hi>25.</hi> num. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Priories and Penſions above twelve Ducats <hi>per annum</hi> in the Popes Books; ſays <hi>Hieron. Gig as.</hi> But this was farther advanc't in after times, as the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11th. <hi>act.</hi> 77.<note place="margin">Marſil. Patav. <hi>2.</hi> part. def. pacis, c. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> So
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:93734:44"/>that <hi>Marſilius</hi> of <hi>Padua</hi> makes a ſad complaint about it. And the Biſhop of <hi>Menda</hi> charges it before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Vienna</hi> for haereſy and Simony, and urges its Reformation.<note place="margin">Durant. in tract. de mod. celeb. conc. Gen. part. <hi>3.</hi> tit. <hi>20.</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan. conc. cath. l. <hi>2.</hi> c.
<hi>30.</hi> Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mang. de ruina &amp; repar. eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae.</note> And
<hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas Cuſanus</hi> charges it for Sacrilege and Simony, in the Council of <hi>Baſil:</hi> and vehemently perſwades its Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.
<hi>Clemangius</hi> ſaith, they had ſo far improved the Law in his time; that whatſoever Eccleſiaſtical Perſon died or exchanged; the Popes Chamber ſhould receive all the Fruits, for the firſt year next enſuing.
<hi>Guynnerin</hi> in his gloſs on the Pragmatick ſanction, calls them the Buyers and Sellers, that Chriſt caſt out of the Temple, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring firſt Fruits and Annates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodor.</hi> a <hi>Nihem</hi> ſays, many great Divines hold it for Hereſy, to affirm ſuch payments can be required,<note place="margin">Niem in notis ad tract. de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. &amp; jur. imp.</note> or ſuch Laws made without the guilt of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſin: and concludes they ſpring from no other Counſel, but the ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the Devil.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain the Emperors uſed not theſe oppreſſions, when they gave In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtitures: for though they oft took the profits of the Temporalities, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the vacancy; and many times by
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:93734:45"/>their Bailiffs, invaded the Goods of the deceaſed Biſhops; upon a pretence of Regality;<note place="margin">Lib. de l' Egl. Gall. c. <hi>16.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi> V. Troſle can. <hi>14.</hi> Nemaus can. <hi>5.</hi> Tholous. can. <hi>4.</hi> Goldaſtus.</note> which the Biſhop of <hi>Maſcon,</hi> in the name of his Dean and Chapter acknowledged the King of <hi>France</hi> might do: though many Councils had condemned it: and many Kings and Princes had renounced that Right. And in particular
<hi>Frederick</hi> 2d to Pope <hi>Innoc.</hi> 4th, and our <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. to the Dean and Chapter of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> &amp;c. yet they never required any Rents, after the Incumbent was inveſted. And if there be any one inſtance of it, it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed a violent Uſurpation. Only Popes have pretended right to it, and thence as the beſt evidence, theſe parts have believed it lawful. So ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily can the Waters of <hi>Seine, Thames</hi> and
<hi>Tyber,</hi> mix, when profit perſwades: otherwiſe it had ſunk with other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal tyrannies, over this Church and State, in the reign of <hi>Henry
8th,</hi> who too readily adopted the Papal oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, into his own family; even to the continuing ſcandalous Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, againſt the common ſenſe of Mankind; but the utter ruine of his Name and Family.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:93734:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Greg.</hi> of <hi>Haymbourgh</hi> a <hi>German</hi> Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer,<note place="margin">Greg. Haymb. conf. Primat. Pap.</note> in the time of the Council of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> makes ſad complaints, how much
<hi>Rome</hi> had ſurcharged Biſhopricks and Livings with <hi>Annates</hi> and other Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacal Exactions. Great ſtruggling there was in the Council of
<hi>Conſtance</hi> to have laid theſe burdens aſide:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 40.</note> but it could not be done, till the
21 Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Council of <hi>Baſil:</hi> and there the Fathers condemned all Annates, Firſt-fruits, Money for Ordinations; Inſtitutions, Inſtallations <hi>&amp;c.</hi> forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any thing to be exacted in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſewhere, for any promotion in the Church whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. And from thence it was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into the Pragmatick Sanction. And an Ordinance at <hi>Orleans,</hi> was made againſt it: in the ſecond Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of which, all Annates <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden: but the Capitolian Geeſe charm all <hi>France</hi> again, ſo that <hi>Jan.</hi> 10,
1562, the King recalls the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and the great <hi>Leviathan</hi> is let looſe, to ſport himſelf in the great Ocean of that Nations treaſure.</p>
            <p>But for <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>60000</hi> Marca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum puri reditus Matth. <hi>Par.</hi> in vit. Hen. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> It repreſented to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth, the inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Covetouſneſs of that See; that it
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:93734:46"/>drain'd more Money yearly from hence, than the Kings whole Revenue amounted to. Yet the exaction is continued; though condemn'd by all ſound Divines, for Simony in the Popes. Yea, though the Cardinals themſelves, elected to that purpoſe, aſſure Pope
<hi>Paul</hi> the third, that it was utterly unlawful,<note place="margin">Conc. delect. Card. An. <hi>1538.</hi> quod extat in Tom. Conc.</note> after they were ſworn, to give him ſound and ſincere advice. And how weakly 'tis excus'd by the flattering Canoniſts, that ſtrive to harden mens conſciences into Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, by diſguiſing their Guilt, may be ſeen elſewhere: yet our zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous covetouſneſs ſwallowed it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out asking any Queſtion for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake. But ſo as to declare it a Revenue or Tax, to ſupport the Crown, which though it be very unequal to charge one ſort of men, and Lands more than all the reſt; and not abating them a Peny, in any other Tax or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy for it; and therefore muſt needs lie heavy, and be thought a ſevere dealing towards a Church, that vies Piety and Loyalty, with any other in the world: yet will it not be Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:93734:46"/>
            <p>We ſhall now conſider what acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are unlawful; and 1. Tis unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to attempt, to obtain any ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al promotion by Money, or any other corrupt conſideration. This was <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> crime, he ſhewed <hi>Studio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam voluntatem,</hi> an earneſt deſire, but failed in his purpoſe. This the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts call mental or intentional Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. It ſeems by <hi>Hughes,</hi> the Law lays hold of theſe attempts: for ſays he, Simony is ſo odious in the eye of the Law,<note place="margin">Hughs Pars, Law. c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> that (the Church being void) if a man ſeeks for money to be preſented: although afterwards the Patron preſent him
<hi>gratis;</hi> it was Lord chief Baron <hi>Tanfield</hi>'s opinion, in his argument, in <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Kitchin</hi>'s Caſe in the Exchequer: that for the Simoniacal attempt only, he is diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to take the ſame Benefice. 'Tis the intention St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſo ſeverely ſentenced, charging him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>That his heart was not right in the ſight of God.</hi> And again, <hi>repent therefore, if perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the thought of thy heart may be forgiven thee.</hi> Yet this thought could make none guilty <hi>in foro huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> without ſome overt act to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it. And thus go the Decretals,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:93734:47"/>If he be detected,<note place="margin">I. q.
<hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quodvis praemium ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuliſſe, ex eodem tempore, noverit ſe eſſe anathematis opprobrio condemnatum,</hi> He was anathematized for offering a gift. And <hi>Gratian</hi> affirms from <hi>Greg. Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Qui ſtudet donum Dei pretio merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> &amp;c. if he caſt about to do it, 'tis a Capital crime, and Simoniacal hereſy. Chriſt whipt the Buyers and Sellers for offering to ſale and cheapening. And
<hi>Gregory</hi> tells <hi>Siagrius. Qui ultro ambit vel importunè ſe ingerit, eſt procul dubio repellendus:</hi> for ſays he, men ſhould not enter the Church <hi>ſuffragio venditorum,</hi> but <hi>judicio Dei:</hi> not by the Mercenary Votes of Men, but by the judgment of God: which appears only when mens judgments are not corrupted with testations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis an unlawful promotion by Simoniacal means, though the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent be not privy to it: no nor Patron neither. For he is (as the Canons diſtinguiſh) <hi>Simoniacè promotus,</hi> though he be not
<hi>Simoniacus.</hi> In conſcience he hath no call from God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>C.</hi> 17. <hi>Num.</hi> 16.</note> and in Law, the Benefice is void: yet here as <hi>Navar</hi> obſerves, the Incumbent falls not under Excommunication. It was never thought fit, men ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:93734:47"/>in the Church by ſin, though none of their own. <hi>Degg</hi> ſhews in a caſe of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Potter,</hi> 17
<hi>Jac.</hi> in the King's Bench, that neither Patron nor Incumbent were Privees, yet the Church was void by Simony.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To contract with a Father, or any other, for a Living, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a marriage, aſſoon as it ſhall fall void is unlawful. That this is Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony by the Canon is proved before, <hi>Nulli liceat Eccleſiam nomine dotalitatis ad aliquem transferre.</hi> And the Act, 31
<hi>Eliz.</hi> 6. compriſes it, in thoſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral words. <hi>If any Perſon for any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, directly or indirectly, ſhall preſent,</hi> &amp;c. A benefit it is, for it goes in lieu of a Portion in whole or part. And (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der favour) 'tis beneath the gravity and learning of a Judge, to ſay the Covenant is good, if the words (in conſideration of a Marriage) be not there: for that were to ſubmit hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to ſubtilty: and to make the beſt Laws a tye to none but Fools, and to trammel Juſtice with Letters and Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables. Yea, tis to make Juſtice pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh words rather than things; ſince the fact will be declared innocent, if it be not ill worded. The Crime is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:93734:48"/>in truth, that the Patron robs the Church for his Childs portion; and chuſes to be ſacrilegious rather than his Daughter ſhall want a Husband. If the Incumbent will appeal to his own conſcience, he might as well have paid 200 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> for it; unleſs he be a man of very deſpicable parts and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis unlawful to perſwade others to give or promiſe any Penſion or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to procure a Living. This is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and Civil Law, that they ſo heavily anathematize:<note place="margin">Nomoc. tit. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> Schol.</note> this is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of
<hi>Photius.</hi> And ſo doth our Law condemn it too; elſe how came the Incumbent then in the Univerſity and knowing nothing of the bargain to be outed for Simony, which he never medled in, as in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> and Rogers Caſe?<note place="margin">Cro. Eliz <hi>788.</hi>
               </note> And in <hi>Fowler</hi> and <hi>Lapthorn</hi>'s Caſe 17. <hi>Jac.</hi> in the Kings Bench. So that ſuch Setters mend not the matter, but make it worſe, and are often inſtruments of diſcovery and witneſſes of truth. <hi>Arſenius</hi> the Monk, makes them all as guilty as <hi>Simon Mugus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Synopſis Can. c. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> not only Preſenter and Preſentee: but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:93734:48"/>which he proves by the Apoſtolical and
<hi>Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Canons, though he miſtake the 22d for the 2d. And they are likewiſe condemned by the 6th and 7th Synod, by <hi>Tharaſius</hi> Epiſtle, and St. <hi>Baſil</hi>'s 85 Canon, and <hi>Gennadius</hi> the Patriarchs Epiſtle: which is evidence enough of the Churches judgment in this caſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis not lawful to give any Bonds or Covenants, that may hinder the Incumbent, from the full enjoyment of the Church, and all its profits du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring life. As is plain by all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, but is more particularly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt in that of <hi>Photius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nomoc. tit.
<hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> Schol.</note> where he tells us, not only Money giving is condemned, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of what kind ſoever: all Bonds by Sureties, and all Pledges <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are there decreed to be void; which Decrees he takes out of the Canons, and civil Law. And our Canons for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the Patron to take <hi>aliquod emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum pacto interveniente.</hi> And elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>nullam pactionem inierit,</hi> he ſhall make no bargain at all. And the Conſtitutions of
<hi>Othobon</hi> the Legate
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:93734:49"/>made <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1268,<note place="margin">Lind. l. <hi>5.</hi> tit. <hi>3.</hi> c. nulli liceat. Conſt Othob. tit. <hi>33.</hi> c. quia plerunque.</note> 
               <hi>univerſas promiſſiones &amp; pactiones penitus revocat;</hi> all Bonds, Contracts, Bargains, are void of what kind ſoever, made in conſideration of a Preſentation. Nor is the Statute much ſhort, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides,
<q rend="margQuotes">If any Perſon by reaſon of any Bond—for any Benefit, whatſoever di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ſhall Preſent,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is void.</q> Will not the word <hi>any Bond</hi> contain charitable Bonds? nor Bonds for Reſignation? 'Tis believed Patrons would not trouble themſelves about Bonds for no benefit whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Hence Juſtice <hi>Foſter</hi> is ſuſpected of too little reaſon or honeſty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Noy.</hi> 142.</note> that was ſo earneſt in <hi>Baker</hi> and <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>'s caſe, to declare a Bond taken by the Patron from the Preſentee to pay 10 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum</hi> to his Predeceſſors Son, in the Univerſity, whilſt unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, a good Bond: though he offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a precedent for it, in the Earl of <hi>Suſſex</hi> caſe; where he ſaid, a like Bond for payment of 5
<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> to his Predeceſſors Widow, was held lawful: for both are alike unreaſonable, as will appear upon theſe enſuing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:93734:49"/>
            <p n="1">1. That the Patron hath no right to all, or any part of the profits: and therefore can no more diſpoſe them, than of any other mans eſtate. The Ordinary hath the profits <hi>tempore va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis:</hi> the Parſon hath the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold: and the Fee-ſimple is <hi>in nubibus, in abeiance, in gremio legis,</hi> ſays Sir <hi>Edw. Cooke.</hi> There are ſome that hold the Fee-ſimple in the Parſon: but none ever thought it in the Patron.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 23.</note> You may ſee this point well diſcuſſed by Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> of <hi>Grayes Inn,</hi> in his
<hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Law:</hi> where he gives the reaſon of the Laws policy, to be, to avoid alienations and diſſeiſins to be made by the Church or any other. And in truth the right of Patronage,<note place="margin">Cowell in v. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronus.</note> is <hi>jus praeſentandi Clericum ad eccleſiam vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ex parte ei conceſſum: qui conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiente Epiſcopo, vel inſtruxit, vel dot avit eccleſiam.</hi> 'Tis a right to preſent a Clark to a vacant Church, granted to him in part, who (with the Biſhops conſent) either built or endowed the Church. And much to the ſame purpoſe is it deſcribed by the Gloſs in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciale vetus,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">L.
<hi>2.</hi> tit. <hi>2.</hi> cap. circumſpecti a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatis.</note> 
               <hi>Jus Patronatus eſt honorificum jus, oneroſum &amp; utile, competens alicui in eccleſia, pro eo quod
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:93734:50"/>Diaeceſani autoritate illam fundavit, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavit vel conſtruxit ipſe: vel is a quo juſtam cauſam habet.</hi>
'Tis an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burdenſome and uſeful right in a Church, accruing to any one, for that he founded, endowed or built it, by the authority of the Dioceſan; either himſelf; or ſome other from whom he claims. So that (ſays the <hi>gloſſe</hi>) <hi>non reſpicit oblationes vel decimas.</hi> It relates not to Offerings and Tythes, but would remain if they were taken away. Nor will that which we call an Advowſon, give him better right, to convert the profits, to any other uſe than the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: for
<hi>Cook</hi>'s Inſtit.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi>
240.</note> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 17. out of <hi>Bracton,</hi> calls it a power to preſent to a Church in his own name, not in anothers: ſtill it relates to the Church, not to its profits; which Law and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom kept out of his fingers. But whoever ſhall conſider the tremendu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous circumſtances, with which the Inſtruments of Foundation, Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or both, were offer'd upon the Altar; to deveſt and diſſeiſe, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their heirs, of the building Gleabes and profits: and to put all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right and poſſeſſion of Almighty God, and his Church, with the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:93734:50"/>Imprecations, upon all that ſhould attempt, to alter, or diminiſh it, would wonder any after-ages would venture to touch the Anathema, and thereby intitle themſelves to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Curſes: but of this before: Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons are Advocates; 'tis ſtrange they ſhould prove Adverſaries: <hi>Patroni à patrocinio</hi> not <hi>à latrocinio.</hi> Their duty is to find out a good Shepherd for the flock: not a Simoniack for his Purſe.</p>
            <p>How early this Right of Patronage came into the Church, may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd by <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Law contain'd in the Novels: where he provides,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Novell.</hi> 57. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> That if any built a Church and endowed it: he might preſent a Clark to it: but the Patriarch might refuſe to ordain him, if he judged him not fit for the ſervice. And by another Law he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Novell.</hi>
123. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> as a ſuppliment to the former, That if the Patron nominated an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Perſon to the Church ſo built and endowed; the Biſhop might both refuſe him, and prefer whom he judged worthy: that ſo Patrons might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent worthy men or loſe their Right. Both theſe Laws imply, that the Right accrues from the foundation of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:93734:51"/>Church: yet was it never ſo abſolute, but the Biſhop had a Negative voice, upon the Patron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Some think the Peoples rights of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, were ſwallowed up by this Advancement of Patrons. But 'tis very plain by all the debates of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that though many things are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced or producible out of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, about the Peoples Rights in chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Biſhops; yet there is no foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtep of any ſuch Right to chooſe Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, or Parochial or Congregational Miniſters: which yet is the point in iſſue, between the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and their Adverſaries. And 'tis pity it is no more minded by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigants on both ſides. For whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Canon gives people any Right, gives it in conjunction with the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: but what Clergy are there to chooſe in a ſingle Congregation? And if there were, what need they chooſe another to make a Paſtoral Relation? muſt there be Paſtors upon Paſtors <hi>in Infinitum?</hi> Hath not the Church of <hi>Virginia</hi> authority to ſend a Paſtor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Indians,</hi> to feed them with the word and, doctrine; and baptize them upon that command, <hi>Go teach
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:93734:51"/>all nations and baptize them:</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the peoples choice? Will any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, he can preach no otherwiſe than as a gifted Brother among them? This <hi>New England</hi> fancy, hath hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the ſalvation of the <hi>Indians</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: And had the Apoſtles and Elders believed it, had hindred the ſalvation of the world.</p>
            <p>Men ſhould conſider, that in the Primitive times, there were no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes to chooſe; nor did the People pay the Presbyters but the Biſhop. Nor were they ſo fixt in any place,<note place="margin">Pallad. in vita Chrys.</note> as not to be moveable at the diſcretion of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> maintained many Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters (whom he ſent to preach in <hi>Phaenicia</hi>) at his own charge. Nor did the world know any other diſtinction, but of City and Regionary Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. They were bred up in the Church, from Lectors, Acolytes, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſts, Sub-deacons, Deacons, Prieſts, in all which offices they uſually ſtaid ſome time; and were advanced at the diſcretion of the Biſhop, without the People. Nor were they permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to convert any offering, made in the Country, to their own uſe, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for it at the City Altar.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:93734:52"/>
            <p>Nor do we hear any Complaints of the people, againſt the uſurpations of theſe Patrons, now newly erected: which we may reaſonably believe they would have done, had they found any Law of God broken, or cuſtom of the Church alter'd, or Rights of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple invaded, or Miniſters obtruded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the uſual practice. Theſe things conſider'd, an unprejudiced mind will be ſatisfied, the people never had nor uſed any right, in chooſing Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational guides: whatever they might do in Electing Biſhops: whom they owned as compleat Paſtors, for wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and cenſures too: and from whom they received their Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and to whom they made their Offerings.</p>
            <p>Nor are the Patrons Antichriſtian (as ſome are pleaſed to call them) whilſt they conſcientiouſly manage, their Right of Praeſentation: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe ſacrilegious practiſes: but are lovers of their Nation and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in building them Synagogues. And might have expected prayers and thanks from any but theſe murmurers; that defame what they cannot imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:93734:52"/>
            <p>A good Author tells us,<note place="margin">Dugd. View of our troubles. c. <hi>35.</hi> p. <hi>411.</hi>
               </note> that ſome in
<hi>Praiſe-God Barebones</hi> Parliament, <hi>Dec.</hi> 13, 1653, were earneſtly voting down Patrons: but others urged, that this was an attempt to deſtroy the Subjects Property; and that ended the debate. Our diſſenting Brethren ſo far favour that Anabaptiſtical fury, in complaining of Patrons invading the peoples Rights, as if they meant to eſpouſe their folly. Queſtionleſs Patrons are apprehenſive enough, that Diſſenters Principles can't take place, but by their ruine; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will keep a watchful Eye upon them. But I return, and am only to diſſwade them from the ill uſe of that Spiritual Truſt that is in their hands.</p>
            <p>If the Patron will be charitable,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 7.
<hi>ep.</hi> 110.</note> he ought alſo to be juſt: and not to rob for a Burnt offering. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, hath vehemently laſhed this wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; telling men they were more loaden by their Sacrilege, than eaſed by their Charity. That 'twas one thing to give Alms to purge our ſins: and another to ſin that we may give Alms. He ſays the rule is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>honour the Lord with thy ſubſtance, not with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:93734:53"/>mens.</hi> Did not Juſtice <hi>Foſter</hi> know, that the ſacrifice of the wicked, was an abomination to the Lord. Is not this to rob the Spouſe of Chriſt for an offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her Husband? to ſacrifice the Prieſt for atoning of the Deity: or like <hi>Judas</hi> to relieve the Poor with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours ointment; O blind hypocriſy, that expects Grapes from Thorns: and to receive good for doing evil.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe charitable Bonds, are a very compendious way to ſtarve Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion out of the world. For if the Patron may give 5
<abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> to the Widow, why not 10 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> to the Daughter; and 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> more to the uſe of the Poor: and as much more to repair High-ways, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and require Bonds for all theſe: And Juſtice <hi>Foſter</hi> declare them good. 'Tis eaſy to cut large Cantals out of another mans Loaf. And the <hi>Logici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> will tell him, <hi>a quatenus ad omne valet argumentum;</hi> If one be lawful, all of the ſame kind are. We may preſume all honeſt Lawyers aſhamed of the Deciſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Should theſe charitable Bonds be judged good, corrupt Patrons might by this colour avoid all Convictions of Simony. For what is more eaſy
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:93734:53"/>than to take Bonds in others names, for our own advantage? Can men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want pretences for Charity? are poor ſuch rare and ſcarce Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? Is it meet for Courts of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature to aſſiſt ſuch avaricious Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms, to baffle the wiſdom of the whole Nation at once. And render their juſt and holy Laws ridiculous? In the Act againſt Simony; <hi>England</hi> hath ſhewed its love to Learning and Religion, as well as to Juſtice and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: and is it not ſad, if a falſe hearted Bond, diſguiſed under a cloak of charity, ſhould render all vain? All the wine of Conſolation to Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Piety, may be drawn out at this one Tap of feigned charity. Should the Lawyers declare the Law in favour of theſe Bonds, they would but encourage Sacrilege, and help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward theſe Patrons damnation: and ſtain the Reverend Scarlet, by ſharing in the ſin; and ſuppreſs the Law to ſupport the Malefactor. But let the Simoniſt remember, if he eſcape this Bar, there is another; at which the conſcience will tell the whole Story: and then the Sentence will be, <hi>Thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney periſh with thee.</hi> O voice of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:93734:54"/>Thunder! but a ſtony heart can't hear it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. 'Tis Simony to give Bonds for Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation at the Patrons pleaſure, though upon pretence of a Son to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red when fit.
'Tis true at firſt bluſh, this Plea ſeems reaſonable:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Crook. p.</hi> 2. 248.</note> and found favour 8.
<hi>Jac.</hi> in <hi>Jones</hi> and <hi>Lawrences</hi> caſe, as Sir
<hi>Geeorge Crook</hi> reports it. And ſo did another 5 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. in the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Crook. Car.</hi> 1.180.</note> between <hi>Babington</hi> and <hi>Wood,</hi> reported by the ſame Author: where was no pretence of a Son. But 'tis ſaid, that in neither of theſe caſes, was any Simoniacal contract averred: otherwiſe it might have been doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful:<note place="margin">Pars Counſ. part <hi>1.</hi> c.
<hi>5.</hi>
               </note> whether the Bonds would have been found good or not, ſays Sir <hi>Simon Degge.</hi> Nor was it likely the Incumbent ſhould alledge a Simonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Contract, for then the Living was void, and himſelf outed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Noy</hi> 22.</note> Yet this Gentleman mentions a caſe in
<hi>Noy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Clerk and Paſchal Trin. 15. <hi>Jac.</hi> in <hi>C. B.</hi> where the Bond for Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at pleaſure was ſued, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Simoniacal: but then the Church is declared void by ſuch judgment, the Incumbent carrying the cauſe, but loſing his Benefice; and is uncapable
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:93734:54"/>of it for ever, though the King ſhould pardon the Simony, and preſent him afreſh.</p>
            <p>But to clear this matter, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, 1. That all the Arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt charitable Bonds conclude as ſtrongly againſt theſe: but would be tedious to repeat.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That if they ſhould not prove Simony in Law, yet would be ſo in conſcience; and likewiſe in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law: which forbids all contracts whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Patrons by theſe Bonds, act a moſt inſolent and arbitrary power: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Liberties of the Church, and all the Subjects of this Kingdom beſide. The Church in <hi>Magna Charta</hi> made at
<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 10 <hi>Feb. Anno</hi> 9. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1224, is the firſt Subject of Liberty; in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Where the King granteth to God: and for him and his Heirs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhall be free, and have all her Rights and Liberties inviolable. One of which was to enter upon her Cures without Compacts and Bargains with Patrons; as appears by the Canons made at <hi>London</hi> in the reign of <hi>Henry</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:93734:55"/>the 2d, and his Son then crown'd King: and by thoſe of <hi>Stephen Langton</hi> made but two years before; as alſo by the Canons of the four firſt general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels,<note place="margin">Hiſt. eccleſiae Angl. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> which were received in
<hi>England</hi> ſays <hi>Bede</hi> long before, and are ſo ſtill, ſays the Statute <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. To impoſe Oaths, Bonds, Contracts upon Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Sheriffs, Knights and Burgeſſes in Parliament, Conſtables, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, Overſeers, more than the Law impoſes, would be thought arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and tyrannical Oppreſſion; and can it be leſs to impoſe ſuch obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the Rectors or Vicars of the Churches? Muſt they enter the Church as Felons, their tryals with Gives and Fetters? Muſt they preach to the Patrons as St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Agrippa</hi> in Chains? May not an Angel of the Church be truſted, till bound to his good behaviour? Who ever laid Shac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles on any Embaſſadors but theſe of Chriſt? the Shepherd is uſed like a Dog; the Patron having put a Rope about his Neck to pull him up or out at his pleaſure. O vain name of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty whoſe ſenſe is bondage!</p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe Bonds may endanger the Proteſtant Religion; for if Patrons
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:93734:55"/>be Popiſh, how dare men in theſe Obligations, reprove it, or confirm their people againſt it? May not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have Sons to prefer as well as Proteſtants? Or have that Sect only no patronages in their hands? The Dog muſt come over at his call that holds the ſtring, whether into Popery or Fanaticiſme. When King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament can't ſilence ſome baſtard Teachers; theſe Patrons can at a word ſilence the moſt Orthodox Divine: if any ſuch enter their Bonds.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Theſe Bonds include a greater Hereſy, then any yet, this fruitful age and Nation hath brought forth. For it preſumes the Miniſterial calling to be for term of years: that God's people may be leaſed out to a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. That he is but a Hireling and <hi>Curatus pro tempore,</hi> whoſe own the Sheep are not, but the Sons. That Prieſts may be laid aſide for no cauſe but the Patrons pleaſure, which tends directly to make him careleſs, to follow the world, and make Hay while the Sun ſhines. Not to conſider the people as his charge, nor to think of living and dying with them; nor of making any account for them.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:93734:56"/>Nor to plant on the Gleab, nor to repair the Houſes or Chancels: but to graſp what he can, becauſe his time may be ſhort. But ſeriouſly, do theſe men think <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Patent was during pleaſure? Was Chriſt leſs than a Prieſt for ever? Was it not a ſad cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, when <hi>Annas</hi> and
<hi>Caiaphas</hi> were high Prieſts for years? Can they think it fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move a Miniſter when he beſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands his people; and bring in an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Novice, becauſe called my ſon? Are they fit for the Kingdom of God, that look back when they have put their hand to the Plough? The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in Chriſt's Vineyard, came in at ſeveral hours, but went out al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, when the dark covering of death ſhut up their day. Our Canons forbid any Prieſts to relinquiſh their calling,<note place="margin">Can. <hi>3.</hi> Jac. can. <hi>76.</hi>
               </note> or to uſe themſelves after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as Laymen upon pain of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication. <hi>Ames</hi> propounds this Queſtion,<note place="margin">Ames. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> n. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>An vocatio ad Miniſterium inſtitui poſſit ad certos annos;</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, <hi>Repugnat planè miniſterii na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> and gives theſe reaſons for it. 1. God hath not allowed it. 2. It a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates affection between Prieſt and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:93734:56"/>People. 3. It makes the dignity of the calling ſeem mercenary. 4. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and People may part to both their prejudice.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>N.</hi> 35.</note> And again tells us what cauſes may juſtify a parting from ones calling. <hi>Si tamen cauſa talis inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedat quae vel ineptum aliquem reddat ad miniſterium exercendum, vel exercitium ejus impoſſibile reddit, velpeccandi neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem adfert exercenti, turn nutu divino ſolvi videtur.</hi> 'Tis certain
<hi>Athanaſius, Nazianzen, Chryſoſtom,</hi> &amp;c. were remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from their Churches, but by Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, not Patrons. And many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for Hereſy or Schiſm; but then 'twas by ſentence of the Church, or State, or both: but never by ſingle Patrons. They ſo ruffle all Laws Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane, that the Lawyers can ſcarce reſolve where the Freehold is, when the Incumbent is a <hi>Farmer at pleaſure.</hi> Theſe men make havock of Chriſt's Inſtitutions, and put Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles on the Noſe of Religion as they liſt. They make Prieſts as ſummer Inſects to be meer Ephemeriſts. If the Incumbent ſay with St. <hi>Paul, We be to me if I preach not the Goſpel:</hi> theſe Gold-ſuckers tell him, you ſhall then preach with
<hi>Bede</hi> to the Quarries, or
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:93734:57"/>with <hi>Orpheus</hi> to the Trees; for we will remove you to make way for our Sons. Thus is Chriſt's, Steward turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his Houſe, without leave or privity of the Maſter.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The care to prefer Sons ſeems natural, but was never judged ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. Old <hi>Eli</hi> was ruin'd for honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sons before God. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.29. And the Decretals treating of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical profits,<note place="margin">16. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>pervenit.</hi>
               </note> complain of the ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing them to unfitting perſons, <hi>vel quod gravius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eſt etiam Conſanguineis;</hi> as if giving them to Kinſmen were the greateſt crime of all. And the rules were, <hi>eſt honeſtum officium ſiliam dotare non tamen ex bonis eccleſiaſticis.</hi> And
<hi>cognatosi juvare ut decenter vivant:</hi> but not to proſtitute the Church to them, as <hi>Soto Cajetan Bannes</hi> &amp;c. affirm. And care was taken in the Election of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as <hi>Balſamon</hi>'s Collections ſhew,<note place="margin">Tit. <hi>3.</hi> n. <hi>41.</hi> ex lib. <hi>1.</hi> cod.</note> that they ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they ſhould have no Sons or Nephews, leſt they ſhould act naturally, and prefer them to the prejudice of Religion. The Law confined Prieſts to one tribe, but theſe like the Heatheniſh ſuperſtition, would confine it to one family. As
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:93734:57"/>the <hi>Pinarii</hi> only could be Prieſts of <hi>Hercules;</hi> and the <hi>Eumolpidae</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> the only Sacrificers to <hi>Ceres.</hi> It ſeems a kind of diſheriſon, to the Patrons Sons, if Churches be not kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Paſtors, by hirelings, till they be fit. Though they may never live to it, nor receive any internal Call: nor affect the imployment; nor be grave or learned enough for it. One would think both Patron and Judges believed Sons put Apprentice to learn the Trade of Prieſthood, and would be out of their time at a certain day, and the Churches were but Shops kept open for them to ſet up in. They may well forgive us, if we think the Atheiſts that deal thus rudely with Religion.<note place="margin">Cokes Jnſt. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>71.</hi> f. <hi>154.</hi>
               </note> Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> produces an old Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram by Which we may ſee what kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Church hath had for theſe Kinſmen.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quatuor Eccleſias Portis intratur in omnes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſaris &amp; Simonis, Sanguinis atque Dei.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prima patet Magnis; Nummo patet altera; Charis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tertia; ſed paucis Quarta patere ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:93734:58"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>By twice two Gates all Churches en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſars, and Simons, Kindred, and Deitie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nobles the firſt; the ſecond Rich men take.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Kin the third; the fourth moſt forſake.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p n="7">7. This Cloak will ſerve to cover all Simony whatſoever; for though ſome have no ſons, they may have Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which would make Sons-in-Law; they may have Grand-ſons, Nephews, Couſins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is it in no degree natural to keep open Livings for them? Doth not nature tye us to provide for Relations ſooner than Strangers? 'Twas never known the Pope wanted a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew for a preferment. One would think Churches were founded not ſo much to ſerve God as theſe Patrons: whoſe Family muſt be ſupported though on the ruines of Religion. But ſtay, how can men eſcape the edge of the Statute by theſe Bonds? ſince it declares, all Bonds given in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a Preſentation, do make that Preſentation void; if they are of any profit or benefit whatſoever. Now can any man ſatisfy his conſcience,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:93734:58"/>that he which takes the Bond is in no better condition, than if he had none. Do not all men believe, he can make Money of it, if he will? Is there no Market in which ſuch a Bond would ſell? Doth not the account of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron and Incumbent both reckon it at 300 or 400
<abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> Can't the Patron de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand 10, or 20
<abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> from the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent every year? and dares he deny him, and ſo be outed of his uſefulneſs and livelihood together. The weakeſt eye can look through this thin Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>web, and much more the ſtrong judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Reverend Bench.</p>
            <p>But let us contemplate a while, what dangerous Tools theſe Bonds are to the Common-wealth. Men marry their Daughters to Incumbents, in hope of a comfortable ſubſiſtence. At length theſe Bonds put forth their horns, and toſs the Fathers hopes into the pit of deſpair. Or peradventure the Patron wants an Oath, which if the Incumbent will not lend him, this cloſe Cur is ſlipt upon him, and worries him out of a thouſand Marks. To have offer'd him Money, had been ſubornation , though but five pounds but to ſue theſe Bonds,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:93734:59"/>find favour in the Court. May not the Patron thus force an unpleaſant Kinſwoman, whom he cannot love, and ſo ruine two at once? May he not force him to relinquiſh the juſteſt ſuit againſt a Pariſhioner by trumping up this Bond againſt him? May he not by theſe curſed ways, rob any Pariſh of the moſt painful and edifying Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, whom their ſouls moſt dearly affect? and tye the Incumbent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Compoſitions? yea (which is worſe) to wink at their Patrons ſins; and proſtitute the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to a Soul more unclean than the common Shoars. This poor man muſt find a 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> to buy pins for the Patrons Miſs, if he require it. Nay the honeſt Neighbours that lend the Incumbent Money for neceſſary uſe: having an eye to his Parſonage to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage their credit: if theſe Bonds prevail , are trapan'd out of their Money. Bleſſed God! what a <hi>lernae malorum</hi> is here?
'Tis not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but a true Patriot will never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure theſe private Daggers, that ſerve to murder publick ſafety.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Theſe Bonds are injurious to every man in
<hi>England,</hi> beſides the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:93734:59"/>Patrons: for they, their Sons or Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are capable (upon due qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation) to be preſented to theſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings: and ought by all Laws divine and humane, to enjoy the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits for their lives, that the Laws of the Kingdom, and the charity of well diſpoſed perſons have ſetled upon them. Theſe profits are not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons inheritance, that they ſhould ſuck profit from them; but the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that can qualify themſelves for them. Nor have Patrons Sons any advantage above other people that way; ſince a vacant Church muſt be diſpoſed in ſix months or lapſed, be their Sons ready or unready. If it be a crime to invade the rights of any one; much more it is to uſurp upon all. So that this practiſe is not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: it robs whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at once. Accordingly, we ought to run to ſuppreſs it as a Common fire, that threatens deſtruction to the whole Neighbourhood, and to treat them that uſurp as Beaſts of prey.</p>
            <p>I have met with one inſtance of this corrupted practiſe, older than one hundred years. And that was of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> a <hi>Patrician,</hi> advanced to the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:93734:60"/>Empire of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> about the year 923, who (the better to ſecure the Soveraignty to himſelf and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) made his two eldeſt Sons, <hi>Stephen</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine Caeſars;</hi> and reſolved to create his younger Son <hi>Theophylact</hi> Patriarch (if poſſible) of the Royal City. To that end, he was put into the Clergy at Eleven years of age:<note place="margin">Curopal. Zonar.</note> and was made Patriarch ſay ſome at ſixteen; he ſhould have been, but that he was a Minor ſay others;<note place="margin">Niceph.</note> and ſo could not receive it in that vacancy. Upon which <hi>Romanus</hi> promoted
<hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> the <hi>Monk,</hi> to the Patriarchal Chair; but under Covenants to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to his Son <hi>Theophylact,</hi> when he ſhould attain the of age twenty five years. At which period <hi>Tryphon</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to reſign, averring the Bonds ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted and unlawful. To judge which, the Emperor called a Synod of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Biſhops, who were aſhamed of the Fact, and would not juſtify the Contract, nor condemn the Patriarch, for refuſing to recede, as a thing hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridly ſcandalous. But admitted an accuſation againſt him, as an illiterate man, and therefore unworthy the Chair. One under pretence of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:93734:60"/>went to him, and informed him of the accuſation, deſiring him to write his Name and Titles upon a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which he would ſhew the Synod, to the utter confutation of his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. Which when the poor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch had done, a Reſignation of the Patriarchate, was written, above his name and deliver'd to the Synod. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which, they inaugurated young <hi>Theophylact</hi> into the Chair of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, Anno Domini</hi> 944. Others I confeſs ſay <hi>Tryphon</hi> was but his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute till he came to that age. This young Patriarch ſuited well his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance; living but twelve years, and that in all kind of Luxury and Riot; minding Dogs and Horſes, more than Churches, and the Souls of men. And leaving nothing remarkable, but that (inſtead of feeding Chriſts Sheep) he fed 2000 Horſes with the profits of his Biſhoprick.<note place="margin">Cedrenus.</note> And better could not be expected, from ſuch an Entrance. He died, 956.</p>
            <p n="7">7. As we have ſhewed it no Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to purchaſe an Advowſon in Fee; ſo 'tis as plain Simony to purchaſe the next Preſentation: eſpecially if the Church be empty, or the Incumbent
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:93734:61"/>ſick or aged. This is <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> though haply not <hi>malum prohibitum.</hi> For here 'tis preſumed the intention is Simoniacal. And in truth the right of Patronage is not ſalable at all, if it be a ſpiritual thing only: but in <hi>England</hi>
'tis accounted by ſome a meer temporal thing. But by the moſt and beſt,
'tis reckon'd partly temporal,<note place="margin">V. Gloſ. <hi>1.</hi> q.
<hi>1.</hi> quod autem.</note> and partly ſpiritual: and ſo it will prove, for as <hi>Lindwood de jurejurando</hi> well notes, conſider it as deſcendable to heirs, and purchaſable in Fee; and ſo 'tis tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but
<hi>jus patronatus, &amp; praeſentatio, dicuntur ſpiritualia reſpectu rei ad quam praeſentatur: quae ſpiritualis eſt.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it as 'tis a preſentation to a Church, and to exerciſe divine offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſo 'tis ſpiritual. And all the profits of a Church are ſpiritual as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to God and his Service. And ſo is the Parſon preſented too.<note place="margin">Extra. de judic. c. quanto: ubi de hoc.</note> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the Canons determine their actions, to be managed <hi>in foro eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtico;</hi> but the cuſtom of <hi>England</hi> is otherwiſe. Now how much Patrons ſcrape out of theſe ſales of Advow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is not eaſy to imagine. Were the Church their Freehold, they could ſcarcely make more; and get the cure
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:93734:61"/>ſerved. <hi>Horne</hi> in his <hi>Speculum Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiariorum</hi> tells us, the Advowſon of a Church is ſo much in the ſpirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that there can be no alienation thereof but in Fee-ſimple.<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>2.</hi> ſ. <hi>27.</hi> ſub Titulo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts.</note> If this were the law under <hi>Edw.</hi> 1, and
<hi>Edw.</hi> 2, in whoſe reign, this Reverend Judge is ſaid to live: how came it to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd? and Contracts, <hi>pro hâc vice</hi> now thought lawful. Do the Lawyers change the Law at their pleaſure, as Sectaries do Religion? then is both Religion and Law ambulatory, and may both leave the Kingdom at length. We may yet hope a right <hi>Engliſh</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, will find time to retrench theſe Enormities, and new lopp this overgrown Tree of Avarice. In the mean time let Patrons know, that if Law allow it, conſcience cannot: for in them 'tis rapine, ſacrilege, betraying of truſt, living on what is none of their own; and enriching themſelves with Church-Revenues.<note place="margin">Com. In Luc. <hi>4.</hi> multi leproſi.</note> I wiſh they would hear St. <hi>Ambroſe, Malè quaeſitâ mercede non tam patrimonium faculta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tûm: quam the ſaurum criminum congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gârunt: aeterno ſupplicio &amp; brevi fructu.</hi> By ill got Goods, we increaſe our treaſure of ſins, rather than of Money,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:93734:62"/>little benefit, but everlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And again in his Book <hi>de dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Sacerdotali,</hi> he ſays <hi>Caro ſuſcepit dignitatem, &amp; anima perdidit honeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem:</hi> they receive Money into their pockets, and loſe honeſty out of their hearts. Our law doth ſo deteſt this avaricious courſe, that it hath made it puniſhable but to Elect a Scholar or Fellow
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">31 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 6.</note> into any Colledge for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: which is a ſmall thing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with preſenting a Prieſt to a Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Having laid down what is Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in Law and Conſcience, as far as we could judge, and occaſion offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; we muſt now conſider what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Common Law hath for it; by which we ſhall diſcover the true old <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpirit: that diſdained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice and falſhood, and ſcorned to do a contumelious action. The Abridger of our Statutes, ſays in the Preface; the whole Senate have beſtowed at leaſt half their time and induſtry, in hacking at part of the Branches, Boughs, Sprouts, Roots or Leaves of that monſtrous ugly, and hideous Tree <hi>Avaritia.</hi>—Yet it ſtill ſprouted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain like a <hi>Hydraes</hi> head in another
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:93734:62"/>form and different ſhape. But the Common Law, hath had the ſame bent and deſign. Simony is odious in the eye of the Common Law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 71. <hi>f.</hi>
153.</note> ſays <hi>Coke</hi> its greateſt Oracle: where he gives a double inſtance of it. A Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dein in Socage, may not preſent to a Living, becauſe he cannot account to the heir for it: as being of no value nor benefit to him. And therefore the Heir ſhall preſent, though he be under age. And alſo if an heir of Tenent <hi>in Capite,</hi> have Livery <hi>cum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itibus,</hi> yet ſhall the heir not preſent to an Advowſon,<note place="margin">V. Com. in ſtat. <hi>31.</hi> Eliz. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> becauſe no iſſues nor profits can be taken thereof. He far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thera ffirms, 'twas the more odious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe always accompanied with perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Again in another place, he tells us, the Common Law ſo much deteſted Simony, that before the Statute of
<hi>Weſtm.</hi> the 2d, no damages could be recover'd upon a <hi>Quare Impedit,</hi> leſt (ſays he), any profit the Patron ſhould take, ſhould ſavour of Simony. And this ſeems to me reaſonable enough yet ſtill: for if the Patron have coſts, why ſhould he have damage of that which never could be profit to him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Weſtm</hi>
2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>f.</hi> 362.</note> had he had it; and could be no dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:93734:63"/>of his Revenue, had he loſt it: but we muſt acquieſce in publick judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Yet he ſays, 'tis ſo with the King ſtill. For he can have no da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage upon his <hi>Quare impedit;</hi> becauſe he could not recover any by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law before; and that Statute helps him not, though it do the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</p>
            <p>And the ſame Author ſeems very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, Bonds for reſignation could not be ſued at Common Law; till the Statute of
<hi>Weſtm</hi> the 2d, for that the Incumbent once inſtituted and ſetled, the Patron could have no Writ to remove him,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. fol. <hi>357.</hi>
               </note> though wrongfully preſented; and gives theſe reaſons for it. 1. Becauſe having <hi>Curam animarum</hi> a great charge, he might the more effectually and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceably attend it. 2. Becauſe he came in by a Judicial Act from the Biſhop, to the Church: who is ſuppoſed in Law to act <hi>Scrutatis Archivis.</hi> And the form of Inſtitution implies no leſs: for the <hi>Te inſtituo ad tale beneficium, &amp; habere curam animarum. Et accipe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram tuam &amp; meam;</hi> Accept thine and my Cure, ſignifies that the Biſhop gives him his own Cure: which alſo ſhews what <hi>Cowell</hi> meant by
<hi>jus patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:93734:63"/>ex parte Conceſſum:</hi> for the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop had ſtill a ſhare in that Right. Now while the Biſhop inſtitutes, and the Arch-deacon inducts for life; It would be ſtrange that the Patron ſhould have power to limit him, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt both at his pleaſure only.</p>
            <p>From hence we may ſee, how much the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſcience, formerly nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeated this ranck poyſon: which our degenerate age, ſo greedily devours. Let them never talk of tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that can ſo glibly ſwallow this accurſed thing. 'Tis a bleſſed ſight to behold this Nation ſhining in her integrity; when all others had blackt themſelves with this Sacred Villany. <hi>Photius</hi> that famous Patriarch, ſaith of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church; whether any Lay-man becomes Procurator of any holy place,<note place="margin">Nomoc. tit. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> ſch. in fine.</note> or receives any eccleſiaſtical Miniſtry:
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo falls on his Knees for pardon. And for the
<hi>German</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Churches, <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great ſays, <hi>in Galliarum vel Germaniae partibus, nullus ad ſacrum ordinem, ſine commodi datione perveniat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4.
<hi>ep.</hi> 51.</note> And for the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, we have obſerved ſomething of their guilt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and ſhall farther note their Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacal
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:93734:64"/>Laws. That men muſt <hi>concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare cum Camera Apoſtolicâ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Syntag. tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatuum.</note> which is flat Simony. <hi>Theodoricus a Niem;</hi> and the Decretals ſay, <hi>Pallium niſi dato commodo non dabatur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deſt. <hi>99.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Novit.</note> No Money no Pall, the price muſt be firſt agreed. They come open mouthed with
<hi>Judas, quid dabitis?</hi> what will you give? Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is a great part of the Pope's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue. <hi>Humphred</hi> attempts in his
<hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tano-Papiſmus</hi> againſt <hi>Campian</hi> to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate the ſeveral ways. <hi>Nummos corradunt pro licentiis</hi>— They ſcrape up Money for Licences, Diſpenſations, Abſolutions, Commutations, from Fornicators, Whores, <hi>Jews,</hi> ill-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted Bigamiſts, Homicides, Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacks: from ſuch as eat Milk-Meats, (ſc. in faſting days) and from them that officiate to the <hi>Greeks</hi> in <hi>Greek;</hi> to the
<hi>Latines</hi> in <hi>Latine:</hi> ſo many Proceſſes <hi>a Rota,</hi> Reſervations, Graces, Indulgences, Preventions, Proviſions, tradings of Dataries, Maſters of the Ceremonies, Porters, Officials, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonotaries, Advocates, Maſters of the Lead, Keepers of the Iron Gates; of the Privy Garden of the Popes and Cardinals: that <hi>Benedict</hi> the 12th doth jocularly tell us: another world muſt
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:93734:64"/>be created, to ſupply all their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſires. Bold <hi>Probus</hi> calls them all <hi>Romuleos vultures:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Probus epiſcopus Tullenſis in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. Annal.
<hi>1380.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Honorius</hi> 4th in particular, a Gold-Sucker.
<hi>Rome</hi> once ſaid of <hi>England,</hi> 'twas <hi>puteus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhauſtibilis;</hi> and <hi>England</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> they had
<hi>Sitim inexplebilem.</hi> Theſe greedy Simoniſts occaſion'd this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtich, nigh 300 years ſince.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Intus quis? Tu quis? Ego ſum. Quid quaeris? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t intrem.</l>
               <l>Fers aliquid? Non. Sta foris. En fero. Quid? Satis, intra.</l>
               <l>Knock, Knock; who's there? 'tis I. What ſeek'ſt? to enter:</l>
               <l>Bring'ſt ought? No. Stand. I bring. What? Well: come venture.</l>
            </q>
            <p>An Aſs loaden with Gold, may be ſure of a Pall, at
<hi>Rome:</hi> when a <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> (if poor) returns naked. But for this Church, few or none but <hi>Campian</hi> had ever impudence enough to charge this crime upon her; till of late, That honour and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both were baniſhed out of the heart, into the purſe. Till our own blood was dearer to us than our Saviour's, and our Nephews nigher of kin to us than our God. 'Twas
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:93734:65"/>gallant in our <hi>Richard</hi> the 1ſt, that he refuſed to ſee the Pope, though in the mouth of <hi>Tyber,</hi> and earneſtly deſired by <hi>Octavian</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Hoſtia,</hi> in diſdain of his Simony, having taken 700 marks of the Biſhop of
<hi>Mains;</hi> 1500 Marks for <hi>William</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi>'s Legantine authority, and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> as
<hi>Math. Paris</hi> and others note.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now ſhew to Patron and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent apart, The ſad conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that attend this vile practice, and ſo draw to a concluſion. We will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Patron and deſire him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider himſelf, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. A hearty Oppoſer of Learning and Religion, the two beſt things in the World, and ſo as a third Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, walks hand in hand with the <hi>Turk</hi> and the Devil. <hi>Gregor. Magnus,</hi> obſerved long ſince to <hi>Theodoric</hi> and <hi>Theobert</hi> Kings, of
<hi>France:</hi> That if we ſuffer men to get livings by Money, <hi>Non vitam corrigere, non mores compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ſtudeant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ep.</hi> 114.</note> 
               <hi>ſed divitias quibus honor ſacer emitur, ſatagunt congregare.</hi> Men will not ſtrive to commend themſelves to preferments, by a good life and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect manners, which prevail nothing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:93734:65"/>but to get money which commands all. And ſo deſtructive is this courſe to Learning,<note place="margin">Defen. Pacis. Part. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Marſilius</hi> of
<hi>Padua</hi> ſaith, becauſe covetous men get away their temporal means, the Clergy were generally inſufficient: and nigh four hundred of them in his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg could not ſpeak <hi>Latine.</hi> Nor is it likely ingenious men, ſhould take much pains to advance themſelves to a halter, and to become Patrons Bond-ſlaves: or their Curates, till their Sons come at age. A younger Brother from the Baudy-houſe rotten in wickedneſs is their beſt Chapman. Or a thick ſcull'd ſon of a Farmer, that hath learned to drink in the Country; and to tell the Colledges names in the Univerſity; at his Fathers charges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the next preferment. But this is to debauch both Church and State: to eclypſe the true glory of a Nation: and to render ſerious Piety, the moſt uſeleſs and deſpicable thing in the world:<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Hoſpit.</note> and to ſplit the Church into infinite Sects. I wiſh theſe Patrons would rather take that famous Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boniſt <hi>Claudius Eſpencaes</hi> advice.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:93734:66"/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>— Secum ipſe diu multumque requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</l>
                  <l>Ecquis apud Cives tanto ſit dignus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore?</l>
                  <l>Nec precibus, pretiove locum det; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſque citatis.</l>
                  <l>More ſed antiquo lecti proſcribat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perte</l>
                  <l>Pontificis nomen —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let Patrons long and much inquire,</l>
                  <l>Which of the Learned fits the Choire.</l>
                  <l>Nor prefer Letters, price, or ſpeed.</l>
                  <l>But publiſh names of Prieſts decreed</l>
                  <l>To chooſe them as in ancient meed.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p n="2">2. As a Betrayer of the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred truſt, devouring the Pupil-Church committed to his protection. A thing ſo baſe, he is fain to hide it in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; as Thieves do robberies; and Cut-throats murders. And ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentile, that none but fordid Spirits, can be got to tranſact it, and they are fain when asked, to cover it with a Lie; and bluſh at the ſudden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of any Stranger among them. The meaneſt wretches, think it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſgraceful to be actors in it.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:93734:66"/>'Tis carried on as Whoredome, by ſigns and half words: rather than openly diſcourſed; though between the Parties alone. 'Tis a Baſtard that none cares to own. It being no leſs diſhonour to theſe men, to purloine, than it was glory in their fathers to endow.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As an Excluder of the beſt men, from entring any Church, where he hath to do; had Patrons been ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in power, our Saviour himſelf, and all his Apoſtles had been excluded: and <hi>Annas</hi> and
<hi>Caiaphas</hi> admitted. Men of conſcience cannot, and men of parts, will not ſtoop to theſe ſinful Conditions.<note place="margin">Calv. Inſt. l.
<hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> ſect. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Nor is it (as
<hi>Calvin</hi> notes) the benefit of the Church, but of the Preſentee; that theſe men look after; as alſo their own; <hi>non ut eccleſiis fit proſpectum</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſediis qui accipiunt;</hi> and hence (as he goes on) they call it not <hi>Miniſterium</hi> but <hi>Beneficium:</hi> not ſervice but benefice, that they preſent to. Yea, theſe men would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the whole 630 fathers, in that famous Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> becauſe they were all againſt Contracts at Entrance, as appears by their 2d Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. Pious and humble men, refuſe
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:93734:67"/>to enter by this Golden Gate, where our Saviour would not. It ſeldom proves a kind Match, where Joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Jewels, are the only way of wooing: but extream bad, where Money is made the only call, and title to affection, between the Prieſt and People. Were St.
<hi>Peter</hi> a Patron, and one ſhould offer him Money, his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer would be, <hi>Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou thinkeſt the gift of God may be purchaſed, with money. Arnobius</hi> notes, that the firſt Chriſtians ſaw ſo much evil in Trade,<note place="margin">Arnob. l.
<hi>2.</hi> mihi <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> they were nigh condemning it: but they have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently condemned this already. How baſe muſt the houſe of God look? when pious and learned, the only veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Gold and Silver, are all exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? How coarſe the Eccleſiaſtical Batch, when all the flowre is bolted out, and nothing uſed but Bran. A ſad Garden, where the Flowers are all caſt out, and nothing left but Weeds. <hi>Dant veniam Corvis</hi> &amp; Let in all the Crows, and exclude the Doves. The ſcandals of the Church, lye much at the door of theſe Patrons; who by promoting leſs fitting men, have advanced the Separations. 'Tis
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:93734:67"/>a bold affront to Chriſt; to let him have no Ambaſſadors, but men of no Conſcience. Had there been more
<hi>Maecenas</hi>'s the Church had had more <hi>Maro</hi>'s: but <hi>Homer</hi> himſelf muſt be packing, if he have no pay.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As the ſole Reteiner of this Sin, in the World. God may be eaſed from this Sin: and Nations freed from the Scourge, that attends, would Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons give leave. Our Kings, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Laws,<note place="margin">Crooke,</note> and all (but one Judges Reports) are againſt it. The People cry it down. The Sectaries decry Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons and Patronages (for their ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritious choice and impoſitions) as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian. The Clergy muſt needs be againſt it, both in Conſcience and Intereſt; for what they do in this kind, muſt be the effect of moral force. If therefore Patrons pleaſe, God may have leſt diſhonour, the Church leſs ſcandal, the Kingdom leſs danger, and mens conſciences leſs trouble, by their laying aſide this crying ſin; and the world will have one ſpecies of ſin leſs than it had. If this may not be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we may reaſonably deſire with the
<hi>Sicilian</hi> (when <hi>Scipio</hi> the <hi>Praetor,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him a fool for his Patron)
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:93734:68"/>that we may have none at all: but that he would appoint him to his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. But why may we not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with them, to eaſe God of this trouble? do they not value? nor can never need his favour? Have they no ſouls to be ſaved? no Heaven to look after? no Hell to beware? no judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day to dread? no account to take care of? Is it all one, whether he pleaſe or diſpleaſe? O then we may fear the gingling of the Silver, makes them forget themſelves: and as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Ambr. In Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam. c. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Religioſarum audientiam Scripturarum tinnitus aeris excludit;</hi> and drowned the voice of the holy Scriptures, yes, and of their conſciences too.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let him ſee his danger to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Family. Did not <hi>Gehezi</hi> take Money, and with it a diſeaſe to him and his Heirs for ever? St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſerved upon it, <hi>facta. authoris ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oeſſio damnatur haeredis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Luc. c.
<hi>4.</hi> &amp; multi leproſi <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> The father eat the ſowre grapes, and ſet all his Families teeth on edge. He contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that curſe that eat up all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Did not <hi>Eſau</hi> take Money for his Birthright and bleſſing, and was made a ſpurious off-ſpring of
<hi>Iſaac</hi> for ever? <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:93734:68"/>and very deſervedly (ſays <hi>Greg. Nazi.</hi>) for how ſhould he come by ſalvation, that had ſold his Saviour? Who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the laſhes of Chriſt, but the Buyers and Sellers in the Temple? the reſt were ſent civilly away. Nor can any bring them in, whom Chriſt whipt out. Nor can they be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the holy Ghoſt, whom Chriſt ejected.</p>
            <p>Every Author can furniſh you with inſtances of the miſerable devaſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that Sacrilege hath made in the world: and Sacrilege (without doubt) it is, to uſurp to your own uſe, what is appropriate to divine Service: and Simony 'tis as a Merchandiſe of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things. Sacrilege, as it reſpects the profits: and Simony, as 'tis a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Spiritual calling. You are not the firſt that have done it; nor the firſt that have been ruined by it. <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us <hi>Theodectes</hi> was ſtruck blind for mixing Scriptures with his Tragedies: but what may we expect, that mix God's treaſure with our eſtate? The <hi>Phocians</hi> had ploughed away but a little of God's ground, and were ſentenced for it in a good ſumm, by that general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:93734:69"/>of <hi>Greece</hi> the <hi>Amphictions,</hi> which being refuſed, they were utterly rout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out. Our Fathers devoted our Church-maintainance to God, by their ſolemn vows at the Altar:
<hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> did no more: yet when they withdrew part, nothing but their ruine could expiate the crime, both dying away ſtrangely, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.1. Your families may grow fat, but not healthful by eating Church Revenues. In ancient time, none deſired or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted any ſuch thing, but indigent wretches,<note place="margin">Cic. Bruto in reliqiis Attici ep. ult.</note> as <hi>Cicero</hi> obſerves to <hi>Brutus: Templis Deorum immortalium imminet hominum egentium &amp; perditorum ſpes.</hi> And few in our Age are guilty of it, but very griping or very ſharking fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. And certainly the ways theſe proud and beggarly men propound for their riſe, will prove their ruine, ſince nothing can be more dangerous, than to build our Houſes ſo near the Flames of the Alrar. And fooliſh to expect God ſhould bleſs them in, and advance them upon the Ruin of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,<note place="margin">De non teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randis eccleſ.</note> and Property. 'Twere well, if the Gentry would often read the Collections of that learned and pious Gentleman, Sir <hi>Henry Spelman,</hi> and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:93734:69"/>they would ſoon diſcover the linger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poyſon men ſwallow, whilſt they greedily devour Church-Morſels. A thouſand Families have done it in our times; and a thouſand Families have periſhed by it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let the Patron conſider the Reſtitution he is bound to make, if he be worth it; or undergoe the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Iniquity for ever. For the ſaddeſt Lamentations, humbleſt Confeſſions, deepeſt Humiliations, ſharpeſt Contritions, loudeſt Ejula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and moſt heavenly ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will do no good, while we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our crimes. Let St. <hi>Aug.</hi> be the Caſuiſt, and he reſolves you:<note place="margin">Ad Macedon. ep. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si enim res aliena cum reddi poteſt, non red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur: non agitur paenitentia ſed fingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> If we reſtore not what we ſin'd in taking, when we can; we do not act repentance, but feign it. <hi>Huic pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitendi medicina non omnino prodeſt,</hi> this medicine of Repentance, neither cures his guilt, nor diſcharges his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. His prayers and tears are abomination to the Lord, becauſe he remains in a State of Simony and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice. This the Heathens underſtood as well as Chriſtians:<note place="margin">Cic. l.
<hi>2.</hi> de le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus.</note> for <hi>Cicero</hi> ſays,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:93734:70"/>'twas a chief Law amongſt them, <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius ne, audeto placare donis iram deorum: ſantè vota reddunto.</hi> Let not a wicked man attempt to pacifie God with gifts; but religiouſly obſerve his vows. Thus <hi>Heſiod</hi> directs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to pay all ſervices to God,<note place="margin">Epv. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> l. a.</note> chaſtly and purely cleared from guilt. If the mind be turn'd: the unjuſt gain muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd. Becauſe what defiled us, when we got it, will defile us while we keep it. Every days Deteiner is as every days freſh Robbery. Like a Thorn in the Fleſh, it ceaſes not to ranckle and prick, till it be drawn out. So that we muſt part with our unjuſt gain, or our juft God, With Spoil or Heaven, for both we cannot hold. We muſt leave our Gift unoffered,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.23.</note> till our Brother be ſatisfied for his wrongs. The Law is <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.15. <hi>If the wicked reſtore the Pledge, give again that he hath rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, walk in the Statutes of life, without committing iniquity, he ſhall ſurely live: he ſhall not die.</hi> And not only things unjuſtly gotten, but unjuſtly deſtroyed, require ſatisfaction: as a Beaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in a Neighbours pit. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.33. Or a ſtack of Corn ſet on fire. <hi>Exod.</hi>
22.6. Or ſtanding Corn. Yea
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:93734:70"/>all things got by plunder, or by cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſhall reſtore again. <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.4, 5. and if there were none alive to receive ſatisfaction, he was bound to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe it to the Lord.
<hi>Numb.</hi> 5.8. even to the Prieſt ſaith the Text; who is the Lord's appointed Receiver. But a Patron in the Caſuiſts judgment, is bound to reſtore, if he had but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted others to wrong the Church: for
<hi>Reſtituere tenetur, qui damnum non impedit cum ex officio deberet.</hi> He is bound to reſtore the damage he hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not in caſe he be obliged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend.<note place="margin">Navar. l. c. <hi>21.</hi> &amp; mult. alios.</note> Hence 'tis the definition calls Patronage <hi>jus oneroſum:</hi> for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron is bound to protect. And the word Advowſon ſuppoſes him an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate, as <hi>Leſſius</hi> notes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 2.
<hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi>
22. <hi>q.</hi> 62. <hi>art.</hi> 4.</note> yes (ſays <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi>) though he uſe no fraud to the Owner or the Law. And yet in this caſe is a moral force on the Preſentee, and a fraud upon the whole Law. Nor is it any great credit, by Quirks to baffle the deſign of a righteous Law.</p>
            <p>Let me upon the whole matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt theſe corrupt Patrons, in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to conſider themſelves lying on their
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:93734:71"/>death-bed, their Souls hovering upon their lips, ready to take its flight into another world: yet afraid to go off, becauſe of the juſt judgment of God at hand: not knowing how to make Reſtitution, and leſs what to anſwer for the robberies committed on the Church by Simony. To reſtore, will weaken his Eſtate, and abate his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens portions. Not to reſtore, leaves him to die impenitent, and to appear at that Tribunal beſmeared all over with guilt. He could haply die for his Children; but to be damn'd for them to Eternity, he thinks hard, his Soul ſhrinks at it: and now counts it a ſad bargain, to loſe heaven and glory for theſe trifles. He now wiſhes he had never known Patronages nor Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Bonds nor Obligations. And at length in deſperation, caſts down (with <hi>Judas</hi>) the gains of iniquity, crying out, <hi>I have ſinned in betraying the Church of God;</hi> and ſo expires his laſt breath in flaming diſcontent. O horrid ſpectacle! fit only for Devils to behold, and Furies to attend: fit to draw tears of bloud from his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens eyes: and groans from his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors Loyns, and ſorrowful Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:93734:71"/>from all his Acquaintance; as too ſad an Evidence of an unhappy bargain in gaining the whole world, and loſing his own ſoul.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next addreſs is to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentee; who (I know will tell me as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Biſhop did him,<note place="margin">Ambr. de digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Sacerd. c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> in the like caſe: <hi>Melius eſt mihi, aurum de ſacello invehere, quam tantum ſacerdotium per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere: quos amem ſolidos (ſi vivo) recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum me illico non diffido.</hi> I do it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, but 'tis better for me to draw Gold out of my Purſe, than loſe ſo great a Biſhoprick. I doubt not but to get my money back again, if I live. But pray conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. You carry about you a very earthy mind, your care will be to gain Shillings not Souls: your mind is more at the Barn than the Church. This is to be that hateful thing to God and man, a ſecular Prieſt. This is not to be the Preacher, but Fool of the Goſpel:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.</note> that will rejoyce in his Goods laid up for many days. Satan prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Chriſt all the Kingdoms of the world which he refuſed: but you would have taken. Is this to be a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt or of <hi>Judas?</hi> you will bid your people leave the world, that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:93734:72"/>you may take it: and adviſe them to ſecure Heaven that you may ſecure Earth. They muſt ſet their affections on things above, that you may graſp all below. Thus your Patron may commend you to the people; but your conſcience will condemn you to God; and then <hi>Caro dominatur populis</hi> (as the ſame Father ſpeaks) <hi>anima ſervit Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. ib.</note> your fleſh governs the people, and your Spirit is governed by the Devil. You enter Chriſts harveſt, <hi>tanquam ad auream meſſem,</hi> as if 'twere a harveſt of Gold not grace. Your care will be more to ſerve your Purſe, than ſave your People. 'Tis well if they be rich in ſaith, but you are reſolved to be rich in money, which looks like ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Bag rather than the Altar. In this Bargain ſays the ſame Father,<note place="margin">Ib.</note> 
               <hi>quod dedit aurum fuit, quod perdidit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima fuit.</hi> He parted with his Gold and loſt his Soul; but got nothing: for ſays he, <hi>aurum dans perdidiſli &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſanctam non acquiſiviſti.</hi> But why would you enter by ſin? could not God find a way for your ſubſiſtence without it?
<hi>ſides famem non formidat,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Hierom;</hi> faith fears not hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and without faith you can't be
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:93734:72"/>ſaved. 'Tis lawful to contrive ways of living, but not ways of ſinning.</p>
            <p>The ancients called it <hi>gratiam ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> the favour of the holy Ghoſt, by which men are called into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry: and every Miniſter may write himſelf <hi>Gratia Dei Paſtor M. N.</hi> Hence this great Biſhop argues, you ought to give nothing for it: becauſe <hi>Pro eo quod gratis datur, ideo gratia vocitatur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. ib.</note> 'Tis called grace in regard it comes <hi>gratis.</hi> And 'tis true what he ſays elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,<note place="margin">Id. In Luc. c.
<hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non enim pretio taxatur gratia Dei.</hi> Gods grace is not to be rated by money. Will you read the judgment of that pious Biſhop
<hi>Jer. Tayler</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning your Entrance.<note place="margin">Ductor dub. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> r. <hi>5.</hi> n. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> His intentions ſays he cannot be right, who by any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct arts doth enter: for that which doth not begin at God cannot be for God. <hi>Non enim ambitione vel pretio, ſed probatae vitae &amp; diſciplinarum teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio, ad honoris &amp; ſacerdotis inſignia oportet promoveri,</hi> ſaid the Emperor
<hi>Theodoſius.</hi> He therefore who Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacally enters, fixes his Eye and heart upon that which he values, to be worth Money: not on the ſpiritual employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment — he that comes into the Field with an Elephant cannot be ſuppoſed to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:93734:73"/>to hunt a Hare. The true reaſon why ſuch a one turn'd Prieſt, was becauſe he could reach no more profitable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Incumbent hath a very tickle hold that thus enters: for (as was ſuggeſted before) if any will diſcover he is both out and undone. In regard the Statute, not only makes the Church void: and ſo he loſes all his charges of Inſtitution, Induction, Firſt-fruits,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> but amerces him as alſo the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, in the double value of one years profit, of the Living thus enterd. Which 'tis probable may be more than he is worth. For the valuation is not to be according to the Kings Book, but what it can be let for, as Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> in his Expoſition on the Statute affirms:<note place="margin">31 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 6.</note> and ſo do all other Law-Books that I have ſeen. Add to this, that the Incumbent is for ever diſabled to hold that Living. And by the Canon-Law is incapacitated to obtain any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preferment whatſoever in the Church. Theſe Incumbents are the worſt ſort of Bandogs: and muſt be at every conſcious Perſons whiſtle. And ſuppoſe them compelled in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him as Witneſſes, he muſt bribe
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:93734:73"/>deep to make them forſwear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for his ſecurity. This State is ſo uneaſy, that I knew one to droop and die away with diſcontent, at the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and chargeableneſs of an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medler. May all men conſider they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe ſlavery rather than preferment; and ruin their worldly as well as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly joy by theſe courſes. And the Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioner may lawfully deny his Tythes, if he can prove the Simony: as it was reſolved in Sir <hi>John Howſe</hi> and
<hi>Wrights</hi> Caſe in <hi>Eaſter</hi> Term,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hob.</hi> 467.168.177.</note> 
               <hi>Jac.</hi> ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a thing is it, for ſuch an Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent to ſue for his profits.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is to conſider, he hath an Oath to ſwallow, and his Conſcience is very large if he can get it down. The ſubſtance of it was decreed in the firſt Council at <hi>Oxford</hi> under <hi>Stephen Langton, Anno Domini</hi> 1222, in theſe words, <hi>Quod propter praeſentationem il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, nec promiſerit, nec dederit aliquid praeſentanti; nec aliquam propter hoc ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit pactionem.</hi> That he gave nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed not only no Money, but nothing at all, nor entred into no Bargain; ſo that all Bonds and Contracts were to be ſworn againſt as well as Money. But the Oath that is now adminiſtred is in
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:93734:74"/>the 40<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Canon of thoſe publiſhed by the Convocation at <hi>London,</hi> 1. <hi>Jac. Anno Dommini</hi> 1603, in theſe words, <hi>I. M. N.</hi> do ſwear, that I have made no Simoniacal payment, Contract, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, directly or indirectly, by my ſelf or by any other to my knowledge, or with my conſent to any Perſon or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever; for or concerning the procuring and obtaining of this eccleſiaſtical dignity, place, preferment office or Living: nor will at any time hereafter, perform, or ſatisfie, any kind of payment, contract, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made by any other, without my knowledge or conſent: ſo help me God through Jeſus Chriſt. And is a Bond for Reſignation no Contract? and doth it not carry the force of a promiſe? And though it name no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, yet doth it not indirectly imply a Reſolution, to content the Patron, in what he ſhall demand? or be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. And is there any other reaſon of theſe Bonds, but to commit legal Simony? and to perjure without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of conſcience? This can be no leſs Simony, than if the Bond had been for Money: ſith the Patron might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to call for that if he pleaſed: and
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:93734:74"/>ſo may here too. But then, if he do call for it, all the world will conclude, (to uſe Sir <hi>Simon Degg</hi>'s own words) That the Incumbent muſt pay what the Patron will demand:<note place="margin">Degg. p. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> or elſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit the Bond, or loſe the Living: and ſo be undone,<note place="margin">Officiperda.</note> and a <hi>Jack</hi> — out of Office. I know nothing therefore, can excuſe ſuch a man from perjury, but the myſtery of Jeſuitiſme. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent ſhould alſo mind, that the words (Simoniacal payment, Contract or promiſe) are not ſtrictly to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, to the Statute-ſenſe. For theſe kind of Oaths, are elder than the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute by many ages: and the words of Canons, are to be underſtood canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and eccleſiaſtical Convocations, ſpeak in eccleſiaſtical ſenſe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are to be taken largely, for ſuch compact as the Canons deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to be Symoniacal. And the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons exclude <hi>aliquam propter hoc pactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem;</hi> any kind of Contract whatſoever in conſideration of a Preſentation: ſo that Bonds for Reſidence; or for not holding two Livings, might be Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny within the Canon, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within this Oath: though they are good deſigns, and correſpond with
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:93734:75"/>our good Laws, and bind men to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what was their duty before. And yet ſuppoſing thoſe Bonds law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, they will no more juſtify Bonds for Reſignations, than a Bond for good behaviour, can juſtify a Bond to ſet the Town on fire: there being no Law nor honeſty in Bonds for prophane Reſignation, but enough to require our good a bearing: which is ſufficient to evince, that Sir <hi>Simon Degge</hi> did ill couple Bonds for preferment of a Son: with Bonds to avoid Pluralities, or non-Reſidence, which were forbidden by the Canon, and the Laws of this Land. However I aſſure my ſelf, that Patrons which are for Bonds of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, will never be for Bonds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Non-Reſidence or Pluralities: ſince Non-Reſidents and Pluraliſts are their uſual Cuſtomers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Such Incumbent may conſider himſelf of little uſe to the Church in which he is: for we have already ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Patron and all others, that are conſcious of his Simony muſt deſpiſe him as a perjur'd wretch. How can he bleſs (ſays a Father) that is accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? or ſanctify others that is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unholy? or communicate Chriſts
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:93734:75"/>body, that is not of his body?<note place="margin">Diſt. <hi>81.</hi> c. Maximianus.</note> So ſays the law
<hi>Qui ſancti non ſunt, ſancta tractare non poſſunt.</hi> He cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their vices, leſt they ſhould thereby be provoked to tell the truth, and out the Reprover. And he muſt be of the Patrons Religion, againſt the 39 Articles, or any part of them as they require. Nor can he ſtand for the honour and freedome of any Church, that is thus intangled. But two things render his condition yet worſe, 1. He is not in the Church as a Guide or Ruler, for his Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Inſtitution, Induction, are all void. Simony enervates the vertue of all Seals. <hi>Non ſuſcepiſti</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>quia gratuitò eam non rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſti.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb de dig. ſacerd. c.
<hi>5.</hi>
               </note> And again, <hi>Quod dedit pecunia fuit, quod accepit lepra fuit.</hi> He gave Money and received Leproſy: that is, nothing but the guilt of ſin. For 'tis a Maxime, <hi>Nulli ex culpâ lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum;</hi> none may be a gainer by his crimes. In Ordination <hi>Leo</hi> obſerves, we get not the Spirit of God, but a Lying Spirit. <hi>Si ſpiritus verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis gratis accipitur, proculdubio ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus mendacii eſſe convincitur, qui non gratis accipitur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>q.</hi> 1.
<hi>gratia.</hi>
               </note> Nay they are not
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:93734:76"/>Prieſts, nor is any thing conveyed: and ſo ſays <hi>Greg. Mag. Quicundque ſtudet per dationem ſacrum ordinem accipere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. Idem.</note> 
               <hi>ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos non eſt.</hi> And again, <hi>Presbyter, ſi per pecuniam eccleſiam obtinuerit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. Idem.</note> 
               <hi>non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eccleſiâ privetur, ſed etiam ſacerdotii honore ſpolietur:</hi> ſo that this Church is void, and he ceaſes to be a Prieſt. Nor would they acknowledge his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings or ſervice to be acceptable or pure.<note place="margin">Hier. In Mat. c. <hi>1.</hi> v. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> So ſays St.
<hi>Hierom, Panem pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutum offerunt quantum ad ſe, qui ad altare indignè accedunt; quique dato munere ſacerdotium praeſumunt.</hi> As to themſelves, they offer polluted bread. Thus the Council of
<hi>Roan;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dec. <hi>7.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> Sanctitum.</note> if any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>turpis lucri gratiâ dejiciatur a clero &amp; alienus exiſtat a regula.</hi> He is outed as irregular, and his Prieſtly acts are ſuch <hi>Quae fieri non debent, ſed fact a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent;</hi> good to others not to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>To conclude, all the Canons and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Conſtitutions go the ſame way, making all things void, ſuch a Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt can do: at leaſt as to himſelf. Hence the Caſuiſts rule,<note place="margin">Sa aphor. Sim. n.
<hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Collatio bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficii Simoniaca nulla eſt,</hi> 'tis a meer nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to preſent by Simony. We muſt ſay of him, as <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Simon Magus,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:93734:76"/>Thou haſt no part, nor lot in this matter,</hi> Act. 8. He is a Uſurper of that holy office by his Criminal Entry.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſtands <hi>ipſo facto</hi> Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate,<note place="margin">Navar. l. c. n. <hi>111.</hi>
               </note> both from his Orders, his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and the Catholick Church. <hi>In eccleſiâ Dei eos conſortium habere non poſſe, qui ſancti Spiritus gratiam nundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentur,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. in Luc. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> they can't hold Church-Communion that trade with the grace of God's Spirit. He that gets any Benefice or Miniſtry, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Dec. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimur.</note> 
               <hi>Ex eodem tempore ſe noverit ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematis opprobrio condemnatum, atque a participatione corporis &amp; ſanguinis domini alienum.</hi> And what comfort can he take in his Calling that is thus intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Nullities and Curſes; and prejudiced by his ſins?</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Primitive Church made no Canons againſt Patrons, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in that age there was no ſuch thing: but Election and Ordination brought the Clergy into their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Offices and Profits. And hence the Canons militate againſt Ordainers and Ordained, Electors and Elected; but the Reaſon is the ſame. The Patron being the ſole Elector, and ſhares with the Biſhop in filling the Church; and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:93734:77"/>here money qualifies for the Miniſtry, the ſpiritual Office is purchaſed, and the grace of God is bought and ſold, as then.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Since Chriſtians are not Stoicks, to think all ſin equal; the Incumbent will do well to conſider, in what rank, the moſt pious Chriſtians placed Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.<note place="margin">Ambr. de dig. Sacerd. c.
<hi>5.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calls it <hi>mortale vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatis is virus,</hi> the deadly poiſon of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs. Pope <hi>Paſchal</hi> calls them <hi>primos &amp; praecipuos haereticos, ab omnibus ſidelibus reſpuendos;</hi> the firſt and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hereticks, to be rejected by all the faithful — again all crimes compared to Simoniacal hereſy,<note place="margin">Dec. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>7.</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> 
               <hi>quaſi pro nihilo reputantur,</hi> are accounted nothing. <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſius</hi> ſaid the
<hi>Macedonian</hi> hereſy was more tolerable: for that made the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt Gods ſervant, but this makes him mans Slave, or his Beaſt to be bought or ſold at his pleaſure.<note place="margin">Ep. Synod.</note> Yea, he thinks it equal to the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Aequaliter peccantes his qui blaſphemaverint, dicentes; Chriſtum in Beelzebub ejicere daemonia;</hi> and adds, that 'tis like the crime of the Traytor
<hi>Judas,</hi> that ſold his Chriſt to the <hi>Jews,</hi> his Murderers.
<hi>Perpetua mulctatur dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione</hi> ſays <hi>Gregory,</hi> and
<hi>Nazi.</hi> ſays (as
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:93734:77"/>
               <hi>Gratian</hi> recites him) <hi>Nam Spiritus ſancti donum pretio comparari, quid aliud eſt quam Capitale crimen?</hi> And St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> again, <hi>Illum conſtat execrabile Chriſto perpetraſſe flagitium,</hi> 'tis a wickedneſs execrable to Chriſt. And hence again thoſe pious men in the Council of <hi>Meaux</hi> in moſt fervent manner cry out, <hi>Cavendum eſt &amp; ſummopere ſtudendum</hi> &amp;c. We muſt beware and endeavour by all might and main. And by the merits of Chriſts bloud muſt forbid, to all Biſhops and Kings, and all higher powers, and all Cheriſhers, Electors,<note place="margin">Grat. <hi>1.</hi> q.
<hi>7.</hi> Et mox.</note> Conſenters and Ordainers to any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical dignity; that none may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any place by Simoniacal hereſy, by himſelf or any Promoter, with any Service, Craft, Promiſe, Commodity or Gift whatſoever. By which we may ſee the zeal of godly men, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirminate that crime, we contrive to bring in. 'Tis perverſeneſs in our judgments, if we reckon that a ſmall thing, which they eſteemed heavier than a Milſtone, and St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely condemned, and for a taſte of our own Church, ſhe hath clos'd with the Primitive in her reſentments of it; for ſhe calls it, the deteſtable Sin of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony;
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:93734:78"/>and ſays buying and ſelling Spiritual and Ecceſiaſtical Functions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 1. <hi>Jac.</hi>
1603. <hi>can.</hi> 40.</note> Offices, Promotions, Dignities and Livings, is execrable before God; I am afraid, he will prove a Baſtard Son, that thinks otherwiſe. Nor is there any Sect, that eſpouſes the Simoniacal cauſe among the many bad cauſes owned in the world.</p>
            <p n="6">6 This Incumbent's condition is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry miſerable in the world;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7.</note> for 1. He is under a very illname. 'Tis his duty to endeavour a good report of thoſe that are without, but he hath a bad one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that are within. If <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> be right, that <hi>a good name is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than great Riches;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.1.</note> he makes a bad bargain, that parts with his Money for a bad one. <hi>Crudelis eſt qui famam negligit,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Aug.</hi> but what is he that <hi>famam deſtruit?</hi> ruins his good name? To have a good Conſcience is moſt neceſſary to his ſalvation, but to have a good name is moſt neceſſary to his vocation.
'Tis no good Character of a Divine, to be reputed ſhameleſs. <hi>Contemptu famae contemnuntur &amp; virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> (ſays one) Fame can't be deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but virtue is caſt off with it, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:93734:78"/>by ſo doing, men fit themſelves for farther villanies.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Liberiùs peccant, cum pudor omnis abeſt.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>A bluſhful countenance is a kind of traſh to an over fleet Villain. A grave Philoſopher aſures us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. they have very impure ſouls that deſire to be much ſpoken of for their great wickedneſs, rather than <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, than ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from evil to live obſcurely. He muſt expect to be eſteemed of no reputation, that hath no other inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for the Miniſtry, but a Bag of Money under his arm.
2. His Bonds given (as his beſt qualification) are ſuable at Law; ſo that he muſt quit his Living, compound with his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, or pay it with charges.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt.</hi> 3. <hi>f.</hi> 154.</note> This was adjudged ſays <hi>Coke</hi> in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pleas <hi>Paſche Eliz.</hi> 40.
<hi>rot.</hi> 1745, in <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Oldbury</hi>'s caſe. The Statute made nine years before, doth not vacate the Bond unleſs he plead a Simoniacal Contract; which is a very husbandly way to vacate the Living; but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful whether it would void the Bond at
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:93734:79"/>laſt. 3. It will blaſt his fortunes in marriage, for who will beſtow any thing better than an <hi>Abigail,</hi> on him that is but Tenent by curteſie; and is blown away by one breath of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons mouth out of all he hath. If the Incumbent conceals it when askt, he cheats the Father-in-Law; if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it, the bargain is broken. Nor is his credit better, for who will lend him any conſiderable ſumm (how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate ſoever his neceſſities be) that knows him indebted in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Marks, or out of his Living? So that this kind of Simony is a
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> utter undoing. Is his Purſe ſo big as to talk of a Purchaſe? but firſt (ſays the Patron) let him diſcharge my Bond: and the fuller he is thought to be, the greater is the Demand; ſo that he hath the pains, and the Patron the profit of his good husbandry. And who will marry ſuch an Incumbents Daughter, whoſe Father may ſoon appear ſcandalous and ſo ſhame him; and out of all, and ſo lye upon him? Our gentle Mother
<hi>Academia</hi> bluſhes to ſee her Sons ſo bad Logicians, as not to find this fallacy, or diſtinguiſh themſelves out of theſe Bonds.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:93734:79"/>But is it not better to have a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in this manner,<note place="margin">Obj.</note> than none at all?</p>
            <p>'Tis better be idle than rob or ſteal,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> and to follow no trade than a ſinful one; but much better with <hi>Marlorat</hi> to work with a Spade in a Town-Ditch than either.
2. 'Tis better to provide for the publick ſafety of the Church of Chriſt than our own. Chriſt left Heaven to do it ſervice, and why can't we a Living? All refuſing theſe Simoniacal Contracts, the Condition of all is better'd by it. 3. You will loſe nothing by it, but appear the more conſcientious and fitting man for the Miniſtry. 4. The Money paid to enter by ſin, would maintain you till an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance be offer'd without ſin. 5.
'Tis better to have a bad Living with a good conſcience, than a good Living with a bad one. 'Tis more reaſonable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Lord hath no need of us, than to intrude without a call.<note place="margin">Dec. de Sim. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> q. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Greg. Mag.</hi> tells <hi>Siagrius, Is qui invitatus renuet, quaeſitus refugit; ſacris altaribus eſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movendus: Qui ultro ambit, vel impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunè ſe ingerit, eſt proculdubio repellendus,</hi> This was the Primitive modeſty, ſome feigning themſelves Fools, ſome deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:93734:80"/>themſelves to be Chriſtians. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers refuſing to be baptized. Others hiding themſelves to avoid their Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. <hi>Greg. Nazianzen</hi> after he was choſen Patriarch of
<hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual then to the beſt preferment in the world) by an Oecumenical Council; obſerving ſome few <hi>Egyptian</hi> Biſhops againſt him,<note place="margin">Hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>7.</hi> c.
<hi>7.</hi>
               </note> refuſed the Patriarchate (as <hi>Sozomen</hi> and many others affirm.) <hi>Priſci viri ſanctique homines difficilius ad Pontificatum vocabantur, quam nunc ex alio amoventur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sylv. ep.
<hi>25.</hi> Cyp. to. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> ſays <hi>Aeneas Sylvius.</hi> And Holy <hi>Cyprian</hi> aſſures us, <hi>Cornelius vim paſſus eſt, ut epiſcopatum coactus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciperet, Cornelius</hi> was forced into the Popedome by plain violence. <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Emiſſenus</hi> that great light of the Church, was earneſtly ſolicited to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Patriarchate of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> by the Synod of <hi>Antioch;</hi> or at leaſt by <hi>Euſebius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. hiſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> but he refuſed it: as he had fled before to <hi>Alexandria</hi> from
<hi>Antioch</hi> to avoid that Patriarchal See. <hi>Pontius</hi> ſhews with what unwillingneſs holy <hi>Cyprian</hi> was call'd forth to the Primacy of
<hi>Carthage.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pontius in vit. Cypr.</note>
               <hi>Syneſius</hi> that acute Divine and Philoſopher, declared in a Letter to his Brother, that he believed not
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:93734:80"/>the Reſurrection, on purpoſe to avoid the Biſhoprick of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> which yet could not defend him.
<hi>Evagrius</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever took him at his word, and hath left him on Record as an Infidel to the Reſurrection, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Evagrius l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> being (in his opinion) not ſo much as willing to ſeem to believe it. So <hi>Euſebius Pamphili,</hi> urged by the Common ſhout of the City of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and ſolicited by <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Letters, upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Synod at <hi>Antioch:</hi> yet conſtantly refuſed the Patriarchal See. The Emperor hearing him alledge, that it was againſt the Decree of the Fathers to remove from a leſs to a greater or other Dioceſs, commended his ſelf-denial;<note place="margin">Sozom. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Nyſſen</hi> gives us a fair account of that man of wonders <hi>Gregorius Thaumaturgus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nyſſen in vit. Greg. Thaumat.</note> his flight into the Wilderneſs to eſcape the Chair of <hi>Naeo-Caeſarea;</hi> yet at length was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought back to it by the prayers and contrivance of <hi>Phedimus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Turon. l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Jo. Diac. l.
<hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>39, 40.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the great, after he was choſen by the Clergy and People of <hi>Rome</hi> to the Papal dignity, wrote earneſtly to <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricius</hi> then Emperor to refuſe his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, of what the Electors had
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:93734:81"/>done, that he might eſcape ſo weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a charge; as <hi>Gregory Turonenſis</hi> and <hi>Joh. Diaconus</hi> report it.</p>
            <p>The Rule then was <hi>Quaeratur Cogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiph. ep. ad. Joh. Hieroſ.</note> his Neighbour Biſhops oft caught, ordained, and reſtored ſeveral Presbyters that fled from him, to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape cape holy Orders. And this was the Imperial Decree, that whoever was ambitious of holy Orders,<note place="margin">Col. l. <hi>1.</hi> tit.
<hi>3.</hi> de epiſ. &amp; cler. c. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> ſhould not be received. This Sentence executed, would abate the number of Simoniſts, and make a thin Church amongſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts and Non-conformiſts too: however, it may ſerve to raiſe a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful bluſh on the face of ſuch as pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe their way of Entry. 6. The world will conclude, there is no merit where the entrance is attempted by Money. 7. By ſuch a Preferment you are more intangled than advanced; and in a year or two (when the Patrons will and pleaſure is) may be as far to ſeek as ever. 8. By the Canons of the Church, Simoniacal Entrance makes you uncapable of any Eccleſiaſtical promotion for ever. <hi>Pius</hi> the 5th his Bull ſpeaks not ſo much, the ſenſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> as the Catholick Church.
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:93734:81"/>The Canons, Civil Law, and Decretals, all affirming depoſition. <hi>Cum omni fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducia clamo, Qui per Simoniam ordinatus eſt alienus eſt a ſacerdotio:</hi> adding this reaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>7.</hi> Si quis omnem. <hi>1.</hi> q.
<hi>2.</hi> Si quis dator.</note> 
               <hi>neque enim venalis eſt gratia ſpiritius:</hi> you get no more than <hi>Simon Magus</hi> by it, who was extirminated for ever. <hi>Perpetua mulctetur damnatione,</hi> ſays
<hi>Greg.</hi> And becauſe Simony vacates all Seals, and conveys no right, the Caſuiſts affirm you are bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to reſign whatever is ſo gotten, and to make Reſtitution of what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits you have received. If you think theſe Canons void in Law, yet they are not in Conſcience: nor in Law neither, as it ſeems by the Statute made 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi>
19. which affirms all Canons not contrariant, nor repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Laws, Statutes and Cuſtoms of the Realm; nor to the damage or hurt of the King's Prerogative Royal, ſhall be now ſtill executed. This is the Statute of the ſubmiſſion of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and was the rule they were to walk by. Nor is the matter altered in this Statute of Simony, 31 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 6, for the fourth Paragraph provides, that the Act ſhould not reſtrain any cenſures Eccleſiaſtical, but that the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:93734:82"/>Ordinary might execute them; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the making of the ſaid Act, upon which <hi>Degge</hi> delivers his opinion, that corrupt Patrons,<note place="margin">Parſons Coun. p. <hi>2.</hi> c.
<hi>5.</hi>
               </note> who take Bonds for Reſignation, without any reaſonable cauſe apparent, may be called to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count before the Ordinary,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and cenſured if occaſion be: and doubtleſs ſo may the Incumbent too. Some ſay the Statute of 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 19, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired as temporary; and indeed ſo it was deſigned, provided a body of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons had been pickt our of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Councils, to have been ratified by ſome ſubſequent act, but that was not done, and probably never will; and therefore (under correction) we may ſay, it is in force ſtill.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſuch an Incumbent ought to conſider, he is ſelf-called, and not called of God. Chriſt the firſt Prieſt of the Chriſtian Church, would not ſtir till his father had ſent him. Nor did any Apoſtle enter the office but as Chriſt ſent them. <hi>John</hi>
20.21. <hi>As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you.</hi> Nor is there any in that office that taketh this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was; <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. He that acts without a warrant, will
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:93734:82"/>not be born out in what he doth. To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage without command hath received puniſhment, in ſucceſsful fights. If we will act without Commiſſion, we muſt do it without comfort too, expecting (as well we may) to hear that reproachful <hi>Nippe,</hi> who required theſe things at thy hand? We forge the Broad Seal of Heaven, if we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon our Saviour's Embaſſy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Order. The Church is bid to <hi>pray the Lord of the Harveſt, to ſend forth able Labourers into his Harveſt. Matth.</hi> 9.38. And how can we expect wages except he ſets us on work? But theſe hire themſelves, and bear witneſs to themſelves of their own worth; artificial Paſtors made by their own contrivance. Like Baſtards they are Sons of their own fortunes; true <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae filii</hi> that no body elſe will father. And thus to enter (ſays <hi>Ameſius</hi>) is <hi>planè Diabolicum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſ. Conſe. l. <hi>4.</hi> c.
<hi>25.</hi> n. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> a meer promotion of the Devil; for (as he adds) <hi>officium curae animarum eſt ſpirituale Dei do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> —
<hi>&amp; proinde idem in genere &amp; ex na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turâ rei eſt, illud officium emere; cum eo quod fecit</hi> Simon, <hi>Act.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. n. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 8. 'Tis not doubted, but the right of calling is principally in Chriſt, but by way of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:93734:83"/>Delegation in the Biſhop, acting in the behalf of Chriſt by virtue of the Commiſſion granted to him,
<hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21. and in the Patron to whom the people muſt be ſuppoſed, to have delegated their power of electing, or rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting; which (when the duſt of contention that blinds mens eyes is laid) will appear as lawful as any Churches can elect Repreſentatives to appear for them in Synods: but then to purchaſe this delegated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Patron, is the fowleſt of all corruptions. We then enter <hi>injuſſi &amp; non vocati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>p.</hi>
227.</note> and therefore <hi>ipſos diaboli nuntios efficaciter convinci poſſe;</hi> ſays <hi>Hunnius</hi> from <hi>Luther,</hi> and ſhew our ſelves to be the Devils Meſſengers. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> tells us himſelf, he that hears one uncalled, doth hear <hi>Diabolum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraliter loquentem,</hi> a Devil incarnate preaching.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In. Luc.</hi> 12.42.</note> This Simoniack Call, is from <hi>Pluto</hi> the God of Hell and Wealth; and his Ambaſſadors they are. Hear how honeſt
<hi>Stella</hi> derides them, on thoſe words, <hi>Quem conſtituit domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſuper familiam. O quanti ſunt Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lati</hi> (ſays he) <hi>quos non conſtituit domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſed ipſi ſe conſtituerunt ſuâ ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, favoribus aut pecuniis;</hi> and thinks
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:93734:83"/>God permits them only for the peoples ſins, as a plague and curſe to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations. Then (ſays he) thou art called of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.6.
<hi>Iſ.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Quando ſine Tuâ ſolicitâ diligentiâ, dignitas Tibi offertur;</hi> and wonders any would be ſo bold as to purchaſe, what <hi>Moſes, Jeremiah</hi> and
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> refuſed and bewailed, and <hi>Jonah</hi> fled from. A man may ſatisfy his conſcience that he is called of God, when his own ſtrong and conſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations ſhall lead him to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry: and his Friends not only conſent but devote him that way, and his own abilities are not only ſufficient, but are better for that way than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And then that he be invited in by ſome Church or Patron, which is a Churches Repreſentative, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ordained and inſtituted by the Biſhop, whom Chriſt Commiſſioned to that purpoſe. But (ſays <hi>Stella</hi>) the Church ever pronounced him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy that thought himſelf worthy.</p>
            <p>Let us now conclude with this hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Obteſtation, to both Patrons and Preſentees; to remember, that ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial is a Goſpel grace, ſelf-ſeeking is a Goſpel diſgrace: by the firſt we can do no hurt, by the ſecond we ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:93734:84"/>do good. In this danger <hi>Alcibia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> will tell you, 'tis better <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to fly the danger, than eſcape at Tryal. A good conſcience cannot eaſily cloſe with ſuſpected wickedneſs, but much leſs when 'tis detected. I know your hearts are hardened by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of ſin, and you are hired by your profit to turn a deaf ear; yet I would be loath to make my Addreſſes to you, as the <hi>Cynick</hi> did to a dead Statue, only to learn to bear a Repulſe. I think I may confidently ſay, if this Doctrine be hid, 'tis hid to them that periſh; whom the God of this world hath blinded. If therefore you deſire to eſcape the Crime and Curſe of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> if you have any regard to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, any care for the Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church, any deſire for the ſafety and glory of your Countrey, any pity for your own ſouls, any ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs for your families, any aim at your own peace within, or at a good name from abroad, if you have any love for Learning, or Reward for vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or kindneſs for Modeſty, abhor theſe vile practiſes. The
<hi>Jews</hi> were thought to worſhip <hi>Bacchus,</hi> becauſe they had a Golden Vine in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:93734:84"/>and won't men think you worſhip
<hi>Plutus?</hi> that have brought the Bank thither. Silver ſhrines may very well become <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple, but more pure ſouls the Temple of Chriſt. Let the Prieſt have leave to purchaſe the Miniſtration, when the Deity is a Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf. But to give or take Money to worſhip the pure Jeſus, is more abſurd, than to offer Wine to the Nymphs and Water to
<hi>Bacchus;</hi> than to throw Bones to the Horſes, and Hay to the Dogs.</p>
            <p>Is it not more gallant in <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> to diſdain earthy mens proffers, than in poor-ſpirited <hi>Gehezi</hi> to run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them? Do holy men boaſt, Silver and Gold have we none; and are we ſuch ignoble minds, as to think we can't be ſaved without them? That Princes amaſs treaſures, is a ſign they are unhappy: Angels and glorified Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that injoy perfect bliſs refuſe it. Pots of Ointment, and rich Waſhes are the purchaſe of the deformed: a native beauty needs no paints nor fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. 'Twas a biting conceit of the Poets, that the Carcaſe of the Sheep that wore the Golden Fleece,<note place="margin">Diſt. <hi>88.</hi> c. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiatorem.</note> was good for nothing. And hence perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture came St.
<hi>Hierom</hi>'s advice, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiatorem
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:93734:85"/>Clericum</hi>—<hi>quaſi quandam pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem fuge. Leo</hi> in his Epiſtle to Biſhop <hi>Anatholius</hi> aſſures him, <hi>Virum Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum &amp; praecipuè Domini Sacerdotem, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut nullo errore implicari, ita nulla opum cupiditate violari oportet. Tert.</hi> reports that <hi>Enoch</hi> delivered it as his judgment,<note place="margin">Lib. De cultu faemin.</note> that Silver and Gold were <hi>ab angelis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis inventa.</hi> Had he ſaid the Simonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal uſe of them had been from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of the Devil, good men would have cloſed with the opinion. <hi>Athenagoras,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leg. pro Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianis.</note> as a man of the old Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian make, calls theſe covetous ſouls, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as leſs worth than their treaſures.<note place="margin">De Relig. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> The beſt
<hi>Lactantius</hi> can ſay of them is, <hi>Quibus rebus nemo melior, nemo juſtior fieri poteſt.</hi> No man was ever made more juſt or more upright by them. Hence he obſerves the moſt vertuous Heathens, <hi>abjecerunt omnia</hi>—<hi>ut ſolam nudamque virtutem, nudi expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs ſequerentur;</hi> rejected all their pelf, to render themſelves more ſleet in the purſuit of virtue. It ſeems the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers had a clearer apprehenſion of them than our droſſy ſouls, too deep immerſed in matter; for they held them to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as voluminous Gowns that hinder our walk; and ſo
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:93734:85"/>do <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mophilus</hi> ſpeaks.<note place="margin">V. Gal. edit. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcula. p.
<hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 'Tis ſtrange that a Chriſtian ſhould damn himſelf, to gain what theſe brave Heathens ſlight. 'Twas beyond my expectation, to hear <hi>Acoſta</hi> ſay ,<hi>Quizacoalt</hi> the God of Riches was the moſt honoured Idol amongſt the <hi>Cholutecas;</hi> yea in all
<hi>America:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acoſt l. <hi>5.</hi> c.
<hi>30.</hi>
               </note> but he confines it to the Merchants. Our Simoniſts being of the ſame trade, are not unlikely to joyn with them; yet 'tis an unaccountable madneſs, that a man ſhould run ſuch infinite hazards, for what can do him ſo little ſervice. Could he buy Heaven and Glory, the pardon of his ſins, the favour of God, the blood of Chriſt, or ranſome his ruin'd ſoul by it, 'twere the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable. But when it will not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe him an hours piece of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor a minutes continuance in this vale of miſery, when his time is come; but that with <hi>Judas</hi> he muſt caſt his unjuſt gain away in fearful deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſhut up his days in the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Clouds of vengeance. Sith his head muſt ake, though incircled with a Golden Diadem; his Foot rage with the Gout, though in a Golden Slipper; his heavy Heart muſt ſigh, <hi>bibit licèt
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:93734:86"/>Gemmas,</hi> though he drink Cordials of Pearl; and cannot ſleep though he ſinks in Down;<note place="margin">Cypr. l.
<hi>1.</hi> ep <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> as the eloquent Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of <hi>Carthage</hi> hath it: who can excuſe them from acting worſe than children, that beat out their ſtrength in purſuing Butterflies? ſince children loſe but their labour: but theſe loſe Chriſt, Heaven, Glory, Soul, Body and all Comfort eternally by it. To be poor at worſt, is but an afflicting ſtate; but to be Simoniacal is a damning State. By ſuch luckleſs Acqueſts, men add more guilt to their conſciences, than Gold to their Purſes. How lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally do theſe unhappy ſouls conſtrue and apply the Satyriſt's ironical ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</p>
            <q>Vende animam lucro —<note place="margin">Perſ. Sat.
<hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
            </q>
            <p>but why may he not ſell his ſoul, that thinks it lawful to ſell his God? and yet ſure, he makes but a bad Title, for the Purchaſer never gets him.</p>
            <p>But ſtay, we are ſlipt into an Ocean of diſcourſe, by following the ſtrong ſtream of Simony, into the bottomleſs Sea of Avarice: and in truth there it begins, and there it ends. The Root
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:93734:86"/>of all evil is the Root of this too; and
'twill be hard to deſtroy theſe profane branches, without plucking up the Root. For (as <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi> obſerved) reckoning up the puniſhment of Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; <hi>privatur Sacerdotio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Invent. lib.
<hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> in fino.</note> 
               <hi>dignitate ac praefectura dejicitur, infamis habetur, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſque aliis afficitur probris;</hi> at length adds, <hi>Tanti criminis ſola eſt avaritia pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens. Timon</hi> obſerves, that covetous that covetous deſires are the Elements out of which men may ſpell all ſorts of evil: and have compoſed this fowl Monſter. Whoever can make the beſt aſſault upon Avarice, will be the moſt fortunate man, in the ſuppreſſion of this moſt inſolent crime. It hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been too hard for all the moral attaques of God and Man; of the Old Teſtament and the New, of Prophets and Apoſtles, of Councils and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of Canons and Statutes, of Conformiſts and Non-Conformiſts. As diſeas'd Bodies have loſt their true Guſto, ſo have theſe Covetous Souls loſt the ſenſe of true praiſe, and are as difficult to be reclaimed, as men perfectly ſtupid, are to be taught. But we may well pity them,<note place="margin">Sen. ep. ad Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. <hi>168.</hi>
               </note> for as
<hi>Seneca</hi> often notes, <hi>In nullum Avarus bonus
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:93734:87"/>eſt, in ſe peſſimus,</hi> he is kind to none, but moſt unkind to himſelf; loading his Soul with ſins, his Name with ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, and his heart with cares. Yet ſince he is alſo a ſhame to his Church and Country, we will riſe up, and call that Senate bleſſed, that ſhall conſider this ſin as the Nations great Grievance, Religions ſcandal, the Churches da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and every private mans injury, who himſelf, his Children or Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may hereafter be qualified for Church-preferments: and ſhall accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly endeavour to perfect bleſt <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> deſign, by making all Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions void and forfeited, that ſhall be clogged with any gifts, payments, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Bonds of any ſort, Covenants, or other Inſtruments whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Since the Patrons duty is no more than to ſearch out, and his right to no more than to preſent a learned and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Guide to the People, to lead them the ſtraight way to Heaven. The Laws of the Land are, or may be made ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to curb all Exorbitancies of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent, without the Patrons By-Laws; which are and will always be made to his private, againſt the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick benefit. May they alſo farther
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:93734:87"/>provide (according to the ancient Law) that no ſales of Advowſons may be good, unleſs they are made in Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimple. By which, theſe ſubtile Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders will be forced upon a new ſtrain of Invention to cheat the world; and a poor conſcientious, modeſt and grave Divine, may ſtand as fair for prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as a Golden Aſs. Worldly ſouls fear men more than God, and Laws more than Goſpel: being led by ſenſe rather than faith.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.14.</note> The Scriptures ſhew that the careleſs neglected, but the Covetous derided Chriſt; and much more will they the cleareſt products of Reaſon and Religion: and therefore we call for the ſcourge of Laws, which are moſt proper for the Fools backs, that can't be perſwaded by the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Arguments: to which therefore I leave them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:93734:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>APologies are never excuſable, but where there are errors real or belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and here they are too viſible to need an Aſteric: the Authors diſtance from the Preſs hath given ſecurity to ſome Erratas to paſs uncontrouled; and many Marginal Citations ſtand awry, ſometimes advanced too high, and at other times depreſſed too low, which will need the ingenuity of a kind Reader to rectify: to whom the Author will hold himſelf a Debter for his pains, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no farther trouble on him, but to add theſe few words to Page</hi> 84. The right of the Crown to the firſt Fruits and Tenths in <hi>England,</hi> accrues from a joint conſent of the whole Church, by an Inſtrument paſſed in full Convocation in the reign of
<hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>A. D.</hi> 1534,<note place="margin">Godwin. Hiſt. of Hen.
<hi>8.</hi>
               </note> to transfer the ſame; which were reſigned to the Church again, after twenty years poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Godw. in vit. Mar.</note> 
               <hi>A. D.</hi> 1554, as judged unlawful for her to hold: yet the emptineſs of her Exchequer cauſed her to reſeize them not long after, for ſupply of preſent wants. Since which time they have continued in the Crown without interruption; wants being as eaſy to be pretended now as ever, and can never fail to a Covetous mind.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
